<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="transcription-omv-journal.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><!-- http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020001"><!-- Change @xml:id -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Narrative of Said Bin Habeeb, An Arab Inhabitant of Zanzibar</title><!-- Change -->
                <title type="alternate">Narrative of Said Bin Habeeb, An Arab Inhabitant of Zanzibar, 31 May 1860</title><!-- Change; note addition of date -->
				<author>Said Bin Habeeb</author>
                <author>[Bombay] Government</author><!-- Change -->
                <principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
                <respStmt xml:id="AM">
                    <name>Anne Martin</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
				<respStmt xml:id="HB">
                    <name>Heather F. Ball</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AW">
                    <name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
                <publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date><!-- Change if necessary -->
                <idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_020001</idno><!-- Change -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr>
						<title>The Transactions of the Bomaby Geographical Society from May 1858 to May 1860</title>
						<editor>Secretary, Bomaby Geographical Society</editor>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="vol">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="pages">146-48</biblScope>
							<!-- Add? -->
							<pubPlace>Bombay</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Smith, Taylor, &amp; Co.</publisher>
							<date>1860</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
                    <title>Narrative of Said Bin Habeeb, An Arab Inhabitant of Zanzibar</title><!-- Change -->
					<author xml:id="SBH">Said Bin Habeeb</author><!-- Change -->
                	<author xml:id="BG">[Bombay] Government</author><!-- Change -->
                    <date type="composition" when="1860-05-31">31 May 1860</date><!-- Change, including attributes -->
                    <placeName type="focusRegion">East and Central Africa</placeName><!-- Change -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
				<!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry --> 
				<!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
			<!-- Change @when, @who, and work description below. -->
			<!-- Note that @who initials are taken from <respStmt> above -->
			<!-- Add new <change> elements below as needed. -->
			<!-- Note that the most recent <change> should always be placed first, at the top -->
            <change when="2018-01-31" who="#AW">OCR Conversion and TEI encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
       	<body n="white"><!-- Change; this is the color of the MS page; value can be any color -->
			<div rend="black" hand="BG"><!-- Change; this is the color of the writing; only use auto-suggested values -->

	<pb facs="liv_020001_0001" n="0001"/><!-- Change and repeat as necessary. Always indent <pb>, as here. -->
<head><seg rend="smallcaps">A<seg rend="small">RT</seg>.  IX.&#8212;NARRATIVE OF SAID BIN HABEEB, AN ARAB INHABITANT OF ZANZIBAR.</seg><space extent="3" unit="chars"/><seg rend="italic">Contributed by</seg> <seg rend="smallcaps">G<seg rend="small">OVERNMENT.</seg></seg></head>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="half-line center"/>
<lb/><p rend="center"><seg rend="small center">Read before the Society by the Secretary on the 31at May 1860.</seg></p>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="half-line center"/>
<lb/><p>I left Zanzibar to travel in the interior of Africa about sixteen years ago. I went partly to trade in ivory, and partly  for  the  purpose of visiting unexplored regions of that great country. I first  travelled  to Ugiji on the shore of the great lake of Tanganika. I then  crossed  the lake, and went twenty-seven days' journey down its western_ coast by boat to Umaroongoo, which is situated near the south  end  of  the lake. A broad river, called the Maroongoo, flows into tJ;ie lake near  this place. From  Umaroongoo,  I  travelled south,  and visited  the  country of a powerful Chief whose title is 'the Casembe.' I first went seven days journey to Peto, thence seven days to Karembo Makoonga ; in  three days more to Karoongwesi, and thence in three days to Roonda, a large town, where the Casembe resides, Roonda is situated ori th"e banks of a large river called the Ruapoora,-the stream flows North towards. the Tanganika lake. The t.:asembe is a Negro, by  name Sultan  Chareka. The people are armed with muskets. There are plenty  of sheep, goats, and poultry procurable at Roonda, but no horses, homed cattle,  or camels. The markets of Roonda are well supplied with meat, fish, grain, and vegetables. There is no money : Venetian beads form the circulating medium. The  people appear  comfortable  and  contented,  the  country is everywhere  cultivated,  and  the  inhabitants  are  numerous.  There are no stone buildings,-all the  houses  are  constructed  of  wood  or mud, with roofs of grass or leaves.  The  Casembe  governs  with mildness and justice,  and  the  roads  are  quite  safe  for  travellers. After residing·for some time at Roonda,  I  went  a journey of twenty· five days to the great copper-mines ; they are situated to the west of Roonda, and the country all forms part of the dominions of  the Casembe; it is well peopled and cultivated. The copper-mines are situated in a large range of mountains ; a great many people are employed at them, and the copper i11 taken for sale all over the country. After

	<pb facs="liv_020001_0002" n="0002"/>
<fw>NARRATIVE OF SAID BIN HABEEB.</fw>
smelting, about seventy-firn pounds weight of copper are sold for four cubits of American sheeting ; iron is everywhere abundant, and the miners' tools are made from iron procured in the  neighbourhood.  A large town called Katanza is situated near the copper-mines,  it  contains a greater population than Roonda. The bazars at Katanza are well supplied with rice, Indian corn, jowarree, bajree, vegetables of various sorts ; sheep and goats are plentiful; cotton is abundant,  and  is made into cloth in the country. There  are  no  horses  or  horned  cattle. Around Katanza, the country is generally populous, and the land well cultivated; but there are also extensive forests and mountains abounding in lions, elephants, and other wild animals. From the copper-mines, or "Masden Safr," it is a journey of  three  days  to Waramba,  the country of an independent chief. The town  of  Katanza  and  the copper-mines are situated in the dominions of a  chit'f,  whose  title is 'Manene.'  A large river, called the Rafira, flows past Katauza, and  joins  the Ruapoora   to   the   North.   I   remained    two    months    at   Katanza; it is a quiet peaceable place,  with  very  few  robbers :  the  people always treated  me  in  a  friendly  manner,  and  goods  of  all  kinds were abundant.  In  payment  of purchases  in  the  markets,   you  break a few beads off a string, and give them  in  exchange.  There  is  no coined money. I  suffered but  little inconvenience from  my  ignorance of the languages of the various countries through which I  passed, because the Africans, who accompanied me from Zanzibar, acquired these languages with surprising rapidity, and always made themselves understood.</p>
<lb/><p>From Katanza, I° travelled in a westerly direction, and, after two months,  reached  a country  called Boira.    The country  through  which I passed is divided into petty states, the chiefs treat travellers well, but
it is necessary to stay amongst them and gain their goodwill.  The country was generally thickly peopled, and grain, fowls, sheep, aml vegetables, always procurable in abundance.</p>
<lb/><p>From Boira, I went a journey of seventeen days to "Warengeh :" the people of this country are the most barbarous I met with during all my travels; they go entirely naked, and pull out all their upper front teeth. From Warengeh, I travelled in two months to a country called Ugengeh, not far from the river  Zambesi;  the chief ruler of this country  is named " 1\lakororo :" the people are a handsome race, many are quite fair with long hair fl.owing over_ the neck, others are as black as negroes. In

	<pb facs="liv_020001_0003" n="0003"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">148</seg>	<seg rend="center">NARRATIVE   OF   SAID   BIN   HABEEB.</seg></fw>
Ugengeh, the people possess abundance of homed cattle, horses, sheep, and goats : they travel about, and carry on a considerable trade. From Ugengeh, I went in thirty days' journey through  a fine rich country  to Lui : there is very little forest in this part ; cattle, sheep, goats, and poultry are everywhere abundant. I reached the city of Loanda, on the shore of the great ocean in eighty-days' journey  from  Lui.  I  remained at Loanda twenty-five days, and then returned into  the  interior.  I trnelled about in various directions, trading  in ivory,  and  visited  the city of Loanda three times. I resided at  various  towns in the interior; and, at length, having been absent from my own country for so many years, I resolved to return to Zanzibar. I travelled  east  until I  reached the river Zambesi, and then proceeded north until I reached the  great lake Nyassa. I travelled seventeen days along the shore of the lake towards its northern end, in order to cross it at a  narrow  point,  and I then returned to the east coast through the country of the Miyan and Magindo tribes. The lake of Nyassa is of vast extent,  a large frigate could manreuvre on it. The country all around is very  rich ;  cotton grows  everywhere  in  great  abundance,  and  the  natives  weave   it into cloth.</p>
<p>During all my journeys,  I  met  with  hospitality  and  friendship,  and I intend returning to the interior of Africa after arranging my  affairs here. I met Dr. Livingstone near the Zambesi, and conveyed letters for him to Loanda. I have never written down anything I observed  during my travels, because Arabs take no interest in the discovery of foreign countries, and do not care to hear of anything unconnected with the acquisition of riches.</p>

			</div>
		</body>	

    </text>
</TEI>
