<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- Next line points to online XSL; use red triangle button in oXygen when done to transform file and check encoding -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/omv-integrated.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020028"><!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>“Tippoo Tib”</title><!-- Title without date --><!-- Check https://onemorevoice.org/bibliography.html for "canonical" name. -->
				<title type="normalized">‘Tippoo Tib’</title><!-- If title surrounded by double quotations, then replace with single quotations here; otherwise remove -->
                <title type="alternative">“Tippoo Tib,” 17 May 1887</title><!-- Title, date -->
                <author>Anonymous</author><!-- First author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates) -->
                <author>Tippu Tip, 1832-1905</author><!-- Second author, etc.: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates); if no second author, remove this line -->
				<author role="first">Anonymous</author><!-- First author only: Surname, Forename -->
				<author role="first-normalized">Anonymous</author><!-- First author only: Forename Surname -->
				<author role="normalized">Tippu Tip</author><!-- Second author, etc.: Forename Surname; if no second author, remove this line -->
                <principal>Heather F. Ball</principal>
                <principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
				<!-- Only people involved in the actual transcription should be listed below; remove everyone else -->
                <respStmt xml:id="CM">
                    <name>Caitlin Matheis</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>Proofing</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AW">
                    <name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
                    <resp>Proofing</resp>
                    <resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>One More Voice</authority>
                <publisher>Livingstone Online</publisher>
                <pubPlace>University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_20028</idno><!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
				<!-- <ref> takes the name of the source used for original, e.g., Internet Archive -->
				<!-- @target = URL of source -->
				<ref target="https://www.gale.com/c/the-times-digital-archive">The Times Digital Archive</ref>
				<!-- Edit <availability> as relevant -->
	            <availability>
					<p>Critically-edited text copyright <hi rend="italic">One More Voice</hi>.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>

			<!-- Use this version of <sourceDesc> if published text; otherwise delete it -->
            <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr n="narrow"><!-- Default is journal/periodical article; if book section, change to <monogr n="book-section">; if columns are narrow, use <monogr n="narrow">; combinations also OK: <monogr n="book-section narrow"> -->
						<title>The Times</title><!-- Publication title: journal or book -->
						<!-- Author here used only for books -->
						<!-- Forename Surname-->
	                    <author></author>
						<editor></editor><!-- Editor (if known; otherwise leave blank -->
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="pages">5</biblScope><!-- Pages (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<pubPlace>London</pubPlace><!-- Publication place (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<date>17 May 1887</date><!-- Item date; same as date in <title type="alternative"> above -->
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
                	<!-- Title without date -->
					<!-- Same as <title> above -->
					<title>“Tippoo Tib”</title>
					<!-- Each author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing) -->
					<!-- Same as <author> above -->
					<!-- xml:id = each author's initials -->
                    <author xml:id="An">Anonymous</author>
                    <author xml:id="TT">Tippu Tip</author>
					<!-- Same as <date> in previous section -->
					<!-- Write out date: Day Month Year -->
					<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
                    <date type="publication" when="1887-05-17">17 May 1887</date><!-- Can be type="composition" or type="publication" -->
                    <date type="composition" when="1887-03-30">30 March 1887</date><!-- Can be type="composition" or type="publication" -->
					<!-- See item for composition place; remove if not given -->
                    <placeName type="compositionPlace">Matadi, Congo River</placeName><!-- Can be "compositionPlace" or "focusRegion" --></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
			<!-- End of published text <sourceDesc> -->

        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry -->
                <!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
			<!-- Use one <change> for each instance of revision -->
			<!-- Always place most recent <change> at top -->
			<!-- Describe using one of the phrases associated with your name above -->
			<!-- E.g., Transcription or TEI Encoding or Proofing, etc. -->
			<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
			<!-- @who = #[your initials], e.g., #AW or #HB or #MBT -->
			<change when="2020-09-10" who="#AW">TEI Encoding</change>
			<change when="2020-09-01" who="#CM">Create and Proof Text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
		<body><!-- Actual color of the MS page; AW will insert appropriate color; remove @n if white because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->
			<div><!-- Acutal color of the writing; AW will use auto-suggested values; remove @rend if black because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->

	<!-- ndash: &#8212; -->
	<!-- mdash: &#8212; -->

	<!-- Put a <pb> at the beginning of each page -->
	<!-- @facs = LEAP ID _ page number, e.g., liv_020010_0001 -->
	<!-- @n = page number only, e.g., 0001 -->
    <pb facs="liv_020028_0001" n="0001"/>
<head rend="caps center">Tippoo Tib.</head> 
<p rend="right"><hi rend="caps">Matadi, Congo River</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">March</hi> 30.<space extent="2" unit="chars"/></p>
<lb/><p>During the two days' stay made by Mr. Stanley's 
ex<!-- - -->pedition at this place, in order to organize the caravan 
inteaded to proceed by way of the Falls to Leopoldville, 
a resident here had a conversation with Tippoo Tib, in 
which the latter entered into full particulars concerning 
his past and present connexion with Mr. H. M. Stanley.</p>
<p>It was at Zanzibar, where Tippoo Tib, aocompanied by 
his son, had gone to sell ivory, that he received Mr. 
Stanley's letter from Brussels, proposing to him to enter 
the service of the Assooiation. No mention was then 
made of any appointment as Governor of the Falls, it 
being merely stated that Tippoo Tib's services would be 
used on the Upper Congo, as near as possible to the centre 
of his operations in Africa. Tippoo Tib mentioned these 
proposals to his son, who advised him not to accept them 
He resolved to await Mr. Stanley's arrival, offering his 
services meanwhile for engaging 200 Zanzibar natives for 
the projected expedition.</p>
<p>After speaking of the services which he had rendered to 
Lieutenant Cameron and Mr Stanley, and particularly to 
the latter on his first expedition, Tippoo Tib was asked what 
had decided him to aceept Mr. Stanley's offer and to ac-
company him to Boma. He replied as follows :&#8212;</p>
<p>"I never clearly understood the object or the 
organiza<!-- - -->tion of the International African Association. The other 
Arab chiefs and myself at first believed, on seeing 
expedi<!-- - -->tions organized at Zanzibar under Captain Cambier and 
Lieu<!-- - -->tenant Becker, that the Europeans wished to compete 
with us in the markets of Tabora and Zanzibar, and 
ex<!-- - -->port, like ourselves, ivory and produce of varibus kinds.
We did not know whether Stanley and the other white 
chiefs were acting for the King of the Belgians, for
Belgium, or for the International Association, and we 
were always left in doubt on the point.</p>
<p>"But now that we have seen that such are not the 
intentions of the whites-that is to say, of the Belgians 
and English, whom we have met on the East Coast ; now 
that they have abandoned this part of Africa in order to 
establish, by common accord, we are told, between all the 
great peoples of Europe, a State where everybody may 
freely trade, we see no further reason to doubt the good
intentions of the whites, who have already done so much
in Africa."</p>
<p>Being next asked if there were not other reasons which 
had led him to accept Mr. Stanley's proposals, Tippoo 
Tib replied :&#8212;</p>
<p>"Yes. I confess that at first the idea of becoming a 
functionary of the Independent Congo State was a singular 
one to me. But Stanley pointed out that I should have a 
privileged position; that the State on its side could only 
gain by seeing its establishments on the Upper Congo 
supported by the authority which for many years past I 
had acquired over the people of the interior, who all knew 
me through having traded with me ; while,as regarded 
my<!-- - -->self, I could not but strengthen my commercial relations 
by means of the support which the Congo State would 
afford to me, as to all who were established on its 
territory.</p>
<p>"I perceived the justice of these arguments, and I had, 
moreover, at heart to remedy, as far as I could, the 
mischief which the Arabs and the population at the Falls 
had done in destroying the station at Stanley Fal1s. This 
act was the result of misunderstanding and imprudence; but 
I do not think that I can refuse to make reparation if, as 
I believe, I can do so."</p>
<p>Tippoo Tib admitted that he was also influenced by 
commercial considerations of another kind, and said :&#8212;</p>
<p>"The circumstances under which trade is carried on 
with the East coast are no longer so favourable as some 
years back, when I commenced trading with Zanzibar and 
abroad. Trade at that period had, so to speak, no 
existence. I established myself at Houron, near Tabora, 
with my old father and my brother Mohamed Massoudi, 
wishing first to create in the neigbbourhood plantations 
yielding satisfactory returns, and above all to monopolize 
the ivory trade by establishing Arab correspondents 
throughout Central Africa, on the shores of the Lakes, 
and as far Nyangoué. The people of the centre, who 
had no means of disposing of their considerable stocks of 
ivory, let me have them at a price which enabled me to 
realize a large profit. In a short time I had monopolized 
nearly all the sources of ivory production, 
and all the trade of the Manyems was in my hands.</p>
<p>"The great difficulty has always been to bring the 
produce of Central Africa to the markets of Tabera and 
Zanzibar. At first this was easy enough, but gradually 
the people of the centre became aware that they could
also gain something by my operations, and commenced 
imposing heavy tribute upon me for right of way through 
their territories. For instanoe, the Wa-Kundis, who 
alone possess the boats necessary for crossing the 
Malagarazi, exact exorbitant terms for the use of them. 
Certain tribes sometimes attacked my caravans, causing 
me heavy loss in men and merchandise.</p>
<p>"Even on the coast the conditions of trade changed. 
The Germans were everywhere, and their pretentions 
rendered business more and more difficult. Great 
diffi<!-- - -->culties arose from this state of things, and on all these 
grounds I concluded that if the trade of Central Africa 
could follow another route and reach the coast by sure 
roads on which no tribute would have to be paid, and 
where no difficulties were to be apprhended, everybody 
would be the gainer. After what I have seea at Banana 
and Boma I believe I am not mistaken, and that traders 
like myself can only gain by dispatching their produce 
from Nyangoue by way of the Falls and the Congo."</p>
<p>On being asked what he would do on reaching the Falls,
and how he would fulfil his mission, Tippoo Tib 
replied :&#8212;</p>
<p>"In the first place I feel sure that Stanley will succeed 
in his enterprise and relieve Emin Pasha. He is a real 
Arab for energy and intelligence. I do not know yet for 
certain whether I shall go with him as far as Wadelai, but 
I think I shall. Once installed at the Falls, I shall rebuild 
the stations and summon all the Arab and native chiefs to 
a great meeting, at which I shall announce to them my nomination 
as Governor, and my intentions. They will 
be surprised, I expect, to see me arrive from this side, for 
the news of my leaving Zanzibar with Stanley and of my 
nomination as Governor cannot reach Nyangoue and 
Central Africa in less than four or five months, and I shall 
arrive at the Falls before that time. When order is 
re<!-- - -->established at the Falls, I shall probably undertake a 
commercial expedition to nyangoue and the Lake
region."</p>
<p>The Arab chief's real name is Hamed-ben-Hamed, the 
<hi rend="italic">sobriquet</hi> of Tippoo Tib having been given to him owing to 
a twitching of the eyelids to which he is subject. The 
best understanding exists between Mr. Stanley and Tippoo 
Tib, and the latter has already been of great assistance in 
maintaining order among the Zanzibar men. Son of an 
Arab of Zanzbiar, Tippoo Tib detests negroes, and is 
attached to the whites, whom, in conversation, he calls his 
European brothers.
</p>


            </div>
        </body>   
    </text>
</TEI>