<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- Next line points to online XSL; use red triangle button in oXygen when done to transform file and check encoding -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/omv-integrated.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020027"><!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>“Original Correspondence: West Africa”</title><!-- Title without date --><!-- Check https://onemorevoice.org/bibliography.html for "canonical" name. -->
				<title type="normalized">‘Original Correspondence: West Africa’</title><!-- If title surrounded by double quotations, then replace with single quotations here; otherwise remove -->
                <title type="alternative">“Original Correspondence: West Africa,” 1 February 1864</title><!-- Title, date -->
                <author>Chamerovzow, Louis-Alexis, 1800-1899</author><!-- First author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates) -->
                <author>Aga, Selim, c.1826-1875</author><!-- Second author, etc.: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates); if no second author, remove this line -->
				<author role="first">Chamerovzow, Louis-Alexis</author><!-- First author only: Surname, Forename -->
				<author role="first-normalized">Louis-Alexis Chamerovzow</author><!-- First author only: Forename Surname -->
				<author role="normalized">Selim Aga</author><!-- Second author, etc.: Forename Surname; if no second author, remove this line -->
                <principal>Heather F. Ball</principal>
                <principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
				<!-- Only people involved in the actual transcription should be listed below; remove everyone else -->
                <respStmt xml:id="CM">
                    <name>Caitlin Matheis</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>Proofing</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AW">
                    <name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
                    <resp>Proofing</resp>
                    <resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>One More Voice</authority>
                <publisher>Livingstone Online</publisher>
                <pubPlace>University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_020027</idno><!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
				<!-- <ref> takes the name of the source used for original, e.g., Internet Archive -->
				<!-- @target = URL of source -->
				<ref target="https://www.gale.com/c/nineteenth-century-uk-periodicals-part-ii">Nineteenth Century UK Periodicals, Part II: Empire</ref>
				<!-- Edit <availability> as relevant -->
	            <availability>
					<p>Critically-edited text copyright <hi rend="italic">One More Voice</hi>.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
	            </availability>
			</publicationStmt>

			<!-- Use this version of <sourceDesc> if published text; otherwise delete it -->
            <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr n="narrow"><!-- Default is journal/periodical article; if book section, change to <monogr n="book-section">; if columns are narrow, use <monogr n="narrow">; combinations also OK: <monogr n="book-section narrow"> -->
						<title>Anti-Slavery Reporter</title><!-- Publication title: journal or book -->
						<!-- Author here used only for books -->
						<!-- Forename Surname-->
	                    <author></author>
						<editor></editor><!-- Editor (if known; otherwise leave blank -->
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="vol"></biblScope><!-- Volume (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<biblScope unit="issue"></biblScope><!-- Issue (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<biblScope unit="pages">2</biblScope><!-- Pages (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<pubPlace></pubPlace><!-- Publication place (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<publisher></publisher><!-- Publisher (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<date>1 February 1864</date><!-- Item date; same as date in <title type="alternative"> above -->
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
                	<!-- Title without date -->
					<!-- Same as <title> above -->
					<title>“Original Correspondence: West Africa”</title>
					<!-- Each author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing) -->
					<!-- Same as <author> above -->
					<!-- xml:id = each author's initials -->
                    <author xml:id="LAC">Chamerovzow, Louis-Alexis, 1800-1899</author>
                    <author xml:id="SA">Aga, Selim, c.1826-1875</author>
					<!-- Same as <date> in previous section -->
					<!-- Write out date: Day Month Year -->
					<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
                    <date type="publication" when="1864-02-01">1 February 1864</date><!-- Can be type="composition" or type="publication" -->
                    <date type="composition" when="1863-11-16">16 November 1863</date><!-- Can be type="composition" or type="publication" -->
					<!-- See item for composition place; remove if not given -->
                    <placeName type="compositionPlace">Fernando Po</placeName><!-- Can be "compositionPlace" or "focusRegion" -->              				</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
			<!-- End of published text <sourceDesc> -->

        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry -->
                <!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
			<!-- Use one <change> for each instance of revision -->
			<!-- Always place most recent <change> at top -->
			<!-- Describe using one of the phrases associated with your name above -->
			<!-- E.g., Transcription or TEI Encoding or Proofing, etc. -->
			<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
			<!-- @who = #[your initials], e.g., #AW or #HB or #MBT -->
			<change when="2020-09-02" who="#AW">TEI Encoding</change>
			<change when="2020-09-01" who="#CM">Create and Proof Text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
		<body><!-- Actual color of the MS page; AW will insert appropriate color; remove @n if white because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->
			<div><!-- Acutal color of the writing; AW will use auto-suggested values; remove @rend if black because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->

	<!-- ndash: &#8211; -->
	<!-- mdash: &#8212; -->

	<!-- Put a <pb> at the beginning of each page -->
	<!-- @facs = LEAP ID _ page number, e.g., liv_020010_0001 -->
	<!-- @n = page number only, e.g., 0001 -->
    <pb facs="liv_020027_0001" n="0001"/>
<lb/><p>Original Correspondence.</p>
<p>WEST AFRICA.</p>
<p>THE following interesting letter is from a 
native African, who, when quite a child, 
was kidnapped from the interior of Nubia. 
and after being several times sold, finally fell 
into the hands of an English family at 
Alexandria, where he acquired the rudiments 
of education, namely, a knowledge of the 
English alphabet. After remaining with 
this family for some time, he came to Eng- 
land in the capacity of servant; and having 
undergone many vicissitudes, at length went 
out to Lagos, to try what he could do on his 
own account. By his good conduct and ex- 
cellent principles, his sobriety, industry, and 
perseverance, he gained the confidence of 
the parties to whom he had been recom- 
mended, and his name is honourably mentioned 
in the despatches of Captain Burton, whom 
he accompanied on his recent visit to the 
King of Dahomey, and who has again en- 
gaged him for his present expedition. We 
have received other communications from 
him, from time to time, but they were strictly 
personal. Tlhe present one appears to us to 
offer sufficient interest to merit a place in 
our columns, and we print it without correc- 
tion.</p>
<p>"Fernando Po, Nov. 16, 1863.</p> 
<p>"RESPECTED SIR,-Your kind favour of the 
14th August came to hand on my return from 
the Congo River, to which place I accompanied 
Consul Burton last July. The condition of that 
country, as far as we ascended, viz. 160 miles 
into the interior, is in a most deplorable state. 
The slave-trade and its accompaniments have 
been, and still are, ruling rampant in that river; 
and the result is a thorough demoralization of 
the inhabitants. The copious drafts of rum and 
other luxuries, showered upon the people by the 
Portuguese slave-traders, has made them so 
thoroughly idle, that the earth groans for the 
want of some one to cultivate it. We found the 
poor victims to the influence of the vile traffic 
entirely in the hands of Satan; for thefts and 
debauchery of every description are rife through- 
out the whole country, but more especially from 
Shark Point, the mouth of the river, to Em- 
bomma, some eighty miles in the interior. Along 
the whole of the line are established baracoons 
and factories of every size and description. At 
some of these I saw plenty of slaves, and more 
particularly at one house in Embomma, where 
the unfortunate wretches were put in irons, 
awaiting the first opportunity of being sent down 
to the coast. I cannot give you a better exam- 
ple than this. We found, in the lower part of 
the river, the weaker sex awfully given to 
drunkenness, and, although nominally acknow- 
ledged by some one as their husband, they are

    <pb facs="liv_020027_0002" n="0002"/>
in reality nothing but common property. I have 
now travelled through the greater part of West 
Africa, the Gambia, Sierra Leone, Liberia, the 
Gold Coast, Dahomey, Lagos, Badagry, Porto 
Novo, and for 400 miles into the interior of the 
Euroba, or Yoruba country, the Benin, the 
Nun, the Brass, New Calabar, Bonny, Old Ca- 
labar, Cameroons, Fernando Po, Gaboon, and 
St. Paul's de Loando. I have visited Africans 
in their most primitive condition; but never in 
the whole of my experience did any thing like 
the state of affairs in the Congo River ever pre- 
sent itself to my notice. I am happy to say, 
however, that Her Majesty's cruisers are doing 
their utmost to suppress this market for human 
blood. When we left the mouth of the Congo 
last October, the Zebra, the Archer, the Griffin, 
the Lee, and the Afulet, were on duty there, so 
that we hope, ere long, to hear that the Portu- 
guese are ultimately compelled to leave the river. 
I hear that, according to present arrangements, 
the power of Portugal ought not to extend be- 
yond Ambrizette, forty miles south of the Zaire, 
or Congo. If so, they ought to be turned out 
of the river by force; for so long as they exer- 
cise their influence over the natives, no legiti- 
mate commerce can be established with them. 
Messrs.- and - is the only English 
house in the river, and I am sorry to say that 
it is a failure; for, encouraged on every point 
by the slave-traders, the native chiefs find 
it more profitable to catch men and sell them 
for plenty of rum and beads and cloth, than to 
spoil their fingers by the manufacture of palm- 
oil. In fact, I cannot see how a profitable traffic 
in native produce can be carried on unless the 
slave-traders were driven out, and the river 
shut up for two or three years, to purge it 
from the effects produced by the vile system ex- 
isting in its bosom. In about five or six days 
I hope to accompany Captain Burton (by whom 
I am now employed) to the Court of the Da- 
homey King. This will be our second visit to 
that country; and, from my slight experience 
of the country and people, I think Captain Bur- 
ton is just the right man in the right place.</p> 
<p>"Many thanks for the receipts, which came 
to hand all safe, as also the copies of the Re- 
porter. The subscribers are quite delighted with 
the news, and wonder they had never heard of 
the Society before this. As the subject has now 
been introduced to their notice, I hope they will 
keep up the communication regularly with home; 
and I see no reason why all the intelligent na- 
tives on the coast should not become subscribers. 
I am sorry to say that the present system of 
education on the coast is not calculated to raise 
the natives much beyond their former scale of 
usefulness. There are only two things that they 
are educated for, viz. clerks and merchants. 
Everybody cannot be a merchant. Why not 
encourage agriculture? The same money that
makes the merchant can make the farmer, and 
I must confess that the latter would be the most 
independent of the two; for, singular to relate, 
that the prejudice of the native against the 
European, and, vice versa, of the European 
against the native, is any thing but encourag- 
ing. The natives have great capacities for 
trade; but the goods supplied to them on the 
coast are invoiced at such high prices, that it is 
really impossible for them to, realize any thing 
for themselves. To prove this, I have only to 
mention the case of Mr. - , one of our 
subscribers. Last year he paid in something 
like 800l. (Eight hundred pounds) sterling 
as his yearly trade account with Messrs.- 
and - . Out of this he received commission 
about fifty pounds with which to maintain himself,
 his wife, and the Kroo- boys, besides a nephew and 
four children. Had it not been that Mr. 
- had other sources to depend upon, his 
brokerage between the Europeans and natives 
would never keep his house in more than dr)y 
bread and water. He begged of me to recom- 
mend him to some gentleman in England with 
whom he could deal . . . . . .</p>
<p>. . . . . . . . .</p>
<p>. . .He has about 3001. to 4001. 
worth of palm-oil, his own private property; 
and I should feel truly grateful if you will put 
him in the way of trading direct with England. 
He intends shipping some of his oil the moment 
he receives a communication from you. As for 
myself, I must candidly confess that I have 
found it more profitable for the present to be 
travelling about. That, however, cannot last, 
for, sooner or later, I must settle down somewhere. 
There are already too many engaged in palm- 
oil ; I therefore think of starting a cotton plan- 
tation at the foot of the Cameroon mountains as 
soon as my period of servitude with my present 
employer has expired. Two or three thousand 
acres taken in and sown with cotton would not 
require more than 3501. to 4001. out here, and, 
from experiments already tried, the farm could 
be made self-supporting after the first year. I 
do not think we shall be more than three months 
in Dahomey, after which I think my master goes 
to England, and then I shall be at liberty to try 
for myself. I enclose a sample of cotton which 
I have grown this year in the Consular grounds. 
There are about two acres sowed with cotton, 
and I expect to gather about three cwt. With 
many thanks for your kind wishes,</p>
<p>"I remain, respected Sir, </p>
<p>"Your grateful Servant,</p>
<p>"SELIM AGA.</p>
<p>"L. A. CIIAMEROVZOW, Esq."</p>

            </div>
        </body>   
    </text>
</TEI>