<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- Next line points to online XSL; use red triangle button in oXygen when done to transform file and check encoding -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="../omv-integrated.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020017"><!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>“The Niger Expedition”</title><!-- Title without date --><!-- Check https://onemorevoice.org/bibliography.html for "canonical" name. -->
				<title type="normalized">‘The Niger Expedition’</title><!-- If title surrounded by double quotations, then replace with single quotations here; otherwise remove -->
                <title type="alternative">“The Niger Expedition,” 25 September 1858</title><!-- Title, date -->
                <author>Anonymous</author><!-- First author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates) -->
                <author>Aga, Selim</author><!-- Second author, etc.: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates); if no second author, remove this line -->
				<author role="first">Anonymous</author><!-- First author only: Surname, Forename -->
				<author role="first-normalized">Anonymous</author><!-- First author only: Forename Surname -->
				<author role="normalized">Selim Aga</author><!-- Second author, etc.: Forename Surname; if no second author, remove this line -->
                <principal>Heather F. Ball</principal>
                <principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
				<!-- Only people involved in the actual transcription should be listed below; remove everyone else -->
                <respStmt xml:id="HB">
                    <name>Heather F. Ball</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
                    <resp>Proofing</resp>
                    <resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AW">
                    <name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
                    <resp>Proofing</resp>
                    <resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>One More Voice</authority>
                <publisher>Livingstone Online</publisher>
                <pubPlace>University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2020</date>
                <idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_020017</idno><!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
				<!-- <ref> takes the name of the source used for original, e.g., Internet Archive -->
				<!-- @target = URL of source -->
				<ref target="https://www.gale.com/c/british-library-newspapers-part-i">British Library Newspapers</ref>
				<!-- Edit <availability> as relevant -->
	            <availability>
					<p>Critically-edited text copyright <hi rend="italic">One More Voice</hi>.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>

			<!-- Use this version of <sourceDesc> if published text; otherwise delete it -->
            <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr n="narrow">
						<title>The Preston Chronicle and Lancashire Advertiser</title><!-- Publication title -->
						<!-- Author here used only for books -->
						<!-- Forename Surname-->
	                    <author></author>
						<editor></editor><!-- Editor (if known; otherwise leave blank -->
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="pages">3</biblScope><!-- Pages (if known; otherwise leave blank -->
							<date>25 September 1858</date><!-- Item date; same as date in <title type="alternative"> above -->
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
                	<!-- Title without date -->
					<!-- Same as <title> above -->
					<title>“The Niger Expedition”</title>
					<!-- Each author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing) -->
					<!-- Same as <author> above -->
					<!-- xml:id = each author's initials -->
                    <author xml:id="An">Selim Aga</author><!-- Not sure what to do about this if Anon. was first? HB --><!-- Fixed. AW -->
                    <author xml:id="SA">Selim Aga</author>
					<!-- Same as <date> in previous section -->
					<!-- Write out date: Day Month Year -->
					<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
                    <date type="publication" when="1858-09-25">25 September 1858</date>
					<date type="composition" when="1858-06-24">24 June 1858</date>
                    <placeName type="compositionPlace">Lagos, West Africa</placeName>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
			<!-- End of published text <sourceDesc> -->

        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry -->
                <!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
			<!-- Use one <change> for each instance of revision -->
			<!-- Always place most recent <change> at top -->
			<!-- Describe using one of the phrases associated with your name above -->
			<!-- E.g., Transcription or TEI Encoding or Proofing, etc. -->
			<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
			<!-- @who = #[your initials], e.g., #AW or #HB or #MBT -->
			<change when="2020-07-21" who="#AW">Coding Review</change>
			<change when="2020-06-29" who="#HB">Transcription and TEI Encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
		<body><!-- Actual color of the MS page; AW will insert appropriate color; remove @n if white because that's the default color -->
			<div><!-- Acutal color of the writing; AW will use auto-suggested values; remove @rend if black because that's the default color -->

	<!-- ndash: &#8211; -->
	<!-- mdash: &#8212; -->

	<!-- Put a <pb> at the beginning of each page -->
	<!-- @facs = LEAP ID _ page number, e.g., liv_020010_0001 -->
	<!-- @n = page number only, e.g., 0001 -->
    <pb facs="liv_020017_0001" n="0001"/>

<p rend="center caps">The <orgName><geogName>Niger</geogName> Expedition</orgName>.</p>
<milestone unit="section" rend="center quarter-line"/><!-- Not sure how to code this little line - it's not a full underline, so maybe quarter-line and centered? HB --><!-- See how I've done it. AW -->
<p>Two letters, addressed to an <term type="collective">English</term> merchant, by <persName>Selim Aga</persName>, a native of <region>Darfur</region>, in <region>Central <bloc>Africa</bloc></region>, who is engaged in the <orgName><geogName>Niger</geogName> expedition</orgName>, have been forwarded for publication to the <hi rend="italic">Carlisle Journal</hi>. When the writer was ten years of age, he was purchased in <country>Egypt</country> by the gentleman to whom the letters are addressed, and he subsequently received an excellent <term type="collective">English</term> education. <persName>Selim</persName> is now upwards of 30 years of age, and is able to render important aid to the <orgName><geogName>Niger</geogName> expedition</orgName>. The following are extracts from the letters :&#8212;</p>
<p><settlement>Lagos</settlement>, <bloc>West Africa</bloc>, <date when="1858-06-24">June 24, 1858</date>.&#8212;I am now with <persName>Lieutenant Glover</persName>, getting provisions and other necessaries for our expedition into the interior of <bloc>Africa</bloc>. We intend to proceed up the river<!-- The Niger River --> in the <hi rend="italic">Spero Meliora</hi>, and to commence our land journey from <settlement>Rabbah</settlement> to <settlement><choice><orig>Kanoo</orig><reg>Kano</reg></choice></settlement> in <region><choice><sic>Housa</sic><corr>Hausa</corr></choice></region>, thence to <settlement>Kirka</settlement> in <region>Bornou</region>, and thence to <region>Begharmi</region>, <region>Wadai</region>, the <geogName>Mountains of the Moon</geogName>, to the source of the <geogName>Nile</geogName>, thence through <region>Darfur</region>, <region>Kordofan</region>, <settlement><choice><orig>Senaar</orig><reg>Sennar</reg></choice></settlement>, <region>Nubia</region>, and <country>Egypt</country>, to <country>England</country>. I think we may be about 18 months<!-- Adrian should this be date coded for Dec 1859 since we have the letter date? HB --><!-- No, OK as is. AW --> before reaching <country>England</country>. l am glad to hear that <persName>Mr. Laird</persName> intends to send many more steamboats to the <geogName>Niger</geogName>, and have not the least doubt that the outlay will be covered in about a couple of years; and under the management of sensible men the trade of the country will increase annually nearly a hundred fold, till every patch of useless ground is under cultivation. To prove this, let us look at the <term type="plant">cotton</term> trade at <settlement>Abeokuta</settlement>. It has been established under the auspices of the <orgName><settlement>Manchester</settlement> Chamber of Commerce</orgName>, and is immediately patronised by the <orgName>Church Missionary Society</orgName>, because that society is now anxious that it should encourage free labour produce, and give up consuming <term type="collective">American</term> slave-grown<!-- Adrian, are we still tagging all things slave-related like this? HB --><!-- No. AW --> <term type="plant">cotton</term>. A lay agent has been sent to <settlement>Abeokuta</settlement> with all the necessaries for cleaning and pressing <term type="plant">cotton</term>. The first twelve months he managed to send about 300 bales, but the second year, which ended in <date when="1857-05">last May</date>, realised something like 1,000, nearly an increase of 250 per cent.; and <persName>Mr. Robin</persName>, the agent, a native of the country, is now obliged to commence business at four or five o'clock in the morning in order to get rid of his customers by six o'clock in the evening. Encouraged by this fact, merchants are about to establish themselves at <settlement>Abeokuta</settlement>, thus giving every encouragement to the natives of this populous town and surrounding country. <settlement>Rabbah</settlement>, although at present a complete ruin, will be one of the greatest commercial emporiums on the banks of the <geogName>Niger</geogName>; for, independent of its position as a marine port, it possesses great interest from the fact of <choice><sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr></choice> being the great medium of communication to <settlement><choice><orig>Kuka</orig><reg>Kukawa</reg></choice></settlement>, <settlement><choice><orig>Kanoo</orig><reg>Kano</reg></choice></settlement>, and the lake <geogName>Tchad</geogName>. The last caravan we met from those localities numbered about 2,000 travellers, with upwards of 600 or 700 <term type="animal">horses</term> and <term type="animal">donkeys</term>. They bring ivory, guns, and hides from the interior to <settlement>Ilorin</settlement>, and receive in return <term type="collective">European</term> goods and clothing, with which they return back to their own country. Therefore, a clever merchant established at <settlement>Rabbah</settlement> would intercept all the trade of the interior, besides the goods which will be supplied by the <term type="collective"><term type="collective"><choice><orig>Tappah</orig><reg>Tapa</reg></choice></term> and <term type="collective"><choice><orig>Nufeh</orig><reg>Nupe</reg></choice></term> people</term>. There is, however, one great want at <settlement>Rabbah</settlement>, <choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan>videlicet</expan></choice>, a judicial officer in the capacity of consul or magistrate. If such an authority could be sent out from <country>England</country> (and he must be a white man), it would induce many emigrants from <country>Sierra <supplied>Leone</supplied></country><!-- Leone? AW --> to settle on the <geogName>Niger</geogName>, thus facilitating the labours of the missionary and the merchant; for, once perfectly satisfied that the general laws of <country>England</country> are extending their benign influence into this part of <bloc>Africa</bloc>, every educated <term type="collective">African</term> who is a native of the river <geogName>Niger</geogName> will venture, with his life and property, to settle on that river<!-- Niger -->. With regard to the trade of the country, I think there is every facility for a very extensive business as far as the natives are concerned, but the question of sending the <term type="foodstuff">produce</term> to the mouth of the river or any other part for shipment is rather a difficult matter, for the <geogName>Niger</geogName> is not always sufficiently full to allow for communication by means of steamboats. A question therefore arises as to whether it would be more profitable for the merchant to store up his goods for the space of six months (the dry season), or to start a quadruped communication from <settlement>Rabbah</settlement> to <settlement>Lagos</settlement>. The latter is practicable, only it would entail an immense expense at the onset. The distance is about 400 miles, and I have now travelled the road three times, twice with <persName><choice><abbr>Lieut.</abbr><expan>Lieutenant</expan></choice> Glover</persName> and once a part of the way by myself, in charge of government<!-- British --> stores for the <geogName>Niger</geogName> camp. The stores consisted of 15 loads; a load weighs from 45 to 60 pounds on an average, and is carried on the head of the bearer; each bearer is paid at the rate of 1,000 cowries per day, or 1s. 3d. sterling <!-- Adrian, not sure what D stands for to expand? HB --><!-- Pounds. AW -->, thus making in 15 days (the period occupied in travelling with loads from <settlement>Rabbah</settlement> to <settlement>Lagos</settlement>) the sum of 18s. 9d. per load. Now, will it pay to employ a bearer to bring a tusk weighing 50lbs., and which costs from £5 to £6 at <settlement>Rabbah</settlement>, for shipment at <settlement>Lagos</settlement>? I think it will. Besides this, a number of <term type="animal">horses</term> or <term type="animal">donkeys</term> might be stationed in the different chief towns on the road, and thus reduce the period of transmit from fifteen to eight or nine days. The price of a <term type="animal">donkey</term> in the <region><choice><sic>Housa</sic><corr>Hausa</corr></choice> country</region> would not be more than 15 shillings, and if a number of young men were redeemed from slavery and put under the superintendence of a partially educated person at the different stations, they could be employed partly in taking charge of the <term type="foodstuff">produce</term> whilst on its way to the next station, partly in cultivating a sufficient amount of ground for the growth of <term type="foodstuff">yams</term>, <term type="foodstuff">corn</term>, and other necessaries for the support of themselves and the <term type="animal">beasts of burden</term> under their charge. Land can be had for nothing, and negotiations can be entered into with different kings and chiefs along the road for perfect freedom to pass with the goods. They (the chiefs) are a great nuisance, for they stopped me at one place (<settlement>Obomishaw</settlement>) demanding 40 cowries for every one of the 15 loads under my charge. I protested against this piece of insolence, threatening the chiefs, with the white man's guns, and succeeded in getting away scot free. The next time I came through the same town with six loads, the chiefs and their men retreated into the town, leaving the gate entirely at my disposal. Not to abandon the subject of trade, however, it may be as well to mention that the price of a slave in the <region>Yariba country</region> is from £7 to £11. The free natives will not work for us, and <term type="collective"><term type="collective">Kroo</term> boys</term> are too lazy, although to be had at a very low price, <choice><abbr>viz.</abbr><expan>videlicet</expan></choice>, from 10s. to 17s. a month; but they scarcely pay for their keep, so that the choice of <persName>Hobson</persName> <!-- Not sure if name or place? HB --><!-- Person. AW --> is left to the man of enterprise&#8212;that is, to purchase slaves for domestic and other purposes till a better remedy is found out.</p>

			</div>
		</body>	
    </text>
</TEI>
