<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- Next line points to online XSL; use red triangle button in oXygen when done to transform file and check encoding -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="../omv-integrated.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020031">
	<!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020031 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>“An Incident in the Late Rebellion in Jamaica”</title>
				<!-- Title without date -->
				<!-- Check https://onemorevoice.org/bibliography.html for "canonical" name. -->
				<title type="normalized">‘An Incident in the Late Rebellion in Jamaica’</title>
				<!-- If title surrounded by double quotations, then replace with single quotations here; otherwise remove -->
				<title type="alternative">“An Incident in the Late Rebellion in Jamaica,” 1855</title>
				<!-- Title, date -->
				<author>Labatt, Philip Cohen, 1823-1854</author>
				<!-- First author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates) -->
				<author role="first">Labatt, Philip Cohen</author>
				<!-- First author only: Surname, Forename -->
				<author role="first-normalized">Philip Cohen Labatt</author>
				<!-- First author only: Forename Surname -->
				<principal>Heather F. Ball</principal>
				<principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
				<!-- Only people involved in the actual transcription should be listed below; remove everyone else -->
				<respStmt xml:id="HK">
					<name>Heidi Kaufman</name>
					<resp>Transcription</resp>
					<resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
					<resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt xml:id="AW">
					<name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
					<resp>Transcription</resp>
					<resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
					<resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>One More Voice</authority>
				<publisher>Livingstone Online</publisher>
				<pubPlace>University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2021</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_020031</idno>
				<!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
				<!-- <ref> takes the name of the source used for original, e.g., Internet Archive -->
				<!-- @target = URL of source -->
				<ref target="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Selections_from_the_miscellaneous_posthu/KKMIAAAAQAAJ?hl=en">Google Books</ref>
				<!-- Edit <availability> as relevant -->
				<availability>
			<p>Critically-edited text copyright <hi rend="italic">One More Voice</hi>.</p>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
						International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
	
			<!-- Use this version of <sourceDesc> if published text; otherwise delete it -->
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr n="book-section"><!-- Default is journal/periodical article; if book section, change to <monogr n="book-section">; if columns are narrow, use <monogr n="narrow">; combinations also OK: <monogr n="book-section narrow"> -->
						<title>Selections From the Miscellaneous Posthumous Works of Philip Cohen Labatt in Prose and Verse</title><!-- Publication title: journal or book -->
						<!-- Author here used only for books -->
						<!-- Forename Surname-->
						<author>Philip Cohen Labatt</author>
						<editor>I. Lawton</editor><!-- Editor (if known; otherwise leave blank -->
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="pages">36-47</biblScope><!-- Pages (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<pubPlace>Kingston, Jamaica</pubPlace><!-- Publication place (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<publisher>E.J. DeCordova</publisher><!-- Publisher (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<date>1855</date><!-- Item date; same as date in <title type="alternative"> above -->
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>	
				<bibl type="sourceMetadata">
					<!-- Title without date -->
					<!-- Same as <title> above --> 
					<title>“An Incident in the Late Rebellion in Jamaica”</title>
					<!-- Each author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing) -->
					<!-- Same as <author> above -->
					<!-- xml:id = each author's initials -->
					<author xml:id="PCL">Labatt, Philip Cohen, 1823-1854"</author>
					<!-- Same as <date> in previous section -->
					<!-- Write out date: Day Month Year -->
					<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
					<date type="publication" when="1855">1855</date><!-- Can be type="composition" or type="publication" -->
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
			<!-- End of published text <sourceDesc> -->

		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry -->
				<!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Use one <change> for each instance of revision -->
			<!-- Always place most recent <change> at top -->
			<!-- Describe using one of the phrases associated with your name above -->
			<!-- E.g., Transcription or TEI Encoding or Proofing, etc. -->
			<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
			<!-- @who = #[your initials], e.g., #AW or #HB or #MBT -->
			<change when="2021-01-07" who="#AW">Initial coding review</change>
			<change when="2020-11-21" who="#HK">Initial transcription and coding</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<!-- Actual color of the MS page; AW will insert appropriate color; remove @n if white because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->
		<body>
			<!-- Acutal color of the writing; AW will use auto-suggested values; remove @rend if black because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->
			<div n="liv_020031">

<!-- ndash: &#8211; -->
<!-- mdash: &#8212; -->

<!-- Put a <pb> at the beginning of each page -->
<!-- @facs = LEAP ID _ page number, e.g., liv_020010_0001 -->
<!-- @n = page number only, e.g., 0001 -->
				
	<pb facs="liv_020031_0001" n="0001"/>
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>			
<head rend="caps center large"><seg rend="large">An Incident 
<lb/>In the Late Rebellion in Jamaica.</seg></head>
<milestone unit="section" rend="half-line quarter-line"/>					
	
<p>It was about ten o'clock at night, towards the end of the last re<!-- ­ -->bellion, that five privates and a sergeant attached to the &#8212;&#8212;company of the <orgName>Trelawny Militia</orgName> were located in an out-house on &#8212;&#8212;estate, for the purpose of protecting that property in an anticipated attack of the insurgents.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It was about as dark a night, reader, as I remember ever to have seen; the rain fell in torrents, not a star was visible, and the thunder broke over our heads in loud and deafening peals, and with a force, too, that shook to its foundation the crazy building in which we were posted.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Not one of us had a dry rag about him; for as the dismantled old house possessed but half a roof, and the pro<!-- ­ -->portion of half a shutter to every three windows&#8212;to say nothing of a most lamentable deficiency of sash frames, the rain poured down as mercilessly on us as it did outside of the house.</p>
	
<p><seg type="word">" Vot</seg> a night for firevorks and <seg type="word">Wauxall, "</seg> said young <persName>Toosy</persName>&#8212;(the last importation from Cokaigne, who had joined our company just be<!-- ­ -->fore the breaking out of the rebellion)&#8212;his teeth chattering in his head, and his lips as blue almost as indigo.&#8212;<seg type="word">" Real</seg> stunning enjoyment I call <seg type="word">this, "</seg> continued he, <seg type="word">" cuss</seg> the <orgName>rebels</orgName>, the black varmints, and <hi rend="italic">juice</hi> take the <hi rend="italic">Curnol</hi> for bordering us on this dirty duty; you hain't got a cigar about you <persName>Dick</persName>, 'ave you? <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>I do think I'd feel better for a <seg type="word">veed "</seg>.</p>
	
<p><persName>Dick</persName> pouch was forthcoming at the word, but the cigars, like everything else about him, were soaked through with water.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/><persName>Toosy</persName>, however, selected one which he thought he might manage, and crawl<!-- ­ -->ing towards the single candle, which flared and sputtered in a porter bottle under a table, where it had been placed to protect it as much as possible from the rain, endeavoured to kindle his cigar at the puny flame.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>His exertions, were, however, ineffectual, and resulted only in his extinguishing the miserable light, and leaving us in utter dark<!-- ­ -->ness.</p>
	
<p><seg type="word">" Here's </seg> a <seg type="word">go, "</seg> exclaimed the unfortunate recruit, as he groped his way back to his comparatively dry corner, amid a volley of abuse from his fellow-sufferers.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <seg type="word">" Here's </seg> a cussed go, I do believe the devil himself has had a hand in everything that has happened to-night. Fust of all <persName>Tom</persName> burnt the priming of his gun near my face, as he says, by accident, and singed off von of my viskers; next that d&#8212;&#8212;d nigger gave me winigar for brandy, and now I have gone and blowed out the holy light ve had.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I'm blessed if it's not enough to drive von <seg type="word">distracted; ” </seg>saying which, poor <persName>Toosy</persName> coolly deposited himself on<lb/>
	

<pb facs="liv_020031_0002" n="0002"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">An Incident in the Late Rebellion in Jamaica.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg> <seg rend="right">37</seg></fw>
a heap of empty bottles and broken glasses.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It required  but that to cap the climax of his misfortunes; starting up with a yell which rung throughout the house, he ran towards the door, determined, as he afterwards told us, rather to brave the storm without, than to remain one moment longer in the house.</p>
		
<p>But he was suddenly foiled in his attempt to escape.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>He had scarcely reached the door when a vivid light shot up on his path, and the entrance to the apartment became occupied by a most extraordi<!-- ­ -->nary apparition.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Toosy</persName> started back with much more vigour than he had exhibited in making for the door; and truly, a man of stronger nerve than our poor Cockney, might have felt some dread at the unexpected visit of the being who had so suddenly broken in upon our privacy.</p>
	
<p>The intruder was a tall gaunt negress, whose age, notwithstanding her erect stature, must have exceeded fifty years; her dress, which barely reached her skinny legs, was tattered, and dripping with moisture; her head was bare, and exposed to view a quantity of woolly grey hair, and her features were sharp and severe. But the most striking object about her face, was her mouth; it looked no more like the usual negro receptacle for cocoas and plantains, than chalk does like cheese; the lower lip hung down so low, as almost to conceal her chin, whilst five or six long white teeth protruding from her gums, gave her an appearance of ghastliness and  terror, which struck a chill to our hearts.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>She carried in her left hand a large horn lantern, the side of which was open; and in her right, a bright matchet or cutlas; <choice><sic>"</sic><corr></corr></choice>no word spoke she,<choice><sic>"</sic><corr></corr></choice> until she had carefully examined the apartment, when in harsh discordant notes, but in terms strikingly devoid of the negro patois, she enquired, <seg type="word">" is </seg> there a negro here?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Does one of that cursed race inhabit this room?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Be he slave or freeman, no negro, nor none of his blood, must hear the words which I have to speak to<!-- ­ --><seg type="word">night. " </seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="word">" There </seg> is no negro here, good <seg type="word"> <persName>mother</persName>," </seg> I replied, <seg type="word">" and </seg>your light at all events, if not yourself, is most heartily <seg type="word">welcome. "</seg></p>
	
<p>She sat down without replying, and appeared to be deep in thought for some minutes; at last she muttered <seg type="word">" I'll </seg> do <seg type="word">it "</seg>&#8212;then turning towards us, enquired, <seg type="word">" who </seg> commands <seg type="word">here? "</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="word">" I </seg> <seg type="word"> do," </seg> said <persName>sergeant S&#8212;&#8212;</persName>, rising from a heap of cloaks on which he had thrown himself. <seg type="word">" I</seg> do, <persName>mother</persName>, what would you with <seg type="word">us? "</seg></p>
		
<p><seg type="word">"Have </seg> you strength and <seg type="word">courage? "</seg> asked she.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/><seg type="word">" Could</seg> you dare the lion in his den, or rouse the savage tiger in the jungle?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>If ye can, follow me&#8212;but I warn ye death will be among ye ere the day breaks on this distracted country.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Follow me at once, and nerve yourselves to accomplish an act of daring and of <seg type="word"> danger. "</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="word">" Softly</seg>, <persName>good mother</persName>," said <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;&#8212;</persName>, "these are not times when men blindly rush into danger, or follow at the beck of every and any one.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>We must know whither you would lead us, and the nature of the expedition on which yon command our <seg type="word">aid. "</seg></p>


<pb facs="liv_020031_0003" n="0003"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">38</seg> <seg rend="center caps">An Incident In The<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg></fw>		
<p>The cautious reply of <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;&#8212;</persName> drew forth some commen<!-- ­ -->datory remarks from young <persName>Toosy</persName>, who was apparently but little dis<!-- ­ -->posed to lend the aid of his powerful arm and great military talents in carrying out the desires of the old woman.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Whether it was that the warning contained in the negress's address damped his courage (and, between us, good reader, <persName>Toosy</persName> was not blessed with any extraordi<!-- ­ -->nary development of the organ of combativeness,) or whether he con<!-- ­ -->ceived that the misfortunes which had already befallen him, were suffi<!-- ­ -->cient for the night, I will not undertake to decide, but his disinclina<!-- ­ -->tion to trust himself to the guidance of the old woman was expressed in terms so forcible and explicit, that they drew upon his luckless head the entire burst of anger which she had been vainly endeavoring to repress.</p>

<p><seg type="word">" Weak </seg> and timid <seg type="word">fool, "</seg> she exclaimed, <seg type="word">"your </seg> chicken-heart would but destroy our chance of success.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Remain here, if you fear to fol<!-- ­ -->low me, and change your musket for a doll.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Is it with men such as you that the government expects to put down this outbreak?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Fools are they to suppose so!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>If there are any <hi rend="italic">men</hi> among ye, follow me at once"; she continued turning to the others, "follow me this in<!-- ­ -->stant, or lose the honor which you will acquire in taking one of the most daring and successful of the <seg type="word"><orgName>rebels</orgName>. "</seg></p>

<p>	The tone in which she spoke, her excited gestures, and air of authority, together with the prospect she held out of our taking an in<!-- ­ -->surgent chief, produced the desired effect.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>In an instant every man was on his feet, busily resuming the military accoutrements which had been thrown aside, and we were just about to follow our strange guide when the storm of rain and thunder burst forth with renewed fury, and for the moment compelled us to abandon all idea of the ex<!-- ­ -->pedition.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <seg type="word">" However </seg> willing we may be to accompany you, my good <seg type="word">woman "</seg> said <persName>Sergeant&#8212;&#8212;</persName>, addressing the negress, <seg type="word">" you </seg> perceive it will be impossible for us to do so at present.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>No human being could live in a night like this, were he exposed to the fury of the elements.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Sit down, therefore, and let us know something more of the service which you require at our <seg type="word">hand. "</seg></p>

<p>She made no answer to this address, but commenced to pace up and down the dilapidated apartment, totally regardless of the heavy fall of water which poured down through the broken roof on her un<!-- ­ -->covered head.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> After continuing this exercise for some minutes, she gradually drew near to the lantern which she had placed under the table, and throwing herself on the floor, begun to warm her long skinny hand at the flame of the candle, muttering some words the while, but in so low a tone as prevented our catching their import.</p>
	
<p><persName>Toosy</persName>, who appeared to have recovered from the effects of all his late misfortunes, except that particular one which had resulted in the loss of his whisker, began to while away the time with a most melan<!-- ­ -->
choly ditty, which, as it belonged to that species of musical composi<!-- ­ -->tions usually termed sentimental, aided not a little in producing the <lb/>
	

<pb facs="liv_020031_0004" n="0004"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">Late Rebellion in Jamaica.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg> <seg rend="right">39</seg></fw>
effects of a sedative on our senses.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Not that there was anything par<!-- ­ -->ticularly somnitic in the air itself&#8212;in fact it was rather an agreeable recital of the loves of a certain <persName>Alice Gray</persName>, and an anonymous youth.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Toosy</persName> possessed little or no musical genius, und had a most extraor<!-- ­ -->dinary knack of converting demi-semi-quavers into breeves, and semi<!-- ­ -->quavers into semi-breeves.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The effect of this peculiar talent on the part of <persName>Toosy</persName> was, as may be supposed, that of extending the air to a most unconscionable length&#8212;and to such a height had he carried this new principle in music, that he once contrived to continue the battle of <placeName>Prague</placeName> through an entire fortnight; at the conclusion of which, he relieved our ears with the welcome announcement that he had forgotten the remaining half of the piece.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Toosy</persName>, I say, had just commenced to while away the time with the afore-mentioned air, and we were just falling into a refreshing slumber, when we were startled by a sudden and loud exclamation from the old woman.</p>
	
<p><seg type="word">“ Stop </seg>," she cried, <seg type="word">" stop </seg> for the love of God!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> That song, that song, it will kill <seg type="word">me. "</seg></p>

<p><seg type="word">“There </seg>," blubbered out the luckless <persName>Toosy</persName>.</p>
		
<p><seg type="word">" There </seg>, I've put my foot in it <seg type="word">again. "</seg><space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <seg type="word">" I</seg> always thought you'd kill somebody yet with your cursed <seg type="word">howling," </seg> said <persName>Dick</persName>, <seg type="word">" Can't </seg> you stop with that d&#8212;d thing you call a song?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It's enough to kill a deaf horse, much less an old nigger woman.<choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>

<p><seg type="word">“ I'm </seg> <seg type="word">sure, "</seg> commenced <persName>Toosy</persName>, apologetically, <seg type="word">" I'm </seg> sure I didn't mean to do any harm to the old 'oman, <seg type="word">but&#8212; "</seg> <seg type="word">" It's </seg> of no conse<!-- ­ -->quence young <seg type="word">man, "</seg> interposed the negress, <seg type="word">"and </seg> no apology is needed.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>'Twas but a momentary spasm that caused me to cry out, and it has <seg type="word">passed. "</seg></p>
				
<p>The words, however, to which she had given utterance, refuted her assertion of sudden illness.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I felt convinced there was some mystery connected with the old woman, and determined to make myself ac<!-- - -->quainted with it.</p>

<p><seg type="word">" You </seg> have not complied with our request, <seg type="word"> <persName>good mother</persName>, "</seg> said I, <seg type="word">" We </seg> asked you to give us some information as to the nature of the service you require of <seg type="word">us. "</seg></p>
	
<p><persName>The old woman</persName> appeared to reflect for a moment, then putting her hands to her eyes and dashing away a few tears which had gathered there, she said in a voice broken with emotion, <seg type="word">" Listen </seg> to me ; draw near all of you, and hearken to the story of  my life&#8212;nearer yet, I must whisper it to you, for I fear I have scarce enough strength left me to tell <seg type="word">it. "</seg></p>
	
<p>We drew closer as she requested, and waited eagerly for the words to fall from her lips.</p>
	
<p><seg type="word">“Do </seg> I look like one who has <seg type="word">suffered? "</seg> she began; <seg type="word">"do </seg> I look like one who has ever known what it is to be happy?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Ye answer not; but let me tell you, I was not always the miserable wretch I appear to be.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Age and misfortunes have broken my spirit, and poverty and neglect are hurrying me to the grave.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>I was and	<lb/>


<pb facs="liv_020031_0005" n="0005"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">40</seg> <seg rend="center caps">An Incident In The<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg></fw>	
am still a slave, though only one in name, for I was ever free to go and come as I liked.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I belonged to <placeName>&#8212;&#8212;estate </placeName>, and was a domes<!-- - -->tic in the great-house, until I bore my first child, when I was called upon to perform the functions of a nurse.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> From these now dry and withered breasts, the only daughter of my dear mistress drew her first sustenance, her unfortunate mother having died in giving her birth.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I nursed my young charge from her infancy, and tended her until she reached the age of twelve years, when my master resolved on sending her to <placeName>England</placeName> to be educated.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>  At her entreaty and my own, I was permitted to accompany her, and I remained in <placeName>England</placeName>with her until she returned to <placeName>Jamaica</placeName>in her 18th year.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Shortly after that event, my master died under circumstances which created suspicion of his having come to his end by violent means; but not<!-- - --> withstanding the many investigations which took place into the cause of his sudden death, the crime could not be traced home to any one, and to all but myself it has been until this night buried in mystery.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Miss Harriet</persName>, as you may suppose, was considerably affected by the death of her beloved parent, and for some months she was plunged into a state of gloom and sorrow, from which I found it difficult to arouse her.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> But unavailing regret, like every thing else, must have an end; and about two years after her father's death she married a young Englishman, named <persName>Gray</persName>, who had but a short time before arrived on the island.<choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>
	
<p><seg type="word">“ It </seg> was about this time also that I married the man with whom I had lived previous to my departure from <placeName>Jamaica </placeName>: but I had soon bitter cause to regret the step I had taken.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The little money which the kindness of my mistress had enabled me to save, was seized by my husband, who was a free man, and lavishly squandered on other women for whom he neglected me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> My spirit rose at this treatment.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> A feeling of hatred towards him sprung up in my breast, which was not a little increased by a proposition he once made to me to rob my mistress to supply his extravagance.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I do not now recollect what at the time prevented my acquainting my  mistress with the nature of the disgraceful proposal which had been made to me, but I have since had bitter reasons to blame myself for not having done so.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Need I say that I met my husband's vile proposition with scorn and revilings? <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>From that moment we met no more until three or four months after our separation, when I received a message from him, stating that he was dying, and earnestly praying me to see him once again before we parted for ever.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I hastened to him, forgetful of all my past sufferings, and found him as he had said, fast hurrying to the grave.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He recog<!-- - -->nised me immediately, and motioning all except myself out of the room, beckoned me towards his bedside.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He held out his hand, and not only implored my forgiveness, but also begged me to pray for God's mercy on his soul for, said he, <seg type="word">" there's </seg> blood  upon it; the blood of a good worthy man lies heavily on it, and I am stained not alone with the sin of ingratitude towards you, but with the heinous <lb/>
	

<pb facs="liv_020031_0006" n="0006"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">Late Rebellion in Jamaica.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg> <seg rend="right">41</seg></fw>	
crime of murder!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>The name of my late master escaped his lips&#8212;my brain reeled at the dreadful confession, and I tottered and fell sense­less to the earth.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> My husband was a corpse ere I awoke from my swoon, and I am to this moment ignorant of the motive which induced him to commit the awful deed, and of the means by which he concealed his guilt.<choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>

<p><seg type="word">" Heaven </seg> only knows what were my sufferings at that time.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>The reflection that my poor, lamented master was struck down in the prime of life by my husband's hand&#8212;that the child which I then bore in my womb was the offspring of a murderer&#8212;that perhaps it would come into the world with all the evils of its father's vile disposition inherent in its nature, drove me mad.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Perhaps it would have been better for myself had I continued in that state, but it was ordained otherwise.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The birth of my child preserved my reason, and I awoke once more to the knowledge of my unhappy condition.<choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>

<p><seg type="word">“ My </seg> mistress also gave birth at this period to a female child, which was called <persName>Alice</persName>, after its paternal grandmother.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> You know now why the song which the young gentleman sung had so great an effect on me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Alice Gray</persName>, my mistress's little daughter became my foster-child; they were playmates in their infancy, and when my young mistress sprung from infancy to girlhood, <persName>Richard</persName> became her constant attend<!-- - -->ant and favorite servant.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Oh! what a happiness, what a consolation it was to me to see the affectionate care which my son took of his little mistress! It atoned almost for my past sufferings, and led me to look forward to an old age of happiness and peace.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> How has the cup of hope been since dashed from my lips!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> How has the hand of my own offspring wrought misery to myself and to all whom I loved!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The serpent was then young; it had not yet obtained its fangs!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> But let me hasten over the few years that intervened between that period and the present.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Days, months, years fled away, varying but little the one from the other.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> My mistress had no more children during all that time, and she bestowed all her affection on <persName>Miss Alice</persName>.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Viewing with horror the idea of a separation from her only and beloved daughter, she would not send her from her, but had her educated at home; and she grew up loving and worthy to be loved.<choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>

<p><seg type="word">" Let </seg> me yet hurry on&#8212;let me hasten to the period when this unhappy country first began to be shaken by the actions of wicked, selfish, and designing men.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The year 1831 opened as brightly as any that had preceded it.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> How did it terminate? In misery: and warfare&#8212;in blood shed for its own sake; for the party-word <hi rend="italic">Freedom</hi> was but little understood by even a fourth of those who proclaimed it in the meeting-house and in the hiding-place.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It was used merely as a cloak to conceal the horrid desires of wicked and malevolent men. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Blind and misguided beings!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Ignorant tools of a grasping and avaricious faction&#8212;Is murder, freedom?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Do arson, sacrilege, ingra<!-- - -->titude, and theft, constitute freedom?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Where were the lightnings of heaven, that the goaders on of this horrible <orgName>rebellion</orgName>were not struck<lb/>


<pb facs="liv_020031_0007" n="0007"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">42</seg> <seg rend="center caps">An Incident In The<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg></fw>	
to the earth? <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Why, oh God!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> why has this beautiful land been red<!-- - --> dened with the blood of its children! <choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>

<p><seg type="word">“ It </seg> was while these fearful occurrences were at their height, that I discovered that my son was connected with a band of dissolute and fugitive negroes; but the discovery was made at too late an hour to enable me to snatch him from the gulf of depravity and sin.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He fled from me, and joined <orgName>the insurgents</orgName>.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Three months have elapsed since he left me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> In the second, after his flight, my mistress's estate was burned to the ground, herself and her husband barbarously mur<!-- - -->dered, and their daughter snatched from the flames and the assassin's knife to be reserved for a far more fearful doom.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> How I escaped in the general massacre and ruin I know not; but one week after the des<!-- - -->truction of the property, I found myself lying in an out-house which the flames had not devoured&#8212;my hands and feet blistered and scarred, my frame weak and feeble, and my mind wandering and at times unsettled.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I sat up on the bare earthen floor and strove to collect my thoughts about me, but was unequal to the task.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Throw<!-- - -->ing myself down again with the intention to take a little repose, the sound of approaching footsteps struck on my ear, and shortly after<!-- - -->wards the door opened and a human being entered the apartment.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Oh Heaven!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> What a sight met my gaze as I cast a startled glance towards the intruder!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I could not believe the evidence of my senses, but started up, drew the object to an open window, and gazed long and earnestly on the pale and emaciated countenance.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The wretched and unfortunate <persName>Alice</persName> stood, or rather crouched before me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> She was almost naked; her hair loose and torn, hung wildly about her once beautiful face; her feet were shoeless, and bleeding from many wounds, and her whole appearance haggard and wretched in the ex<!-- - -->treme.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Great Heaven!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> what a wreck she presented of her former self!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I would rather have seen her dead; I would rather have seen her years before a lifeless corpse in her young beauty than the miserable thing she then appeared.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Reason, speech, beauty, every<!-- - -->thing had fled, and but the senseless torpid frame remained.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Instinct<!-- - -->ively she must have retraced her steps to the home of her childhood.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> God only knows what she expected to find there!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> What she did find, were ruin and desolation.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I clasped her to my bosom&#8212;I washed her bleeding feet with my fast flowing tears&#8212;I tore the wretched rags from off my back, and threw them over her shivering and exhausted body&#8212;but all was unavailing.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> She died within an hour in my arms, but not before she informed me, in a temporary resuscitation of her faculties, that her former play-fellow and servant&#8212;my son, the monster to whom I had given birth, was the heartless wretch who had wrought her ruin.<choice><sic></sic><corr>”</corr></choice></p>

<p><seg type="word">" You </seg> know my story; you have now to learn what motive brought me hither.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> 'Tis revenge, full and ample revenge.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The blood of my dead mistress's child calls to me for vengeance&#8212;and though my own offspring be the sacrifice, shall have it.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> But come, come at once,<lb/>
	

<pb facs="liv_020031_0008" n="0008"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">Late Rebellion in Jamaica.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg> <seg rend="right">43</seg></fw>	
ere the feelings of a parent regain possession of my heart; come ere I repent me of the deed I am about to <seg type="word">commit. "</seg></p>
	
<p>She rose as she ceased speaking.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Her tall form appeared to expand to a gigantic size, as re-armed with the recital of her woes, she drew herself up and gazed on us as if she would have said, <seg type="word">" See </seg>, my mis<!-- - -->fortunes have not yet broken my spirit; I can still act and think for <seg type="word">myself. "</seg> <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Heaven only knows what thoughts were passing in her mind at that moment.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Her eyes flashed, her nostrils dilated, and her breast heaved as though a fearful struggle were going on within her, but not another word escaped her lips at that time; and she soon after regained her composure.</p>
	
<p>The storm had now almost subsided.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The wind would moan and sigh occasionally through the thick foliage of the numberless trees that surrounded the house, but there was no longer any rain or thun<!-- - -->der, and the earth exhaled that peculiar odour which usually rises from it after a heavy rain.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It yet wanted two or three hours of day<!-- - -->light, and <persName>the old woman</persName> urged us to take advantage of the remaining hours of darkness, and hasten in pursuit of her wretched son.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Ac<!-- - -->cordingly we made every preparation necessary for the supposed difficulties of the expedition&#8212;cleaned and dried our firelocks, exam<!-- - -->ined our ammunition, and found that, fortunately, our powder was perfectly dry; and put everything else in an effective condition.</p>
	
<p>	After about an hour's hard walking, we followed our strange guide into a narrow defile, overhung by towering and massive rocks.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> A mountain torrent, swollen by the late rains, roared and splashed down a precipitous gully that ran along the entire line of road, extend<!-- - -->ing in many instances over large portions of the path itself.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Poor <persName>Toosy</persName>'s misfortunes recommenced as we entered on this portion of our march.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> First his hat was knocked over his eyes by an overhang<!-- - -->ing branch; then he lost one boot, which was with difficulty reco<!-- - -->vered; at another time his lankly feet became entangled in some under-wood, and he was thrown on his face with some violence.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Again he lost his footing and plumped up to his middle in a deep hole filled with water; and at last, in sheer desperation, he sat himself down on a piece of fallen rock, and swore not to budge another foot farther.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <seg type="word">" Take </seg> your hand from off <seg type="word">mine, "</seg> said he to one of us who stood by him, <seg type="word">" its </seg> as cold and clammy as ice: take it away, I say, and leave me here, I am determined I vont walk another inch.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> They may do vot they like with me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> They may shoot me, or hang me, or do anything else they please; but I vont go on to be drowned in any more cussed holes.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> There, now go and leave me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> O Lord!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> O Lord!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> vot's this a-coming to me?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Take it off, take it off; it's a climming up my <seg type="word">face. "</seg><space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He shook his right arm violently, and a snake of about a yard in length rapidly uncoiled itself from the limb, and escaped into the bush.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The outcries which the frightened <persName>Toosey</persName> made startled the echoes to so great degree, that I have no doubt many a sleeping bird was deprived of its morning's nap.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> From one extreme<lb/>
	

<pb facs="liv_020031_0009" n="0009"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">44</seg> <seg rend="center caps">An Incident In The<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg></fw>	
the unfortunate youth fled to another, and he begged and prayed us to take him away as soon as possible.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The dangers of remaining where he was appeared to him much greater than any which he might probably encounter in the onward march; and he prepared with much alacrity to accompany us the remainder of the way.</p>
	
<p>Order being once more established, we hasted to make up for the lost time, particularly as some red streaks in the east warned us that the dawn was approaching.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Our way led, for about two miles farther, up the defile, when it was suddenly brought to a close by what appeared to us to be an insurmountable obstacle.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> An enor<!-- - -->mous rock, clothed to its summit with rank vegetation; completely blocked up the path, and barred all egress in that direction.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Finding himself thus circumstanced, doubts of the honesty and good faith of our guide began to enter the mind of <persName>Serjeant S&#8212;</persName>.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He imagined she had led us into this trap in order to give us into the hands of one of the numerous gangs of <orgName>insurgent negroes</orgName> who roamed about in all directions; and his alarm momentarily increased.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Daylight was now fast stealing on us, and it afforded some satisfaction to know that in the event of <persName>Serjeant S&#8212;'s</persName> suspicions being confirmed, we should at least be able to see and oppose the danger by which we were surrounded.</p>
	
<p><seg type="word">“See </seg>," cried <persName>Serjeant S&#8212;</persName> suddenly <seg type="word">" Look </seg> there<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> to the right!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> By heaven there are figures moving on the hill. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Stand to your arms my men.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> We must now sell our lives <seg type="word"> dearly. " </seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="word">“ Hola </seg>! <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Draw not a trigger on our <seg type="word">lives," </seg> interposed our guide, <seg type="word">" the</seg> men on the rock above are friends; they come to aid us in this <seg type="word">enterprise. " </seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="word">“ How </seg> know we that?<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> What proof have we that you have not entrapped us into an ambush? <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Look to yourself, <persName>old woman</persName>, your life shall answer for your <seg type="word">treachery. "</seg></p>
	
<p>	The <persName>Serjeant</persName> stepped forward as he spoke with the intention of seizing her, but she sprung aside with an agility which her age did not betoken, and quickly scrambling up one side of the rock, divided with her powerful arm a thick cluster of underwood, and stepped into the path she had opened for herself.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> A few seconds elapsed and she once more appeared on a portion of the rock which jutted far out into the air.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <seg type="word">" You </seg> forced me to act as I have <seg type="word">done,"</seg> she exclaimed, as she took up her position above us, <seg type="word">" one </seg> word from my lips and not a life among you would be spared&#8212;one musket discharged on this spot and you draw down destruction on your heads! <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Think you that I brought you here to murder you. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>You have heard the story of my life&#8212;do I look like one who has not felt, keenly felt, all the sorrows I described? <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>Heaven pardon you for your murderous doubts!<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> I will yet redeem the pledge I gave you, but think not you have frightened me into doing <seg type="word">so. " </seg><space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <seg type="word">" See! ”</seg> she added, as at a signal twelve or fifteen men rushed down the steep rocks and gathered around her, <seg type="word">"see </seg>! I could have crushed you all had I chosen to do<lb/>


<pb facs="liv_020031_0010" n="0010"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">Late Rebellion in Jamaica.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg> <seg rend="right">45</seg></fw>	
<seg type="word">so." </seg><space extent="1" unit="chars"/> She disappeared behind a portion of the rocks as she spoke, and soon, after we perceived her descending into the defile, accompa<!-- - -->nied by three of her followers.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> As she advanced <persName>Serjeant S&#8212;</persName> stepped forward and in a few words expressed his gratitude for her forbearance.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He now declared his readiness to follow with his men whithersoever she chose to lead him; and giving the word to march, we cautiously ascended a narrow beaten track which our guide pointed out to us.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It was now day-break, but a thick fog which rose from the defile, and overhung the surrounding hills, rendered it ne<!-- - -->cessary that we should tread with the utmost care the precarious path by which we mounted into the region of rock and wood high over our heads.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> A quarter of an hour's toil and exertion brought us in front of what appeared to be a deep fissure in the mountain, the en<!-- - -->trance to which was partly concealed by a quantity of brush-wood and fragments of limestone.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Cautioning us not to utter a word, and to keep within call, but not to show ourselves in the direct path to the cave, the negress strode towards it, followed by the three negroes who, I had forgotten to say, were armed with old rusty fowling pieces and cutlasses.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The loud barking of a dog within the cave be<!-- - -->trayed the approach of the intruder, and the sound of a confused noise in the same direction, shortly after reached our ears.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It was evident that the tenants of the cave were alarmed.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The negress beckoned us to approach, which we did as quickly as the nature of the ground would permit.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> No one had yet issued from the cavern; the persons concealed within were doubtless acting on the defensive, and as it appeared a matter of no difficulty for a party of resolute men to defend the place for a long time, we began to dread that, un<!-- - -->prepared as we were to carry on a siege, we would be compelled to retrace our steps without accomplishing the purpose for which we had severely and laboriously toiled.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Serjeant S&#8212;</persName> called an immediate council of war, and it was determined to dispose of the few men he had under his command with as much effect as possible.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Myself and another were ordered to advance towards the left of the cavern, where a narrow path was distinctly visible, to intercept whomsoever might attempt to escape in that direction; two of the negroes, and as many more of our own party, were directed to clamber over the rocks, and endeavour to discover if there were any outlet at the back of the cave; while <persName>Toosy</persName> and the remaining negro were posted some yards below, in the track by which we had ascended, and ordered give immediate alarm should any hostile movement be observed in that quarter.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;</persName> himself with the negress and <persName>Dick</persName>, under<!-- - -->took to keep possession of the path leading to the mouth of the cavern, and to resist every effort of the beseiged to escape. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Having thus disposed of our small force, we waited as patiently as we could until the opportunity should offer for the exercise of more vigorous and decisive measures.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Half an hour passed away, and matters still remained in the same position.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The sun rose in splendour, and<lb/>


<pb facs="liv_020031_0011" n="0011"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">46</seg> <seg rend="center caps">An Incident In The Late Rebellion of Jamaica.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg></fw>	
dispersed the thick mist which surrounded us.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Exhausted with our previous exertions, and anxious to bring the business to a speedy ter<!-- - -->mination, <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;</persName> now determined to assail the entrance of the cavern at all risks.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He recalled the party under my command which had been posted on the hill, and desiring us to co-operate with him, marched resolutely towards the cave.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Before, however, we had advanced twenty yards, the brushwood which partly concealed the mouth of the cavern was removed, and a young negro of herculean build presented himself at the entrance.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>  He was armed with a long cavalry pistol, which he carried in his hand; by his side hung a broad shining cutlass, and in his belt was stuck what appeared to be a sort of dirk. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He desired us to halt, and presented his pistol to enforce his command. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Utterly regardless, however, of the threaten<!-- - -->ing aspect of the rebel, <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;</persName> commanded us to move forward, but his temerity well nigh cost him his life.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>  A sudden report, the sharp rustling in the air as the bullet flew through it, and the rapid disappearance of the rebel from the spot on which he had been standing, told that he had vainly expended his shot, and had retreated into the cave.</p>
	
<p><seg type="word">" Onward </seg>," exclaimed <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;</persName>, <seg type="word">" and</seg> quickly too, but be careful of being surprised in the <seg type="word">cavern. " </seg> <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> We were now joined by the party who had been sent to learn if there were any other entrance to the cave. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> They reported their failure, which perhaps was fortunate for them, as the sequel will shew.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Our force being thus augmented, we did not hesitate for one moment to enter the stronghold of <persName>the rebel</persName>.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> We 	<choice><sic>"</sic><corr></corr></choice>carried it at the point of the bayonet, <choice><sic>"</sic><corr></corr></choice> but the object of our pursuit was nowhere to be found.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> We could not discover the slightest trace of him.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> He had vanished like a vision, as <persName>Toosy</persName>afterwards observed.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Strewed about the interior of the cave, were some broken victuals, a breaker of water, and some spirits in a bottle.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> In an aperture in the solid rock was a bed composed of dried leaves and grass, covered with several pieces of ragged blanketing, on which lay the  dead  body of a dog, doubtless the same which had warned <persName>the rebel</persName> of an approach, and which he must have slain under the apprehension of its betraying him.</p>
	
<p>	Annoyed at our want of success, and astonished at the apparent mystery in which the escape of <persName>the rebel</persName> was shrouded, <persName>Sergeant S&#8212;</persName> gave strict injunctions to institute an immediate and rigid search throughout the cave, in the hope of discovering some hidden outlet or secret hiding place, for which the cavern offered many faci<!-- - -->lities.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The words, however, had scarcely left his lips, when a loud cry reached our ears.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> It appeared to come from the spot on which we had left <persName>Toosy</persName> and the negro; and impressed with the idea that <persName>the rebel</persName> had found some means to quit the cave, and was then escaping, we hurried out with the view to intercept and take him.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> My blood runs cold, and my cheeks pale, even at this distance of time, when the recollection of that day comes over me.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The hand of<lb/>
	

<pb facs="liv_020031_0012" n="0012"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">The Pleasures of Drink.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/></seg> <seg rend="right">47</seg></fw>	
death was almost on us; certain and deadly destruction hung hover<!-- - -->ing over our heads but one minute before we rushed from the cavern.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> We had scarcely gone one hundred yards, when, with a report like a whole park of artillery discharged simultaneously, and with a concus<!-- - -->sion that shook the earth for an immense distance around, the cave was blown to atoms and scattered in a thousand fragments in all directions.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> For some moments we stood as if rooted to the earth.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> We could neither move nor speak. <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The suddenness of the occurrence, the horrible intention of <persName>the rebel</persName> to involve us in his own dreadful fate, from which we were saved only by the merest accident, struck us all as being so terrible and astounding, that for some minutes we were bereft of motion.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/>  Gradually, however, we recovered ourselves, when the first words uttered were thanks to the Almighty One, who had preserved our lives in the moment of danger.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> This duty being paid, we looked about to observe the effects of the explosion.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> The scorched and disfigured body of <persName>the rebel</persName> was stretched out at no great distance from us; beside it was the mangled remains of his dog, and it struck us as being an extraordinary instance of retributive justice that the slaughtered animal should lie side by side with him who had deprived it of life, within an hour after the act had been committed.</p>
	
<p>	We never learned what became of the old negress.<space extent="1" unit="chars"/> Whether she perished in the cave, or escaped with us, we had no means of ascer<!-- - -->taining; but she was never afterwards seen or heard of.</p>

            </div>
        </body>   
    </text>
</TEI>
