<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- Next line points to online XSL; use red triangle button in oXygen when done to transform file and check encoding -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="../omv-integrated.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020064">
	<!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>“Special General Meeting of the London Missionary Society” (Excerpt)</title>
				<!-- Title without date -->
				<!-- Check https://onemorevoice.org/bibliography.html for "canonical" name. -->
				<title type="normalized">‘Special General Meeting of the London Missionary Society’ (Excerpt)</title>
				<!-- If title surrounded by double quotations, then replace with single quotations here; otherwise remove -->
				<title type="alternative">“Special General Meeting of the London Missionary Society” (Excerpt), September 1836</title>
				<!-- Title, date -->
				<author>Hankey, William Alers, 1771/2-1859</author>
				<!-- First author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates) -->
				<author role="first">Hankey, William Alers</author>
				<!-- First author only: Surname, Forename -->
				<author role="first-normalized">William Alers Hankey</author>
				<!-- First author only: Forename Surname -->
				<author>Tzatzoe, Jan, 1792-1868</author>
				<!-- Second author, etc.: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates); if no second author, remove this line -->
				<author role="normalized">Jan Tzatzoe</author>
				<!-- Second author, etc.: Forename Surname; if no second author, remove this line -->
				<author>Stoffles, Andries, late 1770s-1837</author>
				<!-- Second author, etc.: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing re: dates); if no second author, remove this line -->
				<author role="normalized">Andries Stoffles</author>
				<!-- Second author, etc.: Forename Surname; if no second author, remove this line -->
				<principal>Heather F. Ball</principal>
				<principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
				<!-- Only people involved in the actual transcription should be listed below; remove everyone else -->
				<respStmt xml:id="AM">
					<name>Anne Martin</name>
					<resp>Transcription</resp>
					<resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
					<resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt xml:id="AW">
					<name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
					<resp>Transcription</resp>
					<resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
					<resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>One More Voice</authority>
				<publisher>Livingstone Online</publisher>
				<pubPlace>University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2021</date>
				<idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_020064</idno>
				<!-- Insert LEAP ID, e.g. "liv_020010 -->
				<!-- Edit <availability> as relevant -->
				<availability>
					<p>Critically-edited text copyright <hi rend="italic">One More Voice</hi>.</p>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
						International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>

			<!-- Use this version of <sourceDesc> if published text -->
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr n="narrow">
						<!-- Default is journal/periodical article; if book section, change to <monogr n="book-section">; if columns are narrow, use <monogr n="narrow">; combinations also OK: <monogr n="book-section narrow"> -->
						<title>The Missionary Magazine and Chronicle, Relating Chiefly to the Missions of the London Missionary Society</title>
						<!-- Publication title: journal or book -->
						<!-- Author here used only for books -->
						<!-- Forename Surname-->
						<!-- Editor (if known; otherwise leave blank -->
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
							<!-- Volume (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
							<!-- Issue (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<biblScope unit="pages">54-68</biblScope>
							<!-- Pages (if known; otherwise leave blank) -->
							<date>September 1836</date>
							<!-- Item date; same as date in <title type="alternative"> above -->
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<bibl type="sourceMetadata">
					<!-- Title without date -->
					<!-- Same as <title> above --> 
					<title>“Special General Meeting of the London Missionary Society” (Excerpt)</title>
					<!-- Each author: Surname, Forename, Dates (if known; otherwise nothing) -->
					<!-- Same as <author> above -->
					<!-- xml:id = each author's initials -->
					<author xml:id="WAH">Hankey, William Alers, 1771/2-1859</author>
					<author xml:id="JT">Tzatzoe, Jan, 1792-1868</author>
					<author xml:id="AS">Stoffles, Andries, late 1770s-1837</author>
					<!-- Same as <date> in previous section -->
					<!-- Write out date: Day Month Year -->
					<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
					<date type="composition" when="1836-09">10 August 1836</date>
					<date type="publication" when="1836-09">September 1836</date>
					<!-- Can be type="composition" or type="publication" -->
					<!-- See item for composition place; remove if not given -->
					<placeName type="compositionPlace">Exeter Hall, London</placeName>
					<!-- Can be "compositionPlace" or "focusRegion" -->
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
			<!-- End of published text <sourceDesc> -->

		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry -->
				<!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!-- Use one <change> for each instance of revision -->
			<!-- Always place most recent <change> at top -->
			<!-- Describe using one of the phrases associated with your name above -->
			<!-- E.g., Transcription or TEI Encoding or Proofing, etc. -->
			<!-- @when = YYYY-MM-DD -->
			<!-- @who = #[your initials], e.g., #AW or #HB or #MBT -->
			<change when="2021-06-23" who="#AM"></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text><!-- If file contains custom CSS with rotation, add n="rotate-toggle" -->
		<!-- Actual color of the MS page; AW will insert appropriate color; remove @n if white because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->
		<body>
			<!-- Acutal color of the writing; AW will use auto-suggested values; remove @rend if black because that's the default color; also remove for publications -->
			<div>

<!-- ndash: - -->
<!-- mdash:&#8212;-->


<!-- Anne, for printed texts, break up lines as they appear on the page, but no need to put <lb/> at the beginning of each line. -->

<!-- For Tzatzoe, page 0002 (printed page 55), from "The Chairman then rose, and taking Jan Tzatzoe by the hand..." to page 0003 (printed page 56), ending with "I will not say more". -->

<pb facs="liv_020064_0002" n="0002"/>

<fw><seg rend="center caps">For September, 1836.</seg> <seg rend="right">55</seg></fw>

	<div rend="center">
<gap extent="18" unit="lines" agent="omitted-text"/><!-- Text from previous section. AW -->
<lb/>
	</div>

	<div>
<cb rend="right"/>
<p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Chairman</hi> then rose, and taking
<persName>Jan Tzatzoe</persName> by the hand, addressed him to
the following effect:&#8212;In the name of this
large meeting, which represents a body still
greater than itself, extending throughout
this kingdom, nay, I may say, throughout
the world, I am happy in giving you the
right hand of fellowship. I congratulate
you, in their name, on what God has been
pleased by his grace to do for you, and
when you return, you will be accompanied
with our warmest prayers that you may be
upheld, and that you may grow in spiritual
strength even unto the end.</p>
<p><hi rend="smallcaps"><persName>Jan Tzatzoe</persName></hi> then stood forward, and
was received with loud expressions of grateful
joy. He addressed the meeting in the
<term type="collective">Dutch</term> language to the following effect, <persName>Mr.
Read, jun.</persName> acting as interpreter:&#8212;I am
surprised to see so many people assembled
in the house of God. I am happy to have
the opportunity of seeing those <term type="collective">Christian</term>
friends who sent out <persName>Dr. Vanderkemp</persName>, <persName>Dr. 
Philip</persName>, <persName>Mr. Read</persName>, and all the other Missionaries.
I thank God that you sent out
these devoted men, who came to <country>South
Africa</country> when we were shot with bullets,
and when there was nothing but blood-shed
in that ill-fated country. There was nothing
to be seen but the bullet and assagai, the
bow and the arrow; but the word of God 
has continued to this day. You must not
be wearied in well-doing; the work is still
great, and the work must be spread in the<lb/>


<pb facs="liv_020064_0003" n="0003"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">56</seg> <seg rend="center caps">Missionary Magazine</seg></fw>

<cb rend="left"/>
world. God might convert the world by
his own power, but he employs instruments
to bring men to himself. You must send
us schoolmasters and Missionaries, elevate
us and do us good, and raise subscriptions
for the <orgName>Missionary Society</orgName>. We cannot
allow you to be at rest till this great work
is finished. When we shall have received
the word of God, and shall be in a condition
to send out that word, we will form Missionary
Societies, and we will send forth
the word of God to others. God is great
who has promised it, and he will extend his
word in the world. God is about to do
away with bloodshed and war, and every
thing that is sinful. War is bad, and other
things have been bad, but good is come out
of evil. Who knows, if these things had not
taken place, whether Missionaries would
ever have gone out to that country? If
we wish to serve God we must expect
persecution; we must expect the wicked to
oppose us; but God will surely finish his
own work. When the word of God came
among us we were like the wild <term type="animal">beasts</term>,
we knew nothing! we were so wild that
there was nothing but war and bloodshed.
Every one was against his neighbour; there
was no confidence between man and man,
and each man tried to destroy his brother.
The word of God has turned us; the word
of God has brought peace, has reconciled
one man to another, and in us is fulfilled
that text of scripture, "The <term type="animal">wolf</term> shall dwell
with the <term type="animal">lamb</term>." I thank the <term type="collective">English</term> nation
for what we have received at their
hands. You are our friends; we are your
children. I am like one of your own children.
I have been brought up under the
laws of <country>England</country>, and I have enjoyed all the
privileges of your missions. When we signed
the treaty with the <orgName><term type="collective">British</term> Government</orgName> at
the <geogName type="river"><term type="animal">Buffalo</term> River</geogName>, a paper was read, which
told us that we then became the children of
the king of <country>England</country>, and that we were now
<term type="collective">British</term> subjects. If we are the children of
<country>England</country>, and if one with yourselves, let us
enjoy the privileges of <term type="collective">Britons</term>. Many
<term type="collective">Englishmen</term> in the colonies are bad, but I
will hardly believe that those <term type="collective">Englishmen</term>
belong to you. You are a different race of
men&#8212;they are <term type="collective">South Africans</term>&#8212;they are
not <term type="collective">Englishmen</term>. I have now seen the
<term type="collective">English</term> nation. I have travelled a little in
this country: I have met with a friendly reception
wherever I have gone; and I can
say you are now my friends. I know my
friends. Do not forget us. Our eyes are
upon you. You are our parents. You
sent us the word of God. I hope you will
still continue to send out that word. I
would thank you for ever having sent <persName>Dr.
Philip</persName> to our country. This gentleman
never sleeps in <bloc>Africa</bloc>; he is always doing
good, he is always protecting us. He is
<lb/>
<lb/>

<cb rend="right"/>
our witness; he is a witness of the state of
the colonies, and he is a witness of what
God has done amongst us. He knows what
we have suffered: he suffered with us. He,
like his Master, went about doing good,
although he was persecuted by man. Every
man who wishes to do good must expect
persecution. Could they destroy him, they
would have done it; but they cannot, for he
is in the hand of God. Very few people in
the world love truth: they love darkness.
Truth brings every thing to light; it reveals
what is hidden. But there are very few
people who will allow that they do not love
the truth. They wish to take justice and
injustice in one hand. Every man knows
what is truth, but he wishes to mix the
truth with falsehood. Some people are
afraid to stand out for the truth; other
people won't stand out for the truth; and
others are ashamed of the truth; truth is
the most important thing in the world. It
is honest. Where there is no truth there
is no true honour. We must all adore the
truth&#8212;every man. The word of God is
truth. The word of God tells us to do good;
and the word of God tells us to stand on the
truth. We ought to adhere to the truth, and
to stand by the truth. I will not say more.</p>

<!-- end of first extract - straight onto Stoffles extract AM -->
<!-- For Stoffels, page 0003 (printed page 56), from "Andries Stoffles then rose to address the meeting..." to page 0005 (printed page 58), ending with "I am yours". -->

<p><hi rend="smallcaps"><persName>Andries Stoffles</persName></hi> then rose to address
the meeting. He was received with the
most cordial greetings.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Chairman</hi>, taking him by the hand,
thus addressed him:&#8212;In the name of this
meeting, and of the <orgName><choice><sic>society</sic><corr>Society</corr></choice></orgName>, I congratulate
you on your arrival in this country; but
above all do I congratulate you on the
great blessing which you received in your
own country, through the instrumentality
of the Missionaries sent by this <orgName><choice><sic>society</sic><corr>Society</corr></choice></orgName>. We
are happy in seeing you as a visible token and
evidence of what the power of God can do,
and his grace perform in the hearts of men.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="smallcaps"><term type="collective">Christian</term> <term type="collective">Hottentot</term></hi> then addressed
the meeting in the <term type="collective">Dutch</term> language,
<persName>Mr. Read</persName> acting as interpreter. He spoke
nearly as follows:&#8212;God has done great
things for <bloc>Africa</bloc>, for which we have
reason to be glad. God has done great
things for me, in that I am permitted to address
you on this occasion. <persName>Dr. Vanderkemp</persName> 
and <persName>Mr. Read</persName> told us that the <term type="collective">English</term>
nation sent us the word of God. I will not
dwell upon what we were before, but I will
tell you what the Bible has done for us.
There are three gentlemen in this country
who are witnesses to what <term type="collective">Africans</term> were&#8212;
<persName>Dr. Philip</persName>, <persName>Mr. Read</persName>, and <persName>Mr. Campbell</persName>.
I wish to tell you what the Bible has done
for <bloc>Africa</bloc>. What would have become of
the <term type="collective">Hottentot</term> nation, and every <term type="collective">black man</term>
in <country>South Africa</country>, had you kept the word of
God to yourselves? When you received
the word of God you thought of other nations
who had not that word. When the<lb/>

<pb facs="liv_020064_0004" n="0004"/>
<fw><seg rend="center caps">For September, 1836.</seg> <seg rend="right">57</seg></fw>

<cb rend="left"/>
Bible came amongst us we were naked; we
lived in caves and on the tops of the mountains;
we had no clothes, we painted our
bodies with red paint. At first we were
surprised to hear the truths of the Bible.
The Bible charmed us out of the caves,
and from the tops of the mountains. The
Bible made us throw away all our old
customs and practices, and we lived among
civilized men. We are tame men now.
Now we know there is a God; now we
know we are accountable creatures before
God. But what was our state before the
Bible came? We knew none of these
things. We knew nothing about heaven.
We knew not who made heaven and earth.
The Bible is the only light for every man
that dwells on the face of the earth. I
thank God, in the name of every <term type="collective">Hottentot</term>&#8212;of 
all the <term type="collective">Hottentots</term> in <country>South Africa</country>,
that I have seen the face of <term type="collective">Englishmen</term>. I
have been looking whether a <term type="collective">Hottentot</term>
found his way to this meeting, but I have
looked in vain: I am the only one. I
have travelled with the Missionaries in
taking the Bible to the <term type="collective">Bushmen</term>, and other
nations. When the word of God has been
preached, the <term type="collective">bushman</term> has thrown away his
bow and arrows. I have accompanied the
Bible to the <term type="collective">Caffre</term> nation, and when the
Bible spoke, the <term type="collective">Caffre</term> threw away his shield
and all his vain customs. I went to <placeName>Latakoo</placeName>,
and they threw away all their evil
works, they threw away their assagais, and
became the children of God. The only way
to reconcile man to man is to instruct man
in the truths of the Bible. I say again,
the Bible is the light, and where the Bible
comes, the minds of men are enlightened.
Where the Bible is not, there is nothing
but darkness; it is dangerous, in fact, to
travel through such a nation. Where the
Bible is not, man does not hesitate to kill
his fellow; he never even repents afterwards
of having committed murder. I thank you
to-day: I do nothing but thank you to-day.
Are there any of the old <term type="collective">Englishmen</term> here
who sent out the word of God? I give
them my thanks : if there are not, I give it
to their children. The Bible is still amongst
us. I will not say much. I have told you that
there are three witnesses who came with me,
and they will speak of things. Your Missionaries,
when they came to us, suffered
with us, and they wept with us, and they
struggled for us, till they obtained for us the
charter of our liberties&#8212;the fiftieth ordinance.
(The animation with which the last
clause of this sentence was uttered by <persName>Andries
Stoffles</persName>, produced a deep sensation
throughout the whole auditory.) When the
fiftieth ordinance was published, we were
then brought to the light. Then did the
young men begin to learn to write and read.
Through that ordinance we got infant-
schools, and our little infants have been instructed,
<lb/>
<lb/>

<cb rend="right"/>
and they are making progress in
learning. You, the posterity of the old <term type="collective">Englishmen</term>,
I address you on this occasion; I
am standing on the bones of your ancestors,
and I call upon you, their children, to-day,
to come over and help us. Do you know
what we want? We want schools and 
school-masters&#8212;we want to be like yourselves.
You see before you two men of two different
nations. You who have put your money into
the plates, but who never saw the fruits of
your labours, I stand here before you as the
fruit of your exertions. I thank you again, in
the name of all the <term type="collective">Hottentots</term>, that I have
been permitted to speak one word among
you. But I cannot sit down without thanking
you for having sent <persName>Dr. Philip</persName>. We
owe much to <persName>Dr. Philip</persName> and to the Missionaries
of this <orgName>Society</orgName>. What we have, we
received by them; and it is the Missionaries
of your <orgName>Society</orgName> that have done for us so
many great things. I am to thank you
that you did not keep <persName>Dr. Philip</persName> in this
country. You sent him out young, and we
have brought him back old. But he is like
a young man in that country; he goes
about to encourage schools, and to see that
the work of education prospers. When
<persName>Dr. Philip</persName> first commenced his travels, we
did not see the end of his labours. When
he visited the <term type="collective">Bushmen</term>, we did not know
why he visited them. I call upon you in
the name of <term type="collective">Hottentots</term>, send over men to
help us. We want infant-schools. I see
that the infant-schools will be the greatest
blessing that has ever been conferred on
<country>South Africa</country>. I will tell you a story about
my little grandchild. The little girl came
to me and said, "Grandpapa, do you know
how to make cloth?" I said to her, "Do
you mean to teach me? I have seen <term type="collective">white
men</term>, and I do not know how it is made.
How do you know?" She said, "If you
come over to the schools to-morrow we will
tell you, and we will show you how cloth is
made." I felt rather unwilling, but I went
to the school the next day, and I was quite
surprised when I saw it. I have come to
<country>England</country>, and I have no time to stop with
you in this country; for I want to go back
and tell the little children in <bloc>Africa</bloc> I have
seen every thing you told me of. I hope
you will not be wearied in well-sdoing.
Perhaps some may say, "The <term type="collective">Hottentots</term>
have had the word of God a long time; they
can do well for themselves." But no, we
cannot do without you. Consider us as
your children, and we will call you our parents.
I will not say much more, yet I must
tell you of one gentleman in <bloc>Africa</bloc> to whom
the <orgName>Society</orgName> owes much. There is a gentleman
in <bloc>Africa</bloc> who has lately become acquainted
with us. When we first saw that
gentleman, we thought that he was only the
friend of the <term type="collective">Hottentots</term>, but we find now
that he is the friend of every man. But<lb/>
<cb/>


<pb facs="liv_020064_0005" n="0005"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">58</seg> <seg rend="center caps">Missionary Magazine</seg></fw>
<lb/>
<cb rend="left"/>
this man was quite different to every other
man; for the <term type="collective">Hottentots</term> said, he is our
friend; and the <term type="collective">Caffre</term> says, he is my
friend; and the <term type="collective">English</term> settler says, he is
my friend; and the <term type="collective">Dutch</term> <term type="collective">boor</term> says, he is
my friend; so that man is the friend of all
men. The name of that gentleman is <persName>Fairbairn</persName>.
I can compare <persName>Mr. Fairbairn</persName> to
nothing else but a man having a pair of
scales in his hands, and he throws the white
man in one scale and the black man in the
other, and he makes them equal. I still
continue to thank you, I thank you for
every good <term type="collective">Englishman</term> who has left this
country. I have only told you what the
Bible has done for others, but I have not told
you what it has done for my own soul. But
I will not say any thing about myself; the
three men whom I have named will tell you
all about me. There is <persName>Dr. Philip</persName>, and
<persName>Mr. Campbell</persName>, and <persName>Mr. Read</persName>. When your
first Missionaries, <persName>Dr. Vanderkemp</persName> and
<persName>Mr. Read</persName>, came to us, and when I heard
the bell ring, I did not know what it was. I
thought the people were going to church to
have a meal together. I heard the minister
preaching. I said, "I suppose he is counting."
I listened, and said, "No, he is not
counting." I came to church again the next
day, when I heard the bell ring. The next
time I came to a place of worship the
preacher spoke of every thing that I had
fone from my childhood. I said to myself,
"This is very strange, surely my cousin
must have gone to the Missionary and told
him all about me." My cousin said, "No,
I never spoke about you to the Missionary.
The Bible is that thing that tells you all
about your own heart." Blessed be God, he
has opened my mind, and I have received
the truths of the Bible, and acknowledge
it to be the word of God. I am so convinced
that the Bible is the word of God,
and of the blessings that we derive from it,
that were there any thing I could do for my
own countrymen, I would do it; but it is
the work of God to do it. My nation is
poor and degraded, but the word of God is
their stay and their hope. The word of God
has brought my nation so far, that if a
<term type="collective">Hottentot</term> young lady and an <term type="collective">English</term>
young lady were walking with their faces
from me, I would take them both to be
<term type="collective">English</term> ladies. Do instruct us&#8212;I say
again, do instruct us! Do not leave us to
ourselves. Hold us under your arm. We
are coming on; we are improving; we will
soon all be one. The Bible makes all nations
one. The Bible brings wild man and
civilized together. The Bible is our light.
The <term type="collective">Hottentot</term> nation was almost exterminated,
but the Bible has brought the
nations together, and here am I before you.
You have the honour, I claim nothing.
You give us your pence and your farthings,
and here am I; I am yours.
</p>
	</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
