<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/transcription-omv-journal.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><!-- http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-XSLT/ -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="liv_020003"><!-- Change @xml:id -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes on African Geography</title><!-- Change -->
                <title type="alternate">Notes on African Geography</title><!-- Change; note addition of date -->
				<author>MacQueen, James, 1778-1870</author>
                <author>[Lief Ben Saeid]</author><!-- Change -->
				<author>[Wogga, Thomas]</author><!-- Change -->
                <principal>Adrian S. Wisnicki</principal>
                <respStmt xml:id="AM">
                    <name>Anne Martin</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
				<respStmt xml:id="HB">
                    <name>Heather F. Ball</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt xml:id="AW">
                    <name>Adrian S. Wisnicki</name>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <resp>Editorial Decisions</resp>
					<resp>Proofing</resp>
					<resp>Coding Review</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
                <publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2018</date><!-- Change if necessary -->
                <idno type="LEAP-ID">liv_020003</idno><!-- Change -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct type="journal">
					<monogr>
						<title>Journal of the Royal Geographical Society of London</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="vol">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="pages">371-76</biblScope>
							<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
							<publisher>The Royal Geographical Society</publisher>
							<date>1845</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
                <bibl type="sourceMetadata">
					<title>Notes on African Geography</title><!-- Change -->                	
					<author xml:id="JM">MacQueen, James, 1778-1870</author>
                	<author xml:id="LBS">[Lief Ben Saeid]</author><!-- Change -->
					<author xml:id="TW">[Wogga, Thomas]</author><!-- Change -->
					<title>Notes on African Geography</title><!-- Change -->
                    <date type="publication" when="1854">1854</date><!-- Change, including attributes -->
                    <placeName type="focusRegion">Central Africa</placeName><!-- Change -->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
				<!-- For language abbreviations, see https://www.iana.org/assignments/language-subtag-registry/language-subtag-registry --> 
				<!-- English should be first, then add all other languages in alphabetical order. -->
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="und">Undetermined</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
			<!-- Change @when, @who, and work description below. -->
			<!-- Note that @who initials are taken from <respStmt> above -->
			<!-- Add new <change> elements below as needed. -->
			<!-- Note that the most recent <change> should always be placed first, at the top -->
            <change when="2018-08-02" who="#AW">OCR Conversion and TEI encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>


<!-- Note: This text has the feature of having an extra space or two anytime there is a new sentence, but I don't think we need to reproduce that unless, Heather and Anne, you do? AW -->

    <text>
       	<body><!-- Change; this is the color of the MS page; value can be any color --><!-- No need to specify if it's white. AW -->
			<div rend="black" hand="BG"><!-- Change; this is the color of the writing; only use auto-suggested values -->

	<pb facs="liv_020003_0004" n="0004"/>

<!-- Don't worry about the fact that the text in the upper part of the page (including the heading) and on the preceding pages is missing. That appears in the other template. AW -->

	<div resp="#TW"><!-- I'm using @resp to mark the name of the informant for this seciton. This practice may change. AW -->
<head rend="italic">II. Information obtained from Thomas Wogga, an African.</head>
<p rend="no-indent"><hi rend="smallcaps">This</hi> man is at present in this country: he had been previously,
fourteen or fifteen years, on board of a British man-of-war; and
liberated from slavery about the year 1815 or 1816. He is a
native of a country which he calls Kimcoul; and which, as far as
the accounts which he gives are correct, must be situated near the
sources of the Tshalda, in about 10° N. and 18° to 19° E. He
was exactly 68 days actually travelling from thence to Calabar,
and always in the direction of the setting sun. From the rate at
which he travelled, and the time occupied, he must have made
good at least 10 geographical miles daily, if not more. He states
that Donga was 6 days' journey, on foot, eastward from his
country; that he had been there, his country having been engaged
in war with the people of that district; that there were
plenty of rivers, great and small, in the country of Donga; that
they were not the same as the river in his country, but ran in an
opposite, or rather in a southerly and westerly direction. He was
very clo~ely questioned about his knowledge of this place, and he
always adhered to the statement that he k11Pw it perfectly. He
also stated that he had heard of a country called Ferttee, to the
eastward of his country and of Donga. He gave the name of
every place or town at which he halted in his journey to the coast.
Gold and silver were abundant in Ferttee.</p>
<p>In his country, he says, there is a great river called Ayah,
broader than the Thames. It comes from the E., and runs to
the W. or the set.ting sun. Its course from his country passed
first through a place called Komse, second Mongell, third Pam be,
and fourth Mondt>ll. In his way westward he passed several rivers,
but all smaller, except one about midway ; and they all ran in
the direction of and to join the Great River. This river is joined
on both sides by small streams. During the dry season the Great
River is about 3 feet deep. There are no canoes on the Great
Rirnr: the people either swim across it or pass it on rafts. During
the rainy season there is plenty of hail; the children pick it up and
put it in their mouths as amusement, as it makes them feel cold:
it lies three or four hours on the ground before melting. Plenty of</p>
<lb/>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="line"/>
<lb/><note rend="small">
<note xml:id="note_12" rend="indent">*  Where?&#8212;<hi rend="smallcaps">Ed</hi>.</note>
<note xml:id="note_13" rend="indent">&#134;  The name here intended is M'Sagara, in about 8°S. and 35°E.&#8212;<hi rend="smallcaps">Ed</hi>.</note>
</note>


	<pb facs="liv_020003_0005" n="0005"/>
<fw><seg rend="center"><hi rend="italic"><bibl>African Geography.</bibl></hi></seg> <seg rend="right">375</seg></fw>
<p rend="no-indent">hills, some of them so high as to be always white with snow or hail.
Rain sometimes incessant throughout the year; sometimes dry.
Old people make rain fall-make fires and offerings to bring it.
Many shooting-stars or comets: these run like serpents, and ex-plode.
This takes place before the kings die. Thunder and
lightning very ht>avy, and very frequent. There are plenty of
elephants and monkeys; the monkPys do no hard work. There
are plenty of cows and horses, but these are never employed in
work. There are plenty of sheep, goats, and tiger-cats. There
is also plenty of fish in the rivers: both men and women catch
them in nets; these nets are made of a kind of grass or hemp.
There are plenty of crocodiles and alligators; the people eat
them, and also the guana: sometimes the crocodile kills people
in the riwr. There are plenty of large trees and plenty of brush.
The houses are made round; they are built of mud, thatched all
over, and have small fire-places. They have plenty of fowls.
Each kind of stock live separately. They have plenty of Guinea
corn and Indian corn ; plenty of yams and sweet potatoes of a description
resembling beet-root.</p>
<p>They have as many wives as they like: the king has ten, or
more. ThPy have many slaves, which are either bought or takPn
in war. There are also plenty of yellow and brown people&#8212;God
made them as well as the blacks: the brown or red coloured
people come with camels to buy slaves, &amp;c.; these red people
bring the camels in order to carry themselves and their goods.
His country made war with different nations&#8212;one called Koome,
another Korre, a third Komante, and a fourth Juke: the latter are
marked like the New Zealanders. All these nations are black,
and speak different languages. In his country they make images
of wood and worship them : they also pray to stones. The common
people build their images of clay. Tht>y also build a large
image with stone; this image only the king and courtiers worship:
they make him like a man, with a hole in one side in ordPr- to give
him victuals to eat, consisting of flesh, fowls, &amp;c.</p>
<p>Thomas Wogga is of a deep black colour, but without any of
the real negro countenance, such as the flat nose, thick lips, &amp;c.
He is now considerably advanced in years, but when young must
have been a good-looking man. His country marks are numerous
and full. He describes the general features of his own county, and
of those through which he travelled, with considerable clearness;
but, like every other African black, he can give no explanation
about names of places which are known to us from other quarters,
or of geographical bearings and distances, with any precision, except
as from E. to W_., or from the rising to the setting sun, or by
the sun being to the N. or the S. of the road.</p>


	<pb facs="liv_020003_0006" n="0006"/>
<fw><seg rend="left">376</seg>	<seg rend="center"><hi rend="italic"><bibl>African Geography</bibl>.</hi></seg></fw>
<p>The following is a more particular description of his route:&#8212;
<list rend="small">
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item><seg rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Days.</hi><space extent="6" unit="words"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Kimcoul to Uppe <seg rend="right">.<space extent="1" unit="words"/>.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>1<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Uppe to Auzilliga <seg rend="right">.<space extent="1" unit="words"/>.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>1<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Auzilliga to Ocoom <seg rend="right">.<space extent="1" unit="words"/>.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>7 <space extent="1" unit="chars"/> (long journeys.)<space extent="4" unit="chars"/><space extent="1" unit="words"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Ocoom to Mousookko <seg rend="right">.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>4<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Mousookko to Ungwa <seg rend="right">.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>6<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Ungwa to Uvangah <seg rend="right">.<space extent="1" unit="words"/>.<space extent="2" unit="chars"/>30 <space extent="1" unit="chars"/>(constant travel.)<space extent="3" unit="chars"/><space extent="1" unit="words"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Uvangah to Umblisse <seg rend="right">.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>9<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item>Umblisse to New Calabar <seg rend="right">.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>10<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item><seg rend="right">&#8212;<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
<lb/><space extent="4" unit="words"/><item><space extent="5" unit="words"/>Total <seg rend="right">.<space extent="3" unit="chars"/>68<space extent="6" unit="words"/><space extent="2" unit="chars"/></seg></item>
</list></p>

<p>Uppe is 1 day from the great river Ayah. At Auzilliga there
is a considerable river, but smaller than the Ayah: it runs westward
to join the latter. At Ocoom there is a river, called Moniah,
not so large as the Ayah. Ocoom is N. of the large river, and
not far from it. Ocoom Rirer not far from Great Hiver. Plenty
of yams and tobacco at Ocoom. There is no river at Monsookko,
but plenty of water from springs. The women here have very
large heads. There are large hills here, but not so large as those
in his country. Plenty of brush. U ngwa is a large town, with a
river 20 yards broad, but deep. There is no river at U vangah: it
is a large town, with plenty of bush in it and around it ; there are
many hills in its vicinity, some large and some small. Between
U ngwa and Uvangah one river, not fordable; swam across it. No
river from Uvangah to Umblisse; but the country is hilly, with
plenty of water from springs and rivulets. From U mblisse to
New Calabar the country is flat. In these journeys the people
of the caravan carried each yams for their food.</p>
	</div>
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="quarter-line small center"/>
<lb/><milestone unit="section" rend="quarter-line small center"/>

			</div>
		</body>	

    </text>
</TEI>
