<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Livingstone Online: Annotated African Ethnic Group List</title>
				<author>Adrian S. Wisnicki</author>
				<author>Megan Ward</author>
				<author>Justin D. Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2019</date>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">(c)
						Livingstone Online. <ref
							target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
							Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License</ref>.</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>A Livingstone Online project.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>

				<!-- Current higest number = ethnic0100 -->

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0018">
					<form>
						<orth>Bagenya</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also Wagenya. One of three tribes, all with the same name but ethnically
						distinct, residing in the Congo along the Lualaba River (Droogers 1980:31).
						Through their access to canoes, the Wagenya near Nyangwe both controlled the
						river traffic in the vicinity of the village and were the principal
						suppliers of fish to many of the local markets in the region.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0001">
					<form>
						<orth>Baguha</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group whose descendants are now known as the Holoholo and
						who, in Livingstone's time, lived on the western shore of Lake Tanganyika in
						east Africa.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0016">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKwena</orth>
					</form>
					<def>A SeTswana speaking group in southern Africa. Livingstone became a
						missionary to the BaKwena (under the leadership of Sechele) in 1846.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0002">
					<form>
						<orth>Bemba</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also Awemba. African ethnic group based in the north-eastern part of
						present-day Zambia with historical links to the Luba and Lunda populations
						of the Kantanga region of the Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0003">
					<form>
						<orth>Bena</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in what is the south-central part of
						Tanzania.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0004">
					<form>
						<orth>Bira</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in the Ituri rainforest in the north-eastern
						part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0005">
					<form>
						<orth>Bungu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania and settled to the
						south-east of Lake Rukwa.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0025">
					<form>
						<orth>Basarwa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also San or (often pejoratively) Bushmen. Collective term for southern
						Africa's indigenous hunter-gatherer populations.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0006">
					<form>
						<orth>Garaganza</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group from present-day Tanzania often included in the larger
						Nyamwezi group.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0007">
					<form>
						<orth>Gogo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in the central part of present-day
						Tanzania.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0008">
					<form>
						<orth>Makololo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Sotho people of southern Africa. Having been displaced by political
						upheaval in the early nineteenth century (known as the Mfecane), migrated
						north under the leadership of Sebitwane and came to settle in the Zambezi
						River valley in present-day Zambia around 1840. Makololo porters, sent by
						chief Sekeletu, journeyed with Livingstone on his famous African
						transcontinental journey.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0009">
					<form>
						<orth>Lega</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in the rainforests of the eastern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0017">
					<form>
						<orth>Luba</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group from the central part of present-day Democratic
						Republic of the Congo, whose kingdom constituted one of the major central
						African polities of the eighteenth- and nineteenth-centuries.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0010">
					<form>
						<orth>Manyema</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also Manyuema. Collective group that, in Livingstone's use, encompasses the
						many ethnic groups residing in Manyema, eastern Congo.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0011">
					<form>
						<orth>Masaai</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Well known African ethnic group based in the southern part of present-day
						Kenya and northern part of present-day Tanzania.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0012">
					<form>
						<orth>Ngoni</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group descended from the Nguni of kwaZulu-Natal in
						present-day South Africa who migrated north due to the Mfecane of the early
						nineteenth century.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0013">
					<form>
						<orth>Nyamnyams</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group of uncertain identity. The term Nyamnyam regularly
						refers to the Azande of north-central Africa, but the context of
						Livingstone's use of the term in the 1870 Field Diary points to a different
						group.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0014">
					<form>
						<orth>Nyamwezi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>East African ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania whose members often
						worked as independent traders or served as porters for Arab and African
						caravans.</def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0015">
					<form>
						<orth>Sangu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania and settled to the east
						and south-east of Lake Rukwa.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- 
			
				Groups that follow need to be defined 
				& added to XML (1871 FD)
	

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0020">
					<form>
						<orth>Bakuss/Bakuzz/KunsBakuss/KussBakuss</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>


				<entry xml:id="ethnic0021">
					<form>
						<orth>BaziriWazire/Wazire</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0022">
					<form>
						<orth>Benya</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				<entry xml:id="ethnic0023">
					<form>
						<orth>Malobo</orth>
					</form>
					<def></def>
				</entry>

				-->


				<!-- Missionary Travels Glossary List -->

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0026">
					<form>
						<orth>AmaMpondo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Amapanda by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day South Africa's Eastern Cape (Appiah and Gates Jr.
						2010:195).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0092">
					<form>
						<orth>AmaNdebele</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Matibele and Makonkobi by Livingstone. African ethnic group of
						present-day Zimbabwe, South Africa, and Botswana. The group was founded by
						Mzilikazi, who established the AmaNdebele state, Matabeleland, around 1840
						(Young 2010b:222-23).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0027">
					<form>
						<orth>AmaXhosa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Amakosa by Livingstone. African ethnic group (and part of the Nguni
						linguistic group) based primarily in present-day South Africa's Eastern Cape
						(Heath 2010e:555).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0100">
					<form>
						<orth>AmaZulu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Major African ethnic group (and part of the Nguni linguistic group) of
						present-day South Africa. In the early nineteenth century, the military
						leader Shaka developed a powerful military state (Zululand, in what is now
						KwaZulu-Natal), which conquered and incorporated many other peoples. AmaZulu
						expansion played a key role in the widespread warfare, migrations, and
						political transformation of southern Africa, known as the Mfecane. Today,
						the AmaZulu are South Africa's largest ethnic group (Heath
						2010f:579-80).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0028">
					<form>
						<orth>Baakhahela</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, an African ethnic group
						living to the north of the Basotho nation (present-day Lesotho).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0029">
					<form>
						<orth>Babimpe</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, an African ethnic group
						based in present-day southern Zambia near the confluence of the Kafue and
						Zambezi rivers. However, a group by this name is not recorded in more recent
						sources (Schapera 1960a:49n1).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0030">
					<form>
						<orth>Babindele</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. In his journals, Livingstone describes the group as
						"servants of the Portuguese" residing on the west African coast (Schapera
						1960a:31). </def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0031">
					<form>
						<orth>Babiriri</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Possibly the same group referred to in Livingstone's
						journals as the Babirikwe, who apparently lived near the confluence of the
						Lungwebungu and Zambezi rivers in present-day Zambia's Western Province
						(Schapera 1960a:31).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- up to here.JL -->
				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0032">
					<form>
						<orth>BaFokeng</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bahukeng by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						South Africa's North West province, who are part of the larger BaTswana
						group. Today, their ancestral lands in South Africa are known as the Royal
						Bafokeng Nation (Schweitzer 2015:36).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0033">
					<form>
						<orth>BaHurutshe</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in present-day South Africa's North West
						province, who are part of the larger BaTswana group (Bammann 2016:3).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0034">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKaa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group (and part of the larger BaTswana group) who split from
						the BaRolong kingdom in the early eighteenth century, to settle near the
						Shoshong hills in present-day eastern Botswana. They were eventually
						destroyed as an independent group by the BaNgwato (Otlogetswe and Chebanne
						2018:191-92).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0035">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKalanga</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Makalaka by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day north-eastern Botswana and western Zimbabwe, who speak a variant
						of Shona. The SeTswana term for this group, which Livingstone uses
						(Makalaka), is often considered pejorative (Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla
						2008:158).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0036">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKgalagadi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bakalahari by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						Botswana. The name refers to peoples living in the Kalahari Desert and who
						speak the SeKgalagadi language (a language related to but distinct from
						SeTswana). In the nineteenth century, the BaKgalagadi played a significant
						part in Kalahari trade but were increasingly subjugated by BaTswana groups
						(Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:165-66).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0037">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKgatla</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bakatla by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						Botswana and South Africa, who are part of the larger BaTswana group. There
						are multiple branches of BaKgatla, including the Mmanaana Kgatla and the
						Kgafela Bakgatla (Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:164-65, 222).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0038">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKgatla-Mosetlha</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bamosetla by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						South Africa's North West province, who are part of the larger BaTswana
						group. They are traditionally considered to be the most senior polity of the
						BaKgatla (Schapera 1961:97n1, Otlogetswe and Chebanne 2018:194).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0039">
					<form>
						<orth>Bakoni</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Collective term used by the southern BaTswana to refer to SeSotho-speaking
						groups living to the east and north of the Marico (or Madikwe) River
						(Schapera 1961:54n4).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0040">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKurutshe</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bakurutse and Bakurutze by Livingstone. African ethnic group based
						in the eastern part of present-day Botswana, who are considered to be a
						branch of the Bahurutshe. They are part of the larger BaTswana group
						(Schapera 1961:137n2; Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:179). </def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0041">
					<form>
						<orth>BaKwena</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also called Bakwains by Livingstone. African ethnic group primarily based
						in present-day Botswana. They are traditionally considered to be the most
						senior of the BaTswana polities in Botswana. MoKwena (Mokwain to
						Livingstone) refers to an individual of this group. Livingstone became a
						missionary to the BaKwena in 1846 (Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla
						2008:185-86).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0042">
					<form>
						<orth>Bamakakana</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Nineteenth-century records indicate this was one of
						various groups who settled in the Highveld of present-day central South
						Africa in the late eighteenth century. According to Livingstone, this group
						was part of the Basotho nation (present-day Lesotho) founded by Moshoeshoe I
						(Etherington 2001:22, 41n70).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0043">
					<form>
						<orth>BaNgwaketse</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also called Bangwaketze by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in
						present-day Botswana, and part of the larger BaTswana group. They are one of
						the larger polities of BaTswana and trace their origin to an early split
						with the BaKwena (Morton and Ramsay 2018:220).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0044">
					<form>
						<orth>BaNgwato</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also known as Bamangwato. African ethnic group based in present-day
						Botswana who are part of the larger BaTswana group. The BaNgwato originated
						as an offshoot of the BaKwena that became independent in the late eighteenth
						century (Morton and Ramsay 2018:221).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0045">
					<form>
						<orth>Banoga</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a previous BaTswana group of
						which he found evidence but had ceased to exist by the time of his arrival
						in southern Africa.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0046">
					<form>
						<orth>BaPedi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Baperi by Livingstone. African ethnic group primarily based in
						present-day South Africa's Limpopo province, but also in southern Zimbabwe
						and eastern Botswana (Appiah and Gates Jr. 2010:295; Morton, Ramsay, and
						Mgadla 2008:265).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0047">
					<form>
						<orth>BaPhaleng</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bapalleng by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in the Kalahari
						region of present-day Botswana, who are part of the larger BaKgalagadi group
						(Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:165)</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0048">
					<form>
						<orth>BaPhuthi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Baputi by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						Lesotho, who were integrated into the Basotho nation in the 1820s under the
						rule of Moshoeshoe I (Eldredge 1993:43, Rosenberg and Weisfelder 2013:46).
					</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0049">
					<form>
						<orth>Bapiri</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Possibly a reference to the Bapedi, whom Livingstone
						also calls Baperi.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0050">
					<form>
						<orth>BaPo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based in present-day South Africa's North West
						province, who are part of the larger BaTswana group (Morton 2010:24).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0051">
					<form>
						<orth>BaRolong</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based primarily in present-day South Africa's North
						West province. They are one of the largest BaTswana polities with among the
						longest recorded histories (Schapera 1961:42n6, Legassick 2010:29, Eldredge
						2015:245).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0052">
					<form>
						<orth>Basotho</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Basuto, Basutu, and Basuta by Livingstone. One of the largest ethnic
						groups of southern Africa. The Basotho nation was founded by Moshoeshoe I in
						the early nineteenth century and became present-day Lesotho, gaining
						independence from British colonial rule in 1966 (Olson 1996:534, Appiah and
						Gates Jr. 2010:406). </def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0053">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTaung</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Batau by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day Lesotho, who are part of the larger Basotho group. Having been
						displaced from the region between the Vaal and Sand rivers by the
						AmaNdebele, the BaTaung settled in the territory of the Basotho nation in
						the 1830s (Rosenberg and Weisfelder 2013:74).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0054">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTawana</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Batauana by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day Botswana, who are part of the larger BaTswana group. The
						BaTawana originated as an offshoot of the BaNgwato in the late eighteenth
						century (Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:325).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0055">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTeti</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Batletli by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in the Boteti
						Floodplains of present-day Botswana, who are part of the larger Khoesan
						group. The BaTeti once spoke Deti, an eastern Khoe language, but this was
						gradually replaced by SeTswana (Cashdan 1987:125-26, Wilmsen
						2002:834).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0056">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTlhaping</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Batlapi by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						South Africa's Northern Cape and North West provinces, who are part of the
						larger BaTswana group. They are the southernmost of the BaTswana (Schapera
						1961:16n1).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0057">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTlharo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bamatlaru by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						South Africa's Northern Cape, who are part of the larger BaTswana group
						(Schapera 1961:97n2, Comaroff and Comaroff 1997:53).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0058">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTlokwa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Batlokua by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						Lesotho, Botswana, and South Africa who are part of the larger BaTswana
						group (Olson 1996:561).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0059">
					<form>
						<orth>Batlou</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Probably the Batloung, an African ethnic group based
						in present-day Lesotho (Eldredge 2015:226-27).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0060">
					<form>
						<orth>Batonga</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also called Batoka by Livingstone. Major African ethnic group of the
						Zambezi basin, based primarily in southern Zambia but also in Zimbabwe,
						Botswana, Malawi, and Mozambique. The Tonga-speaking peoples living in the
						vicinity of Victoria Falls are known as the Toka-Leya (Nave 2010c:484,
						Vickery 1986:14).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0061">
					<form>
						<orth>BaTswana</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bechuana by Livingstone. Major African ethnic group based in
						present-day Botswana, Namibia, and South Africa, consisting of numerous
						subgroups. BaTswana polities of present-day Botswana include the BaKwena,
						BaNgwaketse, BaKgatla, BaLete, BaNgwato, BaRolong, BaTawana, and BaTlkowa
						(Nave 2010d:498-99).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0062">
					<form>
						<orth>BaYeyi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bayeiye and Bakoba by Livingstone. Ethnic group based primarily in
						the Ngamiland region of present-day north-western Botswana. The BaYeyi had
						been based in the Chobe and Linyanti regions, but began to relocate to
						Ngamiland in the mid-eighteenth century to escape Lozi expansion (Larson
						1989:23-25). </def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0063">
					<form>
						<orth>Cassanges</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Name sometimes given to the Mbangala of northern Angola. It derived from
						the name Kasanje, an early Mbangala leader who founded the Kasanje Kingdom
						in the upper Kwango (or Cuango) River Valley in the seventeenth century
						(Schapera 1963,1:55n2; Birmingham 1981:79).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0064">
					<form>
						<orth>Chokwe</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Chiboque by Livingstone. Major African ethnic group of Angola,
						Democratic Republic of the Congo, and Zambia. In the nineteenth century,
						they had significant involvement in the wax, ivory, and rubber trades, and
						became one of the wealthiest trading groups of the Congo basin before the
						advent of Belgian colonialism (Heath 2010b:266-67).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0065">
					<form>
						<orth>Damara</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based primarily in present-day north-western Namibia,
						who are one of southern Africa's Khoesan peoples (Barnard 1992:11).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0066">
					<form>
						<orth>Gogo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bagogo by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in the central
						highlands of present-day Tanzania (Appiah and Gates Jr. 2010:524).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0067">
					<form>
						<orth>Haco</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also called Ako by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in Angola, who
						form part of the larger Mbundu group (James 2011:164).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0068">
					<form><orth>Ila</orth></form>
					<def>Called Bashukulompo by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in
						present-day southern Zambia's Kafue Valley (Rijpma 2015:104, Olson
						1996:238).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0069">
					<form>
						<orth>Jinga</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Name sometimes used for the Mbundu. It was derived from the name of the
						seventeenth-century Queen of the Ndongo Kingdom, Nzinga a Mbandi (Schapera
						1963,1:159n5).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0070">
					<form>
						<orth>Kanyika</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Livingstone is presumably referring to inhabitants of
						the Nyika Plateau, which is largely in present-day northern Malawi and
						partly in north-eastern Zambia.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0071">
					<form>
						<orth>Kasabi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Livingstone appears to use the term to refer to
						peoples settled around the upper Kasai River in Angola (Schapera 1963,1:101,
						105)</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0072">
					<form>
						<orth>Kisama</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also called Quisamas by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in Angola's
						present-day Quiçama region, who are part of the larger Mbundu group
						(Schapera 1963,1:170).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0074">
					<form>
						<orth>Landeens</orth></form>
					<def>Term used by the colonial Portuguese in south-eastern Africa to refer to
						groups of Ngoni who had arrived on the southern banks of the Zambezi River
						from the 1830s during the Mfecane (Dritsas 2010:9)</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0075">
					<form>
						<orth>Langa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Balaka and Bamapela by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in
						present-day northern South Africa, who are part of the larger AmaNdebele
						group (Schapera 1961:97n5, Morton 2010:31).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0076">
					<form>
						<orth>Libolo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Libollo by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in north-central
						Angola, who are part of the larger Mbundu group (James 2011:164, Olson
						1996:335).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0077">
					<form>
						<orth>Lozi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Barotse by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day Zambia. They established themselves in the Zambezi Floodplain in
						the seventeenth century where they developed an expansionist state. The Lozi
						were conquered by the Makololo in the 1830s, but re-established their
						independence through an uprising in 1864. The Lozi traditionally called
						themselves the Luyi or Luyana, which accounts for Livingstone's alternative
						names: Baloiana and little Baloi (Nave 2010b:87). </def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0078">
					<form>
						<orth>Lunda</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Balonda, Balunda, and Baloi by Livingstone. African ethnic group of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo, Zambia, and Angola. The Lunda
						established a kingdom in central Africa in the fifteenth century, which
						eventually developed into a powerful commonwealth of interlinking states.
						The Lunda became increasingly involved in long-distance commerce in the
						seventeenth century, and played an important role in the slave and ivory
						trades of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries (Heath 2010d:91-92, Macola
						2016b:1320-22).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0079">
					<form>
						<orth>Luvale</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Balobale by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						north-western Zambia and in eastern Angola. Luvale traditions connect the
						group closely with the Lunda people (Olson 1996:351).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0080">
					<form>
						<orth>Makatla</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, this group was part of the
						Basotho nation (present-day Lesotho) founded by Moshoeshoe I.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0081">
					<form>
						<orth>Makolokue</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, this group was part of the
						Basotho nation (present-day Lesotho) founded by Moshoeshoe I. It is also
						possible that Livingstone is referring to inhabitants of Makolokwe in
						present-day South Africa's North West province.</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0082">
					<form>
						<orth>Makololo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>African ethnic group based primarily in present-day Zambia's Western
						Province, who are part of the larger Basotho group. The Makololo's founder
						was initially a BaFokeng leader based in present-day South Africa's Free
						State. Displaced by the political upheaval in the early nineteenth century
						(known as the Mfecane), the group migrated north and came to settle in the
						Zambezi Valley in present-day Zambia around 1840. Makololo porters, sent by
						chief Sekeletu, journeyed with Livingstone on his famous African
						transcontinental journey (1852-56) (Kalusa 2009:60-61).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0083">
					<form>
						<orth>Mambari</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Name given to Ovimbundu traders from Angola who had established long
						distance caravan routes in central Africa (Birmingham 1981:86).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0084">
					<form>
						<orth>Mang'anja</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Maganja by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						southern Malawi, who are part of the larger Maravi group. The Mang'anja are
						often described as the earliest occupants of Malawi's Shire Highlands and
						Shire Valley (Morris 2016:59, Kalinga 2012:281).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0085">
					<form>
						<orth>Mang'ete</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Banyeti and Manyeti by Livingstone. Livingstone's usage suggests
						this is a specific ethnic group, but the word is actually a Lozi term
						meaning "foreigners" (Colson and Gluckman 1959:19; Schapera
						1963,1:14n3).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0086">
					<form>
						<orth>Maravi</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Cluster of related ethnic groups who traditionally consider themselves to
						be descendants of the Maravi States, a confederacy established by groups who
						migrated into central and southern Malawi and the Shire Valley in the late
						fifteenth century, and which declined in the 1700s. Maravi groups include
						the Chipeta, the Chewa, the Nyanja, and the Mang'anja (Darch 2019:246-47,
						Morris 2016:62).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0087">
					<form>
						<orth>Matlapatlapa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Reference uncertain. Nineteenth-century records indicate this was one of
						various groups who settled in the Highveld of present-day central South
						Africa in the late eighteenth century. According to Livingstone, this group
						was part of the Basotho nation (present-day Lesotho) founded by Moshoeshoe I
						(Etherington 2001:22, 41n70).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0088">
					<form>
						<orth>Mbangala</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bangala by Livingstone. African ethnic group of northern and eastern
						Angola. The Mbangala were involved in long-distance commerce to the Angolan
						coast from the seventeenth century, and became an important trading partner
						of the central Lunda (or Ruund) (Oppen 1993:56).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0089">
					<form>
						<orth>Mbundu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Ambonda and Ambunda by Livingstone. Major African ethnic group based
						primarily in Angola's north-western and north-central regions. Today, the
						Mbundu are Angola's second largest ethnic group following the Ovimbundu
						(Young 2010a:163-64).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0090">
					<form>
						<orth>Mfengu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Fingoe by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day South Africa's Eastern Cape. They were formed over time from a
						variety of immigrant groups who arrived in AmaXhosa territory. In the
						nineteenth century, the term Fingo was also used with less specificity to
						refer to workers from the AmaXhosa homelands seeking employment in the Cape
						Colony (Keegan 1996:146, Appiah and Gates Jr. 2010:168). </def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0091">
					<form>
						<orth>Najwa</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Banajoa by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						Botswana. They were originally Namyba speakers who relocated from
						present-day Zimbabwe as a result of conflict with the AmaNdebele, and
						settled near the Boteti River (Schapera 1960a:14n3; Frawley
						2003,3:126).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0093">
					<form>
						<orth>Ovimbundu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Kimbonda by Livingstone. Major African ethnic group primarily based
						in Angola's central regions. By the late eighteenth century, Ovimbundu
						states had established an extensive trading network from the Angolan coast
						into the interior. Today, the Ovimbundu are Angola's largest ethnic group
						(Birmingham 1981:85-87, Young 2010c:281).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0094">
					<form>
						<orth>Sangu</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also known historically as the Rori. Called Baroro by Livingstone. African
						ethnic group based in present-day Tanzania, and settled primarily in the
						Mbeya and Iringa regions (Olson 1996:509).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0095">
					<form>
						<orth>Shinji</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bashinje and Chinge by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in
						northern and eastern Angola, who are part of the larger Lunda group
						(Schapera 1963,1:123n1; Oppen 1993:212).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0096">
					<form>
						<orth>Shona</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Also known as Mashona. Major African ethnic group of present-day Zimbabwe,
						southern Zambia, and west-central Mozambique. The Shona consist of a number
						of linguistic subgroups who speak variants of the same language, including
						the Korekore, Zezuru, Karanga, Kalanga, Manyika, and Nadau (Young
						2010d:379).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0097">
					<form>
						<orth>Songo</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Basongo by Livingstone. African ethnic group based in present-day
						north-central Angola, who are part of the larger Mbundu group (Olson
						1996:532, James 2011:164).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0098">
					<form>
						<orth>Subiya</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Bashubia by Livingstone. African ethnic group based primarily in
						present-day Botswana, as well as south-western Zambia and Namibia's Caprivi
						Strip. They were subject to the Makololo during the period of Makololo
						ascendancy from the 1830s to 1864 (Olson 1996:536, Kanguma
						2011:36-38).</def>
				</entry>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<entry xml:id="ethnic0099">
					<form>
						<orth>Watuta</orth>
					</form>
					<def>Called Batutu by Livingstone. Itinerant Ngoni in and around lakes
						Tanganyika and Victoria. In the early 1820s, the Ngoni began to migrate from
						the south under the leadership of Zwangendaba, eventually crossing the
						Zambezi River in 1835. Following his death around 1845, the group splintered
						into separate states, with one branch becoming known as the Watuta (Rockel
						2012:224, Spear 2012:253-54).</def>
				</entry>


			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
