<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Livingstone Online: Annotated Geographical Name List</title>
				<author>Adrian S. Wisnicki</author>
				<author>Megan Ward</author>
				<author>Justin D. Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2019</date>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">(c)
						Livingstone Online. <ref
							target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
							Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License</ref>.</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>A Livingstone Online project.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<listPlace>

				<!-- Current higest number = geog0234 -->

				<place xml:id="geog0001" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Anjouan, Comoros</placeName>
					<!-- Johanna -->
					<note type="editorial">Also Johanna Island. Ten men from this island, hired with
						the assistance of the island's British Consul, accompanied Livingstone on
						his last journey.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0058" type="geogName_valley">
					<placeName type="main">Barotse Valley</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone’s name for the Zambezi Floodplain, in the
						Western Province of present-day Zambia.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0061" type="geogName_cape">
					<placeName type="main">Cape Delgago</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Promontory. Northernmost point of Mozambique.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0002" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Castalian springs</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Natural springs near Delphi in ancient Greece.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0003" type="geogName_drainage">
					<placeName type="main">Central line of drainage of the great Nile
						valley</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone incorrectly believed that the Nile originated
						in Lake Bangweulu in present-day Zambia and was fed by a series of sources
						in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0004" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Congo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major river in Africa. On his last expedition,
						Livingstone investigated diverse sections of the river in the mistaken hopes
						that they had some connection to the Nile River system.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0005" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Crophi</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">With Mophi, one of two hills with conical tops that
						Herodotus, the ancient Greek historian, placed in central Africa and cited
						as lying between the sources of the Nile to the north and of the Zambezi to
						the south.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0006" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Euphrates River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in Mesopotamia. One of four rivers said to flow
						from the Garden of Eden.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0007" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Fountain of the Lufira River</placeName>
					<!-- Bartle Frere's fountain -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Bartle Frere's Fountain by Livingstone. The
						Lufira River is tributary of the Lualaba River in present-day Democratic
						Republic of the Congo. Livingstone believed that the Lufira united with the
						Lualaba River to form the fictitious Lake Kamolondo. Livingstone placed the
						source of the Lufira River, which he incorrectly linked to the Nile, three
						or four days' travel time south of the Katanga region (in the southern part
						of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo). Livingstone named the
						source after British colonial administrator H. Bartle E. Frere
						(1815-1884).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0008" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Fountain of the Lufira River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">The Lufira River is tributary of the Lualaba River in
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. Livingstone believed that the
						Lufira River united with the Lualaba River to form the fictitious Lake
						Kamolondo. Livingstone placed the source of the Lufira Rivers, which he
						incorrectly linked to the Nile, three or four days' travel time south of the
						Katanga region (in the southern part of present-day Democratic Republic of
						the Congo).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0063" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Gaboon</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River and estuary. Located in the west of present-day
						Gabon.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0009" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Ganges River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">One of four rivers said to flow from the Garden of
						Eden.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0010" type="geogName_garden">
					<placeName type="main">Garden of Eden</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Biblical garden of God described in the Book of
						Genesis.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0011" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Gihon River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River said to flow out of the Garden of Eden in the
						Bible.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0012" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Hercynia</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Classical name for the stream issuing from the springs at
						Lebadea in ancient Greece.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0013" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Hiddekel River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Hebrew name for the Tigris River of Mesopotamia. One of
						four rivers said to flow from the Garden of Eden.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0014" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Jordan River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in west Asia flowing to the Dead Sea.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0015" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kafue River</placeName>
					<!-- Luenge, Lunga -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Luenge and Lunga by Livingstone. Significant
						river in Zambia and one of the main tributaries of the Zambezi River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0016" type="geogName_desert">
					<placeName type="main">Kalahari Desert</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Large sandy savanna that encompasses parts of present-day
						Botswana, Namibia, and South Africa.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0017" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Kiziwa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Possibly present-day Lake Albert, Uganda.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0065" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kunda River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">A tributary of the Lualaba River in eastern Congo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0018" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Albert (Uganda)</placeName>
					<!-- Albert Nyanza, Baker's Water/Lake, Uerere -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Albert Nyanza, Baker's Water or Lake, and
						Uerere by Livingstone. In 1864, explorer and hunter Samuel W. Baker
						(1821-1893) became the first European to visit the lake, which he named
						after Prince Albert, husband of Queen Victoria.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0019" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Albert (Uganda)</placeName>
					<!-- Lower Tanganyika -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lower Tanganyika by Livingstone. In 1864,
						explorer and hunter Samuel W. Baker (1821-1893) became the first European to
						visit the lake, which he named after Prince Albert, husband of Queen
						Victoria. At the time, Livingstone incorrectly believed that this lake was
						part of Lake Tanganyika and that both were part of the Nile River system
						(only Lake Albert is).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0020" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Bangweulu (Zambia)</placeName>
					<!-- Bangweolo -->
					<note type="editorial">Also Bangweolo. Livingstone incorrectly believed that
						this lake was part of the Nile River system. The lake is actually part of
						the Congo River system.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0021" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Chibungo</placeName>
					<!-- Lake Lincoln -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lake Lincoln by Livingstone. Fictitious lake
						created via the union of the Lufira and Lomami/Lomani Rivers in what would
						have been present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. Livingstone named
						the lake after the American president Abraham Lincoln (1809-1865).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0022" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Kamolondo</placeName>
					<!-- Riverein Lake -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Riverein Lake by Livingstone. Livingstone
						believed that the Lufira and Lualaba Rivers united to form this fictitious
						lake in what would have been present-day Democratic Republic of the
						Congo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0023" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Malawi (Malawi, Mozambique, and
						Tanzania)</placeName>
					<!-- Nyassa -->
					<note type="editorial">Also Nyassa. Also known as Lake Nyasa (in Tanzania) and
						Lago Niassa (in Mozambique). Although not the first European to do so,
						Livingstone visited this lake in 1859 and gave it the name Lake
						Nyassa.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0024" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Mweru (Zambia and Democratic Republic of the
						Congo)</placeName>
					<!-- Lake Moero -->
					<note type="editorial">Also Lake Moero. Livingstone incorrectly believed that
						this lake was part of the Nile River system. The lake is actually part of
						the Congo River system.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0025" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Tanganyika (Tanzania, Democratic Republic of the
						Congo, Burundi, and Zambia)</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">When he wrote the 1870 Field Diary, Livingstone
						incorrectly believed that this lake was part of the Nile River system. The
						lake is actually part of the Congo River system.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0026" type="geogName_lake">
					<!-- Lower and Upper Tanganyika -->
					<placeName type="main">Lake Victoria (Tanzania, Uganda, and Kenya) and Lake
						Albert (Uganda), respectively.</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lower and Upper Tanganyika, respectively, by
						Livingstone. Livingstone incorrectly believed that these two distinct and
						unrelated lakes were in fact part of one larger lake.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0027" type="geogName_lake">
					<!-- Upper Tanganyika, Victoria Nyanza, Nyanza -->
					<placeName type="main">Lake Victoria (Tanzania, Uganda, and Kenya)</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Upper Tanganyika, Victoria Nyanza, and Nyanza
						by Livingstone. In 1858, explorer John H. Speke (1827-1864) became the first
						European to visit the lake, which he named after Queen Victoria, and
						asserted correctly but without definitive evidence to be the source of the
						Nile. Livingstone refused to recognize Speke's assertion.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0028" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lindi River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Tributary of the Lualaba River in present-day Democratic
						Republic of the Congo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0029" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lomami/Lomani River</placeName>
					<!-- Lomame, Loeki, Lofubu, Lualaba West -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lomame, Loeki, Lofubu, and Lualaba West by
						Livingstone. Major river in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.
						Livingstone believed that the Lomami/Lomani formed part of the Nile River
						system, but in fact the river joins the Lualaba River to become the Congo
						River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0030" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lomami/Lomani River</placeName>
					<!-- Young's Lualaba, Young's River -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Young's Lualaba and Young's River by
						Livingstone. Major river in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.
						Livingstone believed that the Lomami/Lomani formed part of the Nile River
						system, but in fact the river joins the Lualaba River to become the Congo
						River. Livingstone named the river after James Young (1811-1883), a Scottish
						industrialist who later become one of Livingstone's trustees.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0031" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lomami/Lomani River</placeName>
					<!-- Young's Lake River -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Young's Lake River by Livingstone. Major
						river in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. Livingstone believed
						that the Lomami/Lomani formed part of the Nile River system, but in fact the
						river joins the Lualaba River to become the Congo River. Livingstone named
						the river after James Young (1811-1883), a Scottish industrialist who later
						become one of Livingstone's trustees. Livingstone called it the "lake river"
						because he believed that it flowed through the fictitious Lake Chibungo
						(renamed Lake Lincoln by Livingstone).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0032" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lualaba and Lomami/Lomani Rivers</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major rivers in present-day Democratic Republic of the
						Congo. Livingstone believed that these rivers formed part of the Nile River
						system, but in fact they join to become the Congo River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0033" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lualaba River</placeName>
					<!-- Central Lualaba, Lualaba East, Lacustrine River  -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Central Lualaba, Lualaba East, and Lacustrine
						River by Livingstone. Major river in present-day Democratic Republic of the
						Congo. Livingstone believed that the Lualaba formed part of the Nile River
						system, but in fact the river joins the Lomami/Lomani River to become the
						Congo River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0034" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lualaba River</placeName>
					<!-- Webb's Lualaba -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Webb's Lualaba by Livingstone. Major river in
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. Livingstone believed that the
						Lualaba formed part of the Nile River system, but in fact the river joins
						the Lomami/Lomani River to become the Congo River. Livingstone named the
						river after hunter William F. Webb (1829-1899).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0035" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lualaba River</placeName>
					<!-- Lake River Webb -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lake River Webb by Livingstone. Major river
						in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. Livingstone believed that
						the Lualaba formed part of the Nile River system, but in fact the river
						joins the Lomami/Lomani River to become the Congo River. Livingstone named
						the river after hunter William F. Webb (1829-1899). Livingstone called it a
						"lake river" because he believed that it united with the Lufira River to
						form the fictitious Lake Kamolondo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0036" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lualaba, Lomami/Lomani, and Lufira Rivers</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Rivers in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.
						Livingstone believed that these rivers formed part of the Nile River system,
						but in fact the Lufira is a tributary of the Lualaba and, in the turn, the
						Lualaba and the Lomami/Lomani unite to become the Congo River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0037" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luapula River</placeName>
					<!-- New Zambesi -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called New Zambesi by Livingstone. River that links
						Lakes Mweru and Bangweolo and that forms part of the border between
						present-day Zambia and the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Portuguese
						explorers and travelers, "armchair geographer" William D. Cooley
						(1795[?]-1883), and, initially, Livingstone all incorrectly believed that
						this river was a tributary of the Zambezi River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0038" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lufira River</placeName>
					<!-- Bartle Frere's Lualaba -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Bartle Frere's Lualaba by Livingstone.
						Tributary of the Lualaba River in present-day Democratic Republic of the
						Congo. Livingstone believed that the Lufira united with the Lualaba River to
						form the fictitious Lake Kamolondo. Livingstone named the source of the
						river after British colonial administrator H. Bartle E. Frere
						(1815-1884).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0039" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lufira River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Tributary of the Lualaba River in present-day Democratic
						Republic of the Congo. Livingstone believed that the Lufira united with the
						Lualaba River to form the fictitious Lake Kamolondo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0040" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lukuga River</placeName>
					<!-- Luamo -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Luamo by Livingstone. Principal outlet of
						Lake Tanganyika; runs west from the lake through the eastern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of Congo and eventually joins the Lualaba
						River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0041" type="geogName_forest">
					<placeName type="main">Metamba</placeName>
					<!-- Metambe -->
					<note type="editorial">Also Metambe. Rainforest in the north-eastern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo that is home to the Lega people
						and that encompasses the valleys of the middle and upper Elila and the upper
						Ulindi Rivers.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0042" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Mophi</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">With Crophi, one of two hills with conical tops that
						Herodotus, the ancient Greek historian, placed in central Africa and cited
						as lying between the sources of the Nile to the north and of the Zambezi to
						the south.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0043" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Mount Kenya</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Second highest mountain in Africa (after Kilimanjaro),
						located in present-day Kenya.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0044" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Mount Kilimanjaro</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Highest mountain in Africa, located in present-day
						Tanzania.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0045" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Nile River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major river in Africa and longest river in the world. The
						search for the source(s) of the Nile motivated the African expeditions of a
						number of important Victorian explorers, among them Richard Burton
						(1821-1890), John H. Speke (1827-1864), Samuel W. Baker (1821-1893), Henry
						M. Stanley (1841-1904), and, of course, Livingstone himself.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0046" type="geogName_valley">
					<placeName type="main">Nile valley</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region surrounding the northern part of the Nile
						River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0047" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Pison</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">One of four rivers said to flow from the Garden of
						Eden.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0048" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Ptolemy's Mountains of the Moon</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Legendary African mountain range cited by Ptolemy
						(c.100-c.170), the ancient geographer, as being located at the source of the
						Nile River.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0049" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Riverine Lakes</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Set of central African lakes that, on Livingstone's
						understanding, included the real Lakes Bangweulu, Tanganyika, Victoria, and
						Albert plus the fictitious Lakes Chibungo (a.k.a. Lake Lincoln) and
						Kamolondo.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0064" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Ruvuma River</placeName>
					<!--Rovuma River-->
					<note type="editorial">Also Rovuma River. Significant river in east Africa that
						forms part of the border between present-day Tanzania and Mozambique.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0050" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Shire River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major river in present-day Malawi that flows out of Lake
						Malawi and is a tributary of the Zambezi River. Livingstone visited the
						river in 1859 during his second expedition to Africa (1858-64).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0051" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Source of the Kafue River</placeName>
					<!-- Oswell Fountain -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Oswell Fountain by Livingstone. Livingstone
						named the source, which he located south of the Katanga region (in the
						southern part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo) in what is
						now Zambia, after William C. Oswell (1818-1893), an explorer and hunter,
						whom Livingstone met and travelled with in South Africa and who remained
						Livingstone's close friend.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0052" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Source of the Zambezi River</placeName>
					<!-- Palmerston Fountain -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Palmerston Fountain by Livingstone.
						Livingstone named the source, which he located south of the Katanga region
						(in the southern part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo) in
						what is now Zambia, after Lord Palmerston (1784-1865), a former British
						Minister, whose anti-slavery policies Livingstone admired.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0053" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Source(s) of the Nile River</placeName>
					<!-- Fountains of the Nile, Fountains of the River of Egypt, Caput Nili, Katanga Head Waters -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Fountains of the Nile, Fountains of the River
						of Egypt, Caput Nili, and Katanga Head Waters by Livingstone. The search for
						the source(s) of the Nile motivated the African expeditions of a number of
						important Victorian explorers. Although John H. Speke (1827-1864) visited
						and correctly claimed Lake Victoria as the principal source in 1858, many
						contemporaries doubted his claim, so the search continued. Livingstone, for
						instance, believed that the sources lay much farther to the south in either
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo or Zambia.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0054" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Sources of the Lomami/Lomani and Lufira
						Rivers</placeName>
					<!-- Young's and Bartle Frere's Fountains -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Young's and Bartle Frere's Fountains by
						Livingstone. Livingstone placed the sources of the Lomami/Lomani and Lufira
						Rivers, both of which he incorrectly linked to the Nile, three or four days'
						travel time south of Katanga (a region in the southern part of present-day
						Democratic Republic of the Congo). He named the sources after, respectively,
						James Young (1811-1883), a Scottish industrialist who later became one of
						Livingstone's trustees, and British colonial administrator H. Bartle E.
						Frere (1815-1884).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0055" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Sources of the Zambezi and Kafue Rivers</placeName>
					<!-- Fountains of the Liambai and Upper Zambesi/Lunga -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Fountains of the Liambai and Upper Zambesi or
						Lunga by Livingstone. Livingstone placed the sources of the Zambezi (Liambai
						or Upper Zambesi) and Kafue (Lunga) Rivers south of Katanga (a region in the
						southern part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo) in what in
						now Zambia. </note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0056" type="geogName_source">
					<placeName type="main">Sources of the Zambezi and Kafue Rivers</placeName>
					<!-- Palmerston's and Oswell's Fountains -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Palmerston's and Oswell's Fountains by
						Livingstone. Livingstone named the sources of the Zambezi and Kafue Rivers,
						which he placed south of the Katanga region (in the southern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo) in what is now Zambia,
						respectively, after Lord Palmerston (1784-1865), erstwhile British Minister,
						whose anti-slavery policies Livingstone admired, and after William C. Oswell
						(1818-1893), an explorer and hunter, whom Livingstone met and travelled with
						in South Africa and who remained Livingstone's close friend.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0062" type="geogName_waterfall">
					<placeName type="main">Victoria Falls</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major waterfall on the Zambezi River, located on the
						border of present-day Zambia and Zimbabwe. In 1855, David Livingstone became
						the first European to visit to the waterfall, which he named after Queen
						Victoria.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0057" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">White Nile</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">The White Nile, which flows north from Lake Victoria, and
						the Blue Nile, which flows west from Ethiopia, are the two main tributaries
						of the Nile River and join together to form the main Nile River at
						present-day Khartoum, Sudan.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0059" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Zambezi River</placeName>
					<!-- Liambai, Upper Zambesi -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Liambai or Upper Zambesi by Livingstone.
						Major river in south central Africa that rises in present-day Zambia, then
						flows east across the continent to the Indian Ocean.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="geog0060" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Zanzibar, Tanzania</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island off the east coast of Africa. In the nineteenth
						century, the center of east Africa's Arab-Indian-African trading network, a
						major international depot, and the site of a notorious slave market.</note>
				</place>


				<!-- Missionary Travels Glossary List -->

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0066" type="geogName_bay">
					<placeName type="main">Algoa Bay</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">A bay of the Indian Ocean in South Africa's Eastern
						Cape.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0067" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Azores</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Archipelago of nine islands in the Atlantic Ocean, around
						900 miles off the west coast of Portugal.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0068" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Baramuana</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a hill in
						the vicinity of Mount Morrumbala in central Mozambique.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0069" type="geogName_valley">
					<placeName type="main">Barotse Floodplain</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Zambezi Floodplain and the Bulozi
						Plain. Called Barotse Valley by Livingstone. Extensive wetlands region
						around the Zambezi River in the Western Province of present-day
						Zambia.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0070" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Bengo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Senza by Livingstone. River in northern
						Angola that enters the sea about ten miles above Luanda.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0071" type="geogName_plateau">
					<placeName type="main">Bié Plateau</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Bihe by Livingstone. Large plateau in central
						Angola that covers about one tenth of the country.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0072" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Boatlaname</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Spring in present-day south-eastern Botswana, about
						seventy miles north of Gaborone (Schapera 1961:169n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0073" type="geogName_cataracts">
					<placeName type="main">Bombue Rapids</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, rapids on
						the Zambezi River between Ngonye Falls in present-day Zambia's Western
						Province and Katima Mulilo in present-day Namibia's Caprivi Strip.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0074" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Boteti River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Zouga by Livingstone. River in present-day
						northern Botswana that issues from the Thamalakane River just south of Maun
						and that forms part of the drainage system of the Okavango Delta. In periods
						of high floods, the Boteti River flows south-east to Lake Xau before
						continuing to the Makgadikgadi Pans (Hughes and Hughes 1992:607,
						620).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0075" type="geogName_rapids">
					<placeName type="main">Cahora Bassa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Kebrabasa by Livingstone. Rapids on the Zambezi
						River in present-day western Mozambique. Livingstone bypassed these rapids
						during his transcontinental expedition (1852-56), but during his later
						Zambezi Expedition (1858-64) he realised that they were impassible and
						prevented the navigation of the river. The rapids were dammed in the 1970s
						to form Lake Cahora Bassa which is used to generate hydroelectricity (Ross
						2002:105).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0076" type="geogName_stream">
					<placeName type="main">Caloi</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a
						tributary of the Bengo River.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0077" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Camaue River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Kamaue by Livingstone. Reference uncertain.
						According to Livingstone, a stream in north-eastern Angola that flows into
						the Tshikapa River, which is in turn a tributary of the Kasai River.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0078" type="geogName_cape">
					<placeName type="main">Cape of Good Hope</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Promontory on the southern tip of the Cape Peninsula in
						present-day South Africa's Western Cape.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0079" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Ceylon</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">British Colony in South Asia from 1796 until its
						independence in 1948. It became known as Sri Lanka in 1972.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0080" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Chifumage River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Chifumadze by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						that joins the Zambezi River about thirty miles north of present-day Lumbala
						(Schapera 1963,1:78n4).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0081" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Chisekesi</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Kisekise by Livingstone. Hill near the present-day
						settlement of Chisekesi in Zambia's Southern Province (Schapera
						1963,2:350n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0082" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Chiumbe River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Chihombo by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						that joins the Luemba River about twenty miles north of the Angolan border
						in the south-western part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo
						(Schapera 1963,1:108n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0083" type="geogName_rivulet">
					<placeName type="main">Chiume River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Chihune by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						which flows into the Chiumbe River near present-day Dala (Schapera
						1963,1:106n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0084" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Chobe River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River that marks the border between present-day Botswana
						and Namibia's Caprivi Strip, and that flows into the Zambezi River at
						Kazungala (at the quadripoint boundary between Botswana, Namibia, Zambia,
						and Zimbabwe). The river rises in central Angola as the Cuando River before
						becoming the Linyanti River and then, from Lake Liambezi (in Namibia), the
						Chobe River (Augustyn et al. 1998a).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0085" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Chuantsa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Possibly Nkokwane Pan, just south of
						Ntwetwe Pan and about ten miles north-east of present-day Orapa in
						north-eastern Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0086" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Chukutsa Pan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Nchokotsa by Livingstone. Pan or depression to the
						south of Ntwetwe Pan and in the immediate vicinity of Ryasana Pan, in
						present-day north-eastern Botswana (Schapera 1960a:6n2, Ransford
						1978:49).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0087" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Chundu</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Chondo by Livingstone. Island in the middle of the
						Zambezi River, on the boundary between present-day south-western Zambia and
						north-western Zimbabwe. It is about fifteen miles upstream from Victoria
						Falls (Schapera 1963,2:325n5).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0088" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Congo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Formerly known as the Zaire River. Also called Zerézeré
						by Livingstone. Major river in Africa and the second longest on the
						continent after the Nile River. It rises in present-day north-eastern Zambia
						and flows in an arc to the west coast, entering the Atlantic Ocean at Banana
						in Democratic Republic of the Congo. During his final journey (1866-73),
						Livingstone explored parts of the Congo River system while under the
						misconception that it connected to the Nile.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0089" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Cuacua River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as Rio dos Bons Sinais. Called Kilimane by
						Livingstone. River in Mozambique that enters the sea near the port city,
						Quelimane.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0090" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Cuanza River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Coanza by Livingstone. Major river in Angola that
						rises on the Bié Plateau and flows to the west, entering the Atlantic about
						thirty miles south of Luanda.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0091" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Cuije River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Quize by Livingstone. River of north-western
						Angola and tributary of the Cuanza River, which it joins near present-day
						Cangandala in Malanje Province (Schapera 1963,1:133n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0092" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Dande River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in northern Angola, that enters the Atlantic about
						twenty-five miles above Luanda at Barro do Dande.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0093" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Danube River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Second longest river in Europe (after the Volga), rising
						in western Germany and flowing to the Black Sea.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0094" type="geogName_cave">
					<placeName type="main">Fingal's Cave</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Sea cave on the south-west coast of Staffa, one of the
						islands of the Inner Hebrides. The cave is notable for the hexagonal basalt
						columns that surround it.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0095" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Goha Hills</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Ngwa by Livingstone. Hills in the Savuti region of
						present-day northern Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0096" type="geogName_bay">
					<placeName type="main">Guanabara Bay</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Bay of Rio de Janeiro by Livingstone. A bay of the
						South Atlantic Ocean in south-eastern Brazil. The city of Rio de Janeiro is
						located on the bay's western shore.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0097" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Impalila Island</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Mparia by Livingstone. Island at the confluence of
						the Chobe and Zambezi rivers in present-day Namibia's Caprivi Strip
						(Schapera 1963,2:325n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0098" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Isle of Dogs</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Area of east London consisting of Millwall, Cubitt Town,
						and Canary Wharf that is surrounded on three sides by the River
						Thames.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0099" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kabompo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in south-central Africa and a major tributary of
						the Zambezi River. It rises in present-day Zambia's North Western Province
						and flows south and west to enter the Zambezi River about fifteen miles
						north of Lukulu in Western Province. Livingstone sometimes mistakenly refers
						to the Kabompo River as the Leeambye (another name for the Zambezi River),
						since he incorrectly believed the Kabompo to be the main stream of the
						Zambezi rather than a tributary (Schapera 1963,1:27n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0100" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kafue River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in present-day Zambia and a major tributary of the
						Zambezi River. It rises in North Western Province near the border with
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo and winds southwards to join
						the Zambezi River several miles above Chirundu on the Zimbabwean
						border.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0101" type="geogName_desert">
					<placeName type="main">Kalahari Desert</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Large sandy plain in southern Africa, covering much of
						present-day Botswana, the eastern part of Namibia, and the northern part of
						South Africa's Northern Cape. Livingstone first crossed the Kalahari to
						reach Lake Ngami in 1849.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0102" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Kalai Island</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island on the Zambezi River, about six miles upstream
						from Victoria Falls.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0103" type="geogName_cataracts">
					<placeName type="main">Kale Rapids</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, rapids on
						the Zambezi River between Ngonye Falls in present-day Zambia's Western
						Province and Katima Mulilo in present-day Namibia's Caprivi Strip.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0104" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kalomo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Tributary of the Zambezi River, which it joins in
						present-day Zambia's Southern Province about thirty-five miles downstream
						from Victoria Falls.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0105" type="geogName_rivulet">
					<placeName type="main">Kaluze River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Schapera suggests this is the Calozi
						River, which he identifies as a tributary that joins the Kasai River about
						forty miles south-east of Dala in present-day Lunda Sul Province in eastern
						Angola (Schapera 1963,1:101n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0106" type="geogName_valley">
					<placeName type="main">Kandehy</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. A valley probably in the vinicity of
						present-day Kasinka in northern Botswana's Chobe District (Schapera
						1960a:111n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0107" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kanesi River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Possibly the Tchinege River, which
						flows into the Chiumbe River in eastern Angola's present-day Lunda Sul
						Province (Schapera 1963,2:241n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0108" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kaongeshi River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Lueta River. Called Caunguesi by
						Livingstone. Tributary of the Kasai River in the southern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo (Schapera 1963,2:245n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0109" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kasai River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Casai and Loke by Livingstone. River in
						central Africa and a major tributary of the Congo River, that forms part of
						the border between present-day Angola and Democratic Republic of the Congo.
						The Kasai River rises in Angola on the Bié Plateau and flows into the Congo
						River at Kwamouth in the western part of Democratic Republic of the
						Congo.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0110" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Kasala</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a mountain
						in the vicinity of Cassange in north-central Angola's present-day Lunda
						Norte Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0111" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Khama-Khama Pan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Kama Kama by Livingstone. Pan or depression in
						present-day north-eastern Botswana. On one of Livingstone's visits there in
						March 1853, it was the home of members of the Khoesan led by Horoye and
						Mokantsa (Schapera 1960a:102).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0112" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kolobeng River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in present-day south-eastern Botswana. Livingstone
						built his third mission station near this river in 1847, just west of
						present-day Gaborone.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0113" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Koobe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a spring
						on the south-western edge of Ntwetwe Pan in present-day north-eastern
						Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0114" type="geogName_stream">
					<placeName type="main">Kopong</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Khopong by Livingstone. River crossing the
						northward road from Kolobeng, about seventeen miles north of present-day
						Molepole in Botswana. Today, there is a village of this name about ten miles
						north of Gaborone (Schapera 1960a:3n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0115" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Koue Bokkeveld Mountains</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Bokkefelt by Livingstone. Mountain range in
						present-day South Africa's Western Cape.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0116" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kuruman River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in present-day South Africa's Northern Cape that is
						now mostly dry. Robert and Mary Moffat, Livingstone's parents-in-law,
						established the Kuruman mission station near this river in the 1820s.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0117" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kwango River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as Cuango River. Called Quango by Livingstone.
						Major river of central Africa that rises in central Angola and flows into
						the Kasai River near the present-day city of Bandundu in the western part of
						Democratic Republic of the Congo (Kisangani 2016:365).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0118" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Kwilu River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Quilo and Kweelo by Livingstone. Major river that
						rises in Angola and flows north into the western part of present-day
						Democratic Republic of the Congo. It joins the Kwango (or Cuango) River near
						the city of Bandundu, shortly before the Kwango flows into the Kasai River
						(Kisangani 2016:366).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0119" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Dilolo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Lake in present-day Moxico Province in eastern
						Angola.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0120" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Malawi</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as Lake Nyasa (in Tanzania) and Lago Niassa
						(in Mozambique). Called Lake Nyassa by Livingstone. Third largest lake in
						east Africa, lying between Malawi, Mozambique, and Tanzania. Livingstone
						reached this lake in 1859 during his second major African expedition
						(1858-64).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0121" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Ngami</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Shallow lake in present-day north-western Botswana. It is
						north of the Kalahari Desert and at the south-western end of the Okavango
						Delta. Livingstone first reached this lake in 1849 with William Cotton
						Oswell.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0122" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Tanganyika</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lake Tanganyenka by Livingstone. Second largest
						lake in east Africa. It lies mainly between present-day Tanzania and
						Democratic Republic of the Congo, while also entering Burundi and
						Zambia.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0123" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">Lake Xau</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as Lake Dow. Called Kumadau by Livingstone.
						Intermittent lake in present-day north-central Botswana, about forty-five
						miles west of Orapa. The lake is usually dry but is sometimes fed by the
						Boteti River (Hughes and Hughes 1992:625).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0124" type="geogName_headland">
					<placeName type="main">Land's End</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Peninsula in Cornwall and the most westerly point of
						mainland England.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0125" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lekone River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Schapera suggests this is the Lukuni
						River, which he identifies as a feeder of the Sinde, a river that in turn
						flows into the Zambezi River just west of present-day Livingstone in
						Zambia's Southern Province (Schapera 1963,2:333n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0126" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Lephephe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lopepe by Livingstone. Spring about fifteen miles
						north of Boatlanama and about forty-five miles south-west of the BaNgwato
						capital, Shoshong, in present-day east-central Botswana (Schapera 1959,
						2:64n22).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0127" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Liambezi Lake</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Zabesa or Zabenza by Livingstone. Shallow lake in
						present-day Namibia's Caprivi Strip near the border with Botswana formed by
						the broadening of the Chobe River (Schapera 1963,1:1n3; Hughes and Hughes
						1992:696).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0128" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Libolo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Libollo by Livingstone. Highland region in
						north-western Angola's present-day Cuanza Sul Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0129" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Likuáre River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingtone, a feeder of
						the Cuacua River (or Rio dos Bons Sinais) in Mozambique.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0130" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Limpopo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River of south-eastern Africa that rises in the
						Witswaterand in present-day South Africa and flows to the Indian
						Ocean.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0131" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Livoa River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Schapera suggests this is a
						tributary of the Luambo, a river that runs into the Chifumage River, which
						in turn joins the Zambezi River in present-day eastern Angola (Schapera
						1963,1:78n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0132" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Lobotani</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Spring about fifty miles west of the BaNgwato capital,
						Shoshong, in present-day east-central Botswana (Schapera 1960a:4n4)</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0133" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lokalueje River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Kalueje by Livingstone. Reference uncertain.
						Schapera suggests this is the Luambo, a river that runs into the Chifumage
						River, which is a tributary of the Zambezi River in present-day eastern
						Angola (Schapera 1963,1:74n1; 1963,2:262n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0134" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lombe River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in north-western Angola and a tributary of the
						Cuanza River, which it joins about twenty miles west of present-day
						Cangandala (Schapera 1963,1:134n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0135" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Loyela</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island on the Zambezi River in present-day Zambia's
						Western Province, about eight miles south-west of Namushakende.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0136" type="geogName_rivulet">
					<placeName type="main">Lozeze River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Schapera suggests this is the
						Luicheze River, which he identifies as a tributary joining the Kasai River
						in north-eastern Angola's present-day Lunda Sul Province (Schapera
						1963,1:101n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0137" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luachimo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Loajima by Livingstone. River rising in Angola and
						a major tribuary of the Kasai River, which it joins near the present-day
						city of Tshikapa in Democratic Republic of the Congo (Schapera
						1963,1:112n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0138" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lualua River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Luare by Livingstone. Tributary of the Cuacua
						River, which it joins in east-central Mozambique (Schapera
						1963,2:471n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0139" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luangue River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Loange River. River rising in Angola
						and a tributary of the Kasai River, which it joins about fifteen miles
						upstream of present-day Dibaya-Lubwe in south-western Democratic Republic of
						Congo (Schapera 1963,1:227n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0140" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luangwa River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Loangwa by Livingstone. River in present-day
						Zambia and a major tributary of the Zambezi River. It rises near Isoka and
						flows southwards to enter the Zambezi River between Luangwa (Zambia) and
						Zombo (Mozambique).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0141" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luare River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Schapera suggests this is a feeder
						of the Lui River in northern Angola (Schapera 1963,1:131n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0142" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lubilash River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Sankuru River in its lower course.
						River in the southern part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo
						and the primary tributary of the Kasai River, which it joins near
						Bena-Bendi.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0143" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lucala River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lucalla by Livingstone. River in north-western
						Angola and a major tributary of the Cuanza River, which it joins near
						present-day Massangano in Cuanze Norte Province (Newitt 2010:142n4).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0144" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luembe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Loembwe by Livingstone. River rising in Angola and
						a tributary of the Kasai River, which it joins about twenty-five miles
						upstream of present-day Tshikapa in south-western Democratic Republic of the
						Congo (Schapera 1963,1:108n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0145" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lufige River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lefuje by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						that joins the Zambezi River in present-day Moxico Province, about ten miles
						north of the Zambian border (Schapera 1963,1:47n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0146" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lui River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in northern Angola and a tributary of the Kwango
						(or Cuango) River, which it joins near present-day Milando in Lunda Norte
						Province (Schapera 1963,1:131n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0147" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Luinha River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in present-day Cuanza Norte Province in
						north-western Angola.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0149" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lulua River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lolo and Lolua by Livingstone. River in
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo. While Livingstone says this
						river flows southwards, it actually flows northwards to enter the Kasai
						River near Bena Makima (Schapera 1963,1:87n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0150" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lunache River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lonatje by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						and tributary of the Zambezi River, which it joins about twenty miles
						south-west of present-day Cazombo in Moxico Province (Schapera
						1963,1:66n4).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0151" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lungwebungu River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Loeti and Langebongo by Livingstone. River in
						south-west-central Africa and the largest tributary of the Zambezi River. It
						rises in central Angola, flowing east and south-east to join the Zambezi
						River about six miles north of present-day Lukulu in Zambia's Western
						Province (Schapera 1963,1:1n4).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0152" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lunkuni</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Longkonye by Livingstone. River in present-day
						north-western Zambia that joins the Zambezi River near the Angolan border,
						about seven miles north-west of Chinyingi in North-Western Province
						(Schapera 1963,1:37n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0153" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Lurilopepe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Indentifed by Livingstone as a pan
						or depression in the immediate vicinity of Khama Khama Pan in present-day
						north-eastern Botswana. In his journals, Livingstone uses the names Liuli
						Lipepe and Lurilophepe for the same place (Schapera 1960a:11, 102).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0154" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Lutembo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lotembwa by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						and tributary of the Chifumage River, which it joins about forty-five miles
						west of present-day Cazombo in Moxico Province (Schapera
						1963,1:81n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0155" type="geogName_rivulet">
					<placeName type="main">Lutete River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lotete by Livingstone. Tributary of the Lucala
						River, which it joins in north-western Angola (Schapera
						1963,1:204n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0156" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Mababe River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Identified by Schapera as a
						watercourse connecting the Ngoga River to the Mababe Depression in
						present-day northern Botswana (Schapera 1960a:13n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0157" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Madeira Islands</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Archipelago of two inhabited islands (Madeira and Porto
						Santo) and two groups of uninhabited islands (the Desertas and the
						Selvagens) in the Atlantic Ocean, about 600 miles south-west of
						Portugal.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0158" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Magaliesberg Mountains</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Cashan Mountains by Livingstone. Mountain
						range in present-day northern South Africa, extending from Pretoria to
						Rustenburg (Appiah and Gates Jr. 2005:251).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0159" type="geogName_rivulet">
					<placeName type="main">Magoye River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Makoe by Livingstone. River in southern Zambia and
						tributary of the Kafue River, which it joins near present-day Mazabuka in
						Southern Province (Schapera 1963,2:351n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0160" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Makondo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River of present-day Angola and Zambia and tributary of
						the Zambezi River, which it joins near present-day Chinyingi in Zambia's
						North-Western Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0161" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Maloti Mountains</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Maluti Mountains. Mountain range in
						present-day Lesotho.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0162" type="geogName_pass">
					<placeName type="main">Manakalongwe Pass</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Unicorn's Pass and Porapora by Livingstone.
						Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a pass in the Shoshong Hills
						in present-day east-central Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0163" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Marico River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Madikwe River. Called Marikwe by
						Livingstone. River in the north-eastern part of present-day South Africa,
						that forms one of the main headstreams of the Limpopo River (Schapera
						1960a:18n18).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0164" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Marile River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Schapera, a river that
						branches off the Zambezi River and rejoins the main channel near Mongu in
						present-day Zambia's Western Province (Schapera 1960a:21n8, 224n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0165" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Mashuwe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Mashue by Livingstone. Spring about twenty-five
						miles west of the BaNgwato capital, Shoshong, in present day east-central
						Botswana (Ransford 1978:75, Schapera 1960a:4n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0166" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Mathuluani</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a spring
						fifty miles north of Serotle on the road to Chukutsa Pan in present-day
						east-central Botswana (Schapera 1960a:304-5).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0167" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Matlomaganyana</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Links by Livingstone. Series of springs in
						the vinicity of present-day Matlamanyane in north-eastern Botswana (Schapera
						1960a:10n5, Spinage 2012:202).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0168" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Mauritius</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island in the Indian Ocean, about 550 miles east of
						Madagascar. Livingstone sailed via Mauritius on his return to Britain in
						1856, following his transcontinental expedition.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0169" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Mohotluani</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Possibly another spelling for
						Mathuluani, a spring that Livingstone locates fifty miles north of Serotle
						on the road to Chukutsa Pan in present-day east-central Botswana (Schapera
						1960a:304-5).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0170" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Mokoko River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Dry river bed in present-day east-central Botswana that
						remains a major landmark around Letlhakane (Steyn and Atamelang
						2014:49).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0171" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Mokokonyani</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a spring
						in the vicinity of present-day Letlhakane in east-central Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0172" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Mombo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Moamba by Livingstone. River in eastern Angola
						that joins the Luachimo River about twenty miles north-east of present-day
						Saurimo in Lunda Sul Province (Schapera 1963,2:239n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0173" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Monzuma River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Mozuma and Dila by Livingstone. River in
						present-day southern Zambia that joins the Zongwe River near Lake Kariba
						(Schapera 1963,2:346n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0174" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Mosamba</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Since Livingstone describes Mosamba
						as the source of the Kwango (or Cuango) River, he is possibly referring to
						the Alto Chicapa highlands of north-central Angola where that river
						rises.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0175" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Motlatsa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a spring
						in the vicinity of present-day Letlhakane on the road to Chukutsa Pan in
						east-central Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0176" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Mount Morrumbala</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Morumbala by Livingstone. Mountain of central
						Mozambique in present-day Zambezia Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0177" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Mount Gorongosa </placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Mountain of central Mozambique in present-day Sofala
						Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0178" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Mull</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island of the Inner Hebrides, off the west coast of
						Scotland.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0179" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Mutirikwe River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Motirikwe by Livingstone. River in present-day
						south-eastern Zimbabwe and a tributary of the Runde, a river that latterly
						joins the Save River at the Mozambique border.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0180" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Muto River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Mutue and Mutu by Livingstone. Channel connecting
						the Zambezi and Cuacua rivers in east-central Mozambique, in the vicinity of
						present-day Mopeia District (Schapera 1963,2:471n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0181" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Namilanga</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Spring in the vinicity of present-day Senkobo in Zambia's
						Southern Province (Schapera 1963,2:335n4).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0182" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Nampene Island</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island on the Zambezi River near present-day Katombora in
						Zambia's Southern Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0183" type="geogName_cataracts">
					<placeName type="main">Ngambwe Rapids</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Nambue and Nambwe by Livingstone. Rapids on the
						Zambezi River about fifteen miles above present-day Sesheke in Zambia's
						Western Province (Schapera 1960a: 194n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0184" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Ngoga River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Chō and Tsō by Livingstone. Branch of the Okavango
						River in present-day north-western Botswana (Schapera 1960a:26n1, Van der
						Valk 2012:152).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0185" type="geogName_waterfall">
					<placeName type="main">Ngonye Falls</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as Sioma Falls. Called Gonye by Livingstone.
						Waterfall on the Zambezi River a few miles downstream from Sioma in
						present-day Zambia's Western Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0186" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Ngwezi River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Unguesi by Livingstone. River in present-day
						Zambia that joins the Zambezi River about ten miles upriver of Impalila
						island in Southern Province (Schapera 1963,2:336n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0187" type="geogName_waterfall">
					<placeName type="main">Niagara Falls</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major waterfall in North America on the Niagara River, at
						the boundary between Ontario and New York state.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<!-- Derived from glossary entry geog0045 -->
				<place xml:id="geog0188" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Nile River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major river in Africa and the longest river in the world.
						It rises in the Great Lakes region of central Africa and flows north to
						enter the Mediterranean at the Egyptian coast. The search for the source(s)
						of the Nile motivated the African expeditions of a number of important
						Victorian explorers, among them Richard Burton (1821-1890), John H. Speke
						(1827-1864), Samuel W. Baker (1821-1893), Henry M. Stanley (1841-1904), and,
						of course, Livingstone himself.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0189" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Nkowane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Nkauane by Livingstone. Spring in the vicinity of
						Nkowane Pan in present-day east-central Botswana, about forty miles
						south-east of Letlhakane (Schapera 1960a:5n8).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0190" type="geogName_lake">
					<placeName type="main">North Loch</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Former loch in Edinburgh, Scotland, in the area that is
						now Princes Street Gardens. The loch was created by King James III in the
						fifteenth century in order to bolster the defences of Edinburgh Castle and
						was drained in the eighteenth century. Livingstone incorrectly identifies
						North Loch with the Edinburgh Meadows, but the Meadows are in fact on the
						site of the former Burgh Loch (also known as South Loch) (Crawford 2013:100,
						Coghill 2005:75).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0191" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Ntwetwe Pan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Large pan or depression in present-day north-eastern
						Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0192" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Nyamonga </placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a mountain
						of central Mozambique in the vicinity of Mount Gorongosa.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0193" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Okavango River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Embarrah and Varra by Livingstone. Major river in
						southern Africa. It rises as the Kubango River on the Bié Plateau of central
						Angola, and crosses present-day Namibia's Caprivi Strip into Botswana where
						it widens into the Okavango Delta.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0194" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Orange River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major river of southern Africa that rises in present-day
						Lesotho and flows west to enter the Atlantic at Alexander Bay on South
						Africa's west coast.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0195" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Orapa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Spring in present-day north-eastern Botswana about
						fifteen miles north-west of Letlhakane. Today, Orapa is the site of a major
						diamond mine.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0196" type="geogName_fountain">
					<placeName type="main">Otse</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Spring in the vicinity of Otse Hill in present-day
						south-eastern Botswana, about twenty-five miles south-west of Gaborone. Otse
						is also the name of the local village.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0197" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Pezo River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Schapera suggests this is the Peso
						River, which he identifies as a tributary that joins the Luangue River in
						northern Angola's present-day Lunda Norte Province (Schapera
						1963,1:234n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0198" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Piri</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Peeri by Livingstone. Hills near present-day
						Cazombo in eastern Angola's Moxico Province. Schapera notes that this is not
						a specific geographical place name but is rather the Luvale word for hill or
						mountain, "pili" (Livingstone 1857aa:306-07, 685; Schapera
						1963,1:69n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0199" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Ranges of Cahenda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, mountains
						in north-western Angola just north of Ambaca.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0200" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Rapesh</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a spring
						to the north of Ntwetwe Pan, near present-day Gweta in north-eastern
						Botswana. In his journals, Livingstone also uses the name Kiadjara for the
						same place (Schapera 1960a:9, 10n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0201" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Rio Cataziana</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Catrina by Livingstone. Distributary of the
						Zambezi River, that enters the sea about seven miles above the
						river's main mouth on the Mozambique coast (Schapera 1963,2:473n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0202" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Rio Mucelo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Maiudo by Livingstone. Distributary of the Zambezi
						River, which branches off that river about twenty-five miles from the
						Mozambique coast. It enters the sea about ten miles down the coast
						from the main mouth of the Zambezi River.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0203" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">River Clyde</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in Scotland that rises in the Southern Uplands and
						flows into the Atlantic on the west coast. Livingstone's home town of
						Blantyre is on the Clyde. In the nineteenth century, Clydeside shipyards
						made Glasgow the world's leading shipbuilding city.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0204" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Roggeveld Mountains</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Roggefelt by Livingstone. Mountain range in
						present-day South Africa's Northern Cape.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0205" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Saloisho</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a range of
						hills in the vicinity of Shinde's town (the paramount of the southern
						Lunda), which was near the confluence of the Lumbala and Zambezi rivers in
						present-day eastern Angola's Moxico province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0206" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Sanshureh River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a branch
						of the Chobe River filled by seasonal flooding in present-day Namibia's
						Caprivi Strip.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0207" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Save River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Sabi River. Called Sabia and Sabe by
						Livingstone. River in south-eastern Africa that rises near present-day
						Harare in Zimbabwe and enters the Indian Ocean on the Mozambique
						coast.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0208" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Savuti Channel</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Sonta by Livingstone. Intermittent and
						predominantly dry channel in present-day northern Botswana that connects the
						Linyanti Swamps and the Mababe Depression (Ransford 1978:62, Schapera
						1960a:15n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0209" type="geogName_fountain">
					<placeName type="main">Serinane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a hot
						spring in the vicinity of present-day Lephephe in east-central
						Botswana.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0210" type="geogName_fountain">
					<placeName type="main">Serotli</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Spring about fifty miles north-west of the BaNgwato
						capital, Shoshong, in present-day east-central Botswana (Schapera
						1960a:304n7).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0211" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Shire River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major river of present-day Malawi that flows south from
						Lake Malawi to join the Zambezi River in central Mozambique about thirty
						miles downstream of Sena. Livingstone explored this river and the Shire
						Highlands during his Zambezi Expedition (1858-64).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0212" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Shoshong Hills</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Bamangwato hills and Bakaa mountains by
						Livingstone. Hills in present-day east-central Botswana. The BaNgwato and
						BaKaa settled there in the eighteenth century and were resident in the
						vicinity during Livingstone's period in Botswana (Schapera 1960a:304n6,
						1961:17n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0213" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Southern Lueti River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Simah by Livingstone. River in present-day
						Zambia's Western Province (Schapera 1960a:175n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0214" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Sulina Channel</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Distributary of the Danube River in Romania.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0215" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Taba Cheu</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a hill in
						present-day southern Zambia in the vicinity of Lake Kariba.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0216" type="geogName_mountain">
					<placeName type="main">Table Mountain</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Mountain at the northern point of present-day South
						Africa's Cape Peninsula, notable for its distinctive flat top.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0217" type="geogName_rivulet">
					<placeName type="main">Tamba River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River in north-eastern Angola that joins the Mombo River
						in present-day Lunda Sul Province, shortly before the Mombo flows into the
						Luachimo River (Schapera 1963,2:237n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0218" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Taprobane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Name used by the ancient Greeks for Sri Lanka.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0219" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Thamalakane River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Tamunakle by Livingstone. River of present-day
						north-western Botswana that provides a line of drainage from the southern
						Okavango Delta. The river divides just south of Maun to form two branches:
						the Boteti River which flows south-east and the Nhabe River which leads
						south-west towards Lake Ngami (Hughes and Huges 1992:618).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0220" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Thaoge River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Teoughe by Livingstone. River in present-day
						north-western Botswana that was once the major western outlet of the
						Okavango delta. Previously, the river supplied Lake Ngami but it no longer
						does so as a result of diversions to its course (Hughes and Hughes
						1992:618).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0221" type="geogName_spring">
					<placeName type="main">Thutsa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. According to Livingstone, a spring
						in present-day north-eastern Botswana just north-east of Orapa (Schapera
						1960a:70).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0222" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Tsaugara Pan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Maila by Livingstone. Pan or depression in
						present-day north-eastern Botswana, to the north of Ntwetwe Pan and the east
						of Khama Khama Pan (Schapera 1960a:11n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0223" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Tshikapa River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Chikapa by Livingstone. Tributary of the Kasai
						River, which it joins about forty miles north of the Angolan border in
						present-day south-western Democratic Republic of the Congo (Schapera
						1963,1:116n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0224" type="geogName_hill">
					<placeName type="main">Tsodilo Hills</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Sorila by Livingstone. Hills in present-day
						north-western Botswana about twenty-five miles west of Sepupa and thirty
						miles south of the Namibian border. They are known for their ancient rock
						paintings, which number over 4000 and appear at hundreds of distinct sites
						(Schapera 1960a:67n1; Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:34-35).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0225" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Ulva</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island just west of Mull, and part of the Inner Hebrides
						off the west coast of Scotland. Livingstone's grandfather Neil had been a
						farmer in Ulva before he moved to Blantyre in 1792.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0226" type="geogName_pan">
					<placeName type="main">Unku</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Possibly Kumsedisha Pan, just
						north-east of Khama Khama Pan in present-day north-eastern Botswana. In his
						journals, Livingstone also uses the name Gumkirreh for the same place
						(Schapera 1960a:11n4).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0227" type="geogName_valley">
					<placeName type="main">Upper Zambezi valley</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called valley of the Leeambye by Livingstone. Region
						surrounding the upper part of the Zambezi River.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0228" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Vaal River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Likwa by Livingstone. River of present-day South
						Africa and a tributary of the Orange River. It rises in Mpumalanga and flows
						south-west to join the Orange near Douglas in the Northern Cape.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0229" type="geogName_valley">
					<placeName type="main">Valley of the Nile</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in Egypt around the course of the Nile
						River.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0230" type="geogName_waterfall">
					<placeName type="main">Victoria Falls</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">One of the world's largest waterfalls, located on the
						Zambezi River, and bordering present-day Zambia and Zimbabwe. Livingstone
						sighted the falls in November 1855 and gave them the name Victoria Falls.
						They are known as Mosi-oa-Tunya in Lozi and as Shongwe in the Shona
						language.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0231" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Wilge River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Namagari by Livingstone. River in present-day
						central South Africa and tributary of the Vaal (Dreyer 2001:73).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0232" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Zambezi River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Leeba/Loiba and Leeambye/Liambai by
						Livingstone at parts of its course. Major river in south-central Africa that
						rises in present-day Zambia, then flows east across the continent to the
						Indian Ocean. During his transcontinental expedition (1852-56), Livingstone
						was hopeful that the Zambezi could provide a highway into central Africa,
						but during his later Zambezi Expedition (1858-64) he realised that he had
						overestimated the river's navigability. Livingstone provides various other
						local names for stretches of the river including Luambéji, Luambési, Ambézi,
						Ojimbési, Luabo, and Cuama.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0233" type="geogName_river">
					<placeName type="main">Zangue River</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Pungue by Livingstone. Tributary of the
						Zambezi River, which it joins near present-day Caia in Mozambique's Sofala
						Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="geog0234" type="geogName_island">
					<placeName type="main">Zanzibar</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island in the Indian Ocean off the coast of present-day
						Tanzania. In the nineteenth century, Zanzibar was the major center of a
						commercial network extending across east and central Africa and the primary
						entrepôt of the east African and Indian Ocean slave trade (Sheriff
						1987:1-4).</note>
				</place>



			</listPlace>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
