<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Livingstone Online: Annotated Organization List</title>
				<author>Adrian S. Wisnicki</author>
				<author>Megan Ward</author>
				<author>Justin D. Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2019</date>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">(c)
						Livingstone Online. <ref
							target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
							Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License</ref>.</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>A Livingstone Online project.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<listOrg>

				<!-- Current higest number = org0090 -->

				<org xml:id="org0001">
					<orgName type="main">2nd Egyptian expedition</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Expedition (1840-41) organized by Muhammad Ali, Viceroy
						of Egypt (r. 1805–48), and led by Joseph-Pons d'Arnauld, Louis Sabatier, and
						Ferdinand Werne that navigated the White Nile to 4° 42' N in 1841. The first
						expedition (1839-40) only reached as far as, roughly, the modern town of
						Bor, Sudan (6° 12' N.).</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0003">
					<orgName type="main">Banian</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Related to people who were an offshoot of the Indian
						merchant class at Muscat and became important traders in Zanzibar.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0004">
					<orgName type="main">Banian slaves</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Group of liberated slaves formerly owned by Banian
						merchants and hired by John Kirk, the acting British Consul and Political
						Resident at Zanzibar, to assist Livingstone. These slaves were a constant
						source of irritation to Livingstone due to their resistance to his travel
						plans.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0005">
					<orgName type="main">Banians</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">People who were an offshoot of the Indian merchant class
						at Muscat and were important traders in Zanzibar</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0006">
					<orgName type="main">Boers</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">European farmers who settled at the Cape. They were
						predominantly, though not exclusively, of Dutch origin. After the Great Trek
						of the 1830s, the term was used interchangeably with Voortrekkers.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0008">
					<orgName type="main">Cushite</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Person from Cush (in present-day Ethiopia).</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0010">
					<orgName type="main">Johanna men</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Group of ten men (including their leader Musa) from
						Johanna (Anjouan), Comoros, who accompanied Livingstone during his last
						journey. The Johanna men had been hired with the assistance of the British
						Consul at Johanna.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0030">
					<orgName type="main">Governors D'Almrida</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">The brothers João Tavares d'Almeida (Governor-General of
						Mozambique) and António Tavares d'Almeida (Governor of Tete) who held their
						respective positions during the time of Livingstone's Zambezi Expedition
						(1858-64).</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0011">
					<orgName type="main">Kilwans</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">People from Kilwa. Kilwa (a collective name for Kilwa
						Kisiwani, Kilwa Kivinje, and Kilwa Masoko, all in present-day Tanzania) was
						one of the most important centers for the slave trade on the east coast of
						Africa in the nineteenth century.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0013">
					<orgName type="main">London Hunterian Society</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Society of medical professionals based in London, founded
						in 1819 and named in honor of the Scottish surgeon John Hunter.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0014">
					<orgName type="main">London Missionary Society</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Non-denominational missionary society formed in England
						in 1795 by evangelical Christians, primarily serving missions in Africa and
						the South Pacific.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0007">
					<orgName type="main">Messrs Coutts and Co.</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone's bankers, based on the Strand in
						London.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0015">
					<orgName type="main">Moravian</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Related to Moravia, a region in the eastern part of the
						present-day Czech Republic.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0002">
					<orgName type="main">Nassick African Asylum</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Government-run school for freed slaves in Nashik,
						India.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0017">
					<orgName type="main">Nassickers</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Group of nine men who accompanied Livingstone on his last
						journey selected on the advice of Sir Bartle Frere, then Governor of Bombay,
						from a government-run school for freed slaves in Nashik, India.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0018">
					<orgName type="main">P &amp; O company</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Company. British
						shipping company.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0019">
					<orgName type="main">Phoenician</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Person from the ancient civilization of Phoenicia, on the
						coastlines of present-day Lebanon, Palestine, Israel, and Syria.</note>
				</org>


				<org xml:id="org0025">
					<orgName type="main">Ringleading Nassick deserters</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">The Nassickers were a group of nine men who accompanied
						Livingstone on his last journey selected on the advice of Sir Bartle Frere,
						then Governor of Bombay, from a government-run school for freed slaves in
						Nashik, India.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0022">
					<orgName type="main">Royal Academy</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Institution designed to promote the arts, founded in
						London in 1768.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0020">
					<orgName type="main">Royal Geographical Society</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Society of geographers, founded in 1830 in London. One of
						Livingstone's sponsoring organizations.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0021">
					<orgName type="main">Routledge</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">British publishing company.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0023">
					<orgName type="main">Sepoys</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Group from the Bombay Marine Battalion and under the
						command of an Indian corporal that joined Livingstone for part of his last
						journey.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0024">
					<orgName type="main">Swahili</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">African group of complex intercultural origins. Resides
						along the coast of east Africa from Somalia to Mozambique.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0026">
					<orgName type="main">Ujijian</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Ujiji, a village on the eastern shore of Lake Tanganyika,
						served as one of the major trading depots in the Arab-African trading
						network of east Africa in the nineteenth century.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0027">
					<orgName type="main">Ujijian traders</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Ujiji, a village on the eastern shore of Lake Tanganyika,
						served as one of the major trading depots in the Arab-African trading
						network of east Africa in the nineteenth century.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0028">
					<orgName type="main">Ujijian trading</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Ujiji, a village on the eastern shore of Lake Tanganyika,
						served as one of the major trading depots in the Arab-African trading
						network of east Africa in the nineteenth century.</note>
				</org>

				<org xml:id="org0009">
					<orgName type="main">Voertrekkers</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Dutch and other European settlers who voluntarily left
						the Cape Colony in the 1830s during the Greak Trek, a series of migrations
						north into the southern African interior in order to escape British control.
						The Voortrekkers eventually established the Boer Republics, the Orange Free
						State and the Transvaal.</note>
				</org>



				<!-- Missionary Travels Glossary List -->

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0052">
					<orgName type="main">27th (Inniskilling) Regiment of Foot</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Enniskillens by Livingstone. Irish infantry
						regiment in the British Army, dating from 1689, acclaimed for its role at
						the Battle of Waterloo. In 1881, it merged with the 108th (Madras Infantry)
						Regiment to form the Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers (Chant
						2013:183-84).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0031">
					<orgName type="main">Aboriginal</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone uses the term to refer to indigenous
						inhabitants.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0032">
					<orgName type="main">Admiralty</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Government department responsible for managing the
						British Royal Navy, from the early nineteenth century until 1964 when it was
						amalgamated into the newly created Ministry of Defence.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0033">
					<orgName type="main">Afro-Portuguese</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Called African Portuguese, Native Portuguese, and
						"half-caste" by Livingstone. These variety of terms are used to refer to
						traders of Afro-Portuguese descent who had established routes and networks
						in central Africa.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0034">
					<orgName type="main">Algerine Arabs</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference to the people of Algeria, or more broadly to
						North African Muslim communities.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0035">
					<orgName type="main">Ambaquistas</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Ambacistas and Ambakistas by Livingstone.
						Inhabitants of Ambaca, an early Portuguese trading centre in west Africa.
						The term originated in the 1840s to describe Kimbundu-speaking
						Afro-Portuguese traders from Ambaca, who had acquired a significant presence
						in west African commerce, particularly in slaves and ivory. Later, it was
						also used less precisely by some contemporary commentators to refer to any
						Kimbundu-speaking traders in Portuguese Africa who behaved in ways regarded
						as "European" (Fish and Fish 2002:76, Dias 1986:292-93).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0036">
					<orgName type="main">Anatolian Sipahis</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Annatolans by Livingstone. Cavalrymen of the
						Ottoman Empire, in Asia Minor. They were a privileged class, holding local
						fiefdoms in exchange for military service. Livingstone draws a parallel
						between the sipahis, fighting on behalf of their people, and the "Kaffir
						Police," an AmaXhosa force established by the Cape Colony in the 1830s which
						largely revolted against the colonial administration during the Eighth Cape
						Frontier War (Augustyn et al. 2017g, Ross 2014:183).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0039">
					<orgName type="main">Anglo-Portuguese Mixed Commission for the Suppression of
						Slavery in Cape Town</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Mixed or Joint Commissions were judicial bodies created
						as a means of enforcing anti-slavery treaties in international contexts.
						Held between nation states, in this case between Britain and Portugal, they
						delivered verdicts on vessels seized for suspected slave trafficking
						(Niekerk 2004a:196-97).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0037">
					<orgName type="main">Baptist</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Protestant movement, with origins in seventeenth-century
						English Puritanism. It encompasses a range of groups and denominations,
						which lay particular emphasis on the doctrine of believer's baptism by
						immersion. Most Baptists follow a congregational model of church governance.
						The Baptist Missionary Society was formed in 1792 and made African missions
						a priority from the 1840s (Stanley 1992).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0038">
					<orgName type="main">Boers</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">European farmers of Dutch, German, and Huguenot origin
						who settled at the Cape in the eighteenth century. Large numbers of their
						descendants left the Cape Colony, migrating north beyond British rule in the
						"Great Trek" of 1836-46. These settlers, or Voortrekkers, established
						independent states in the southern African interior, including the South
						African Republic (or the Transvaal), the Natalia Republic, and the Orange
						Free State (Raugh 2004:53-54).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0055">
					<orgName type="main">British German Legion</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">German military unit, raised in 1854 to fight for the
						British in the Crimean War. The war ended before the legion saw combat, and
						in 1856 the majority were instead settled in British Kaffraria. Sir George
						Grey, the Cape Governor, hoped they would provide increased protection
						against the AmaXhosa on the eastern Cape and act as a civilising influence.
						The scheme was unsuccessful. Half the legion left South Africa in 1858 to
						fight against the Indian Mutiny, and in 1861 the remainder were
						decommissioned (Laband 2009a:85-86, 101-03).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0040">
					<orgName type="main">British Museum</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Britain's premier national museum, established in 1753.
						Its current building in Bloomsbury, London, was built between 1823 and
						1852.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0041">
					<orgName type="main">Bushmen</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Another term for the San people of southern Africa
						(primarily resident in Botswana, Namibia, and south-eastern Angola), who
						historically adopted a hunter-gatherer lifestyle. The term Bushmen is still
						in use, but it is contested and sometimes considered pejorative (Heath
						2010a:222).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0044">
					<orgName type="main">Chartist movement</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Working class movement of the 1830s and 40s that
						advocated British political reform through parliamentary means. Their major
						goals were articulated in The People's Charter which demanded universal male
						voting rights, voting by secret ballot, salaries for MPs, an end to property
						qualifications for election, the construction of equal electoral districts,
						and annual parliamentary elections. The movement was also active in
						campaigning for land reform (Epstein 1994:136).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0045">
					<orgName type="main">Church Missionary Society</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Church of England missionary agency. A product of the
						evangelical revival, it was established in 1799 as the Society for Missions
						in Africa and the East, before becoming the Church Missionary Society in
						1812. It was the major means of the global spread of Anglicanism in the
						nineteenth century. The majority of its supporters were low church and
						evangelical Anglicans (Melton 2005:147).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0046">
					<orgName type="main">Circassians</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">People group of the Circassia region in the north-western
						Caucasus. From the 1760s the Circassians engaged in an extended war of
						resistance against Russian territorial expansion in the Caucasus, before
						finally being defeated in 1864 (Augustyn et al. 2017a).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0047">
					<orgName type="main">Coldstream Guards</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Oldest infantry regiment in the British Army in
						continuous service, dating from 1650 (Chant 2013:75-76).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0048">
					<orgName type="main">Covenanters</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Seventeenth-century Scottish Presbyterians who resisted
						the imposition of episcopal modes of worship, forming "Covenants" to
						maintain their religious principles in 1638 (the National Covenant) and 1643
						(the Solemn League and Covenant). Having supported the Parliamentarians in
						the English Civil War, they temporarily achieved religious liberty.
						Following the Restoration in 1660 and the reintroduction of Episcopalianism
						in Scotland, they experienced severe persecution for over twenty-five years
						(Kapic and Vander Lugt 2013:38, Spear 1992:88).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0049">
					<orgName type="main">Dollond</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Optical instrument makers. John Dollond (1707–1761) and
						his son, Peter (1731–1820 ), established themselves as opticians in the
						1750s and developed a reputation for producing high-quality instruments.
						They made improvements to refracting telescopes and later developed the
						achromatic lens (Clifton 2013).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0050">
					<orgName type="main">Dutch Reformed</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Protestant tradition that emerged in the Netherlands
						during the sixteenth-century Reformation. Its key theological documents are
						the Belgic Confession, the Heidelberg Catechism, and the Canons of Dort. The
						Dutch Reformed Church in South Africa originated in this tradition, having
						arrived with Dutch emigrants in the seventeenth century. It became the
						largest denomination among South Africa's Afrikaner population and continues
						to be their major church (Augustyn et al. 2017b, 2010).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0051">
					<orgName type="main">Empacasseiros</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">A name given to ancillary African troops employed by the
						Portuguese army in west Africa. They served as part of Portuguese colonial
						defences in Angola, but could also be employed on a private basis as
						sentinels and messengers. The term broadly translates as "buffalo hunters,"
						originating in the seventeenth century as a compound of the Kimbundu word
						for red buffalo, "mpakasa," and the "Portuguese suffix -eiro for the person
						associated with an object" (Birmingham 2011:92, Miller 1976:160).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0053">
					<orgName type="main">Episcopalian</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Christian denominations that follow the episcopal form of
						ecclesiastical structure, in which the church is governed by a hierarchy of
						bishops. Many Epsicopalian churches belong to the worldwide Anglican
						communion.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0054">
					<orgName type="main">Faculty of Physicians and Surgeons of Glasgow</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Institution for the licensing of physicians and surgeons,
						founded in 1599 (known today as the Royal College of Physicians and Surgeons
						of Glasgow). It was unique in serving as a regulatory body for both sections
						of the medical profession, physicians and surgeons. Livingstone had hoped to
						join London's Royal College of Surgeons, but the London Missionary Society
						found the fees prohibitive. Instead, they paid for him to take the more
						affordable examinations of the Glasgow institution, and he became a
						licentiate on 15th November 1840 (Geyer-Kordesch and Macdonald 1999:ix, Ross
						2002:22).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0056">
					<orgName type="main">Government House, Cape Town</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Colonial Governor's residence, built in the 1790s. It is
						now called De Tuynhuis and houses the offices of the State President.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0057">
					<orgName type="main">Griqua</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Southern African group of Khoekhoe and European descent,
						though their ancestry also includes the San and Bantu peoples. They
						developed group identity in the eighteenth century, and established several
						influential states on the borders of the Cape Colony in the nineteenth
						century. European colonialism deprived them of most of their territory by
						the 1880s (Schweitzer 2015:15, 18-19).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0070">
					<orgName type="main">Henry Monteith &amp; Co.</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Textiles manufacturer, who owned the Blantyre cotton
						works where Livingstone began employment in 1823.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0058">
					<orgName type="main">Hottentot</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Term referring to the Khoekhoe people of southern Africa
						(primarily resident in Namibia and South Africa), who were historically
						pastoralist in lifestyle. The term dates from the seventeenth century and is
						now considered pejorative. It reportedly originates in a Dutch word for
						"stutter" or "stammer," "Huttentut," applied to the group on account of the
						clicking sounds in the Khoekhoe language. In the nineteenth century,
						Khoekhoe physicality and behaviours were the subject of much evolutionary
						speculation and racial science (Heath 2010c:573, Nave 2010a:650).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0059">
					<orgName type="main">Independent</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Another term for Congregationalism, a Protestant movement
						that advocates the independence of individual congregations and their right
						to self-government, while rejecting higher ecclesiastical structures.
						Livingstone left the Church of Scotland and joined the local
						Congregationalist church in the early 1830s. The London Missionary Society
						was predominantly a Congregationalist organisation.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0060">
					<orgName type="main">Jesuits</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Members of the Society of Jesus, a Roman Catholic order
						founded by Ignatius of Loyola in 1540. The Society is notable for its
						defence of Catholicism during the Counter-Reformation, and for its
						commitment to education and missionary activity. It first sent missionaries
						to Africa in the 1550s and eventually commissioned more foreign mission
						agents than any other order (Newitt 2005:139, Augustyn et al. 2019d).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0042">
					<orgName type="main">Kaffir</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Caffre by Livingstone. Term referring to the
						AmaXhosa of southern Africa. During the early period of European
						colonisation, it was applied to all Bantu-speaking Africans but in the
						nineteenth century it came to have its more specific application to the
						AmaXhosa. The term, however, continued to be used to generalise about Bantu
						peoples and is now considered derogatory. It has its origin in the Arabic
						word "kafir," which means "unbeliever" (Mills 1996:615).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0061">
					<orgName type="main">Knights of Malta</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Christian military order (also known as the Knights of
						St. John or the Knights Hospitaller), which originated in the twelfth
						century to defend the Holy Land and provide health care to Christian
						pilgrims. Following the Muslim reconquest of Jerusalem in 1187, they settled
						on the island of Rhodes where they battled with the Ottoman Empire. Defeated
						in 1522, they relocated to Malta where they held a sovereign territory until
						conquered by Napoleon Bonaparte in 1798 (Greene 2009:313).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0090">
					<orgName type="main">Korana</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Corannas by Livingstone. One of the Oorlam groups
						that emerged in the late eighteenth century around the Cape Colony’s
						northern frontier. Oorlam communities were mixed race, with a combination of
						Khoesan, Sotho-Tswana, slave, and European descent. The Korana were largely
						Khoekhoe and Sotho-Tswana in ancestry (McDonald 2015, Legassick
						2010:48).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0062">
					<orgName type="main">Light Brigade</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">British cavalry brigade led by James Thomas Brudenell
						(Seventh Earl of Cardigan), which charged a well-defended Russian stronghold
						in the Battle of Balaklava (25th October 1854) during the Crimean War. The
						failed assault, in which the cavalry was decimated, was famously
						memorialised in Alfred, Lord Tennyson's poem, "The Charge of the Light
						Brigade" (Bunting 2017).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0063">
					<orgName type="main">Locrians</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Inhabitants of Locris, a central region of Ancient Greece
						that was divided in two by the states of Phocis and Doris. The Locrians
						established a colony called Locri in Italy in 700BCE, where they developed
						the first written legal system in the Greek world, known as the "Locrian
						Code" (Buckler 2012:854, Sacks 1996:132).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0064">
					<orgName type="main">London Missionary Society (LMS)</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Evangelical missionary society formed in England in 1795,
						primarily serving missions in Africa and the South Pacific. Although
						established on a non-denominational basis, it was increasingly regarded as a
						Congregationalist organisation. Livingstone was commissioned by the Society
						in 1840 and served as one of its missionaries until 1857 (Porter
						2004:49-50).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0065">
					<orgName type="main">Lords of the Isles</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Scottish title, dating to the Middle Ages, used by the
						rulers of the islands off Scotland's west coast and parts of the western
						mainland. These lords had considerable power and autonomy until the late
						fifteenth century, when the title was appropriated to the Scottish monarchy
						by King James IV. By describing Toka-Leya chiefs near Victoria Falls,
						deposed by Sebitwane, as "Lords of the Isles," Livingstone characterises
						them as despotic rulers who had been domesticated by a higher authority
						(Panton 2011:303).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0066">
					<orgName type="main">Madras Army</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Army of the Madras Presidency, formed by the East India
						Company in the mid-eighteenth century. It was transferred to the British
						Crown in 1858 following the Indian Rebellion, along with the Bengal and
						Bombay Armies and the Company's other possessions (Schmidt 2015:60, Raugh
						2004:216).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0067">
					<orgName type="main">Mansion House, London.</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Official residence of the Lord Mayor of London, built in
						the mid-eighteenth century at Bank Junction.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0068">
					<orgName type="main">Mantatees</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">General term applied to Sotho-speaking migrants and
						labourers in the nineteenth century. It was originally used to denote the
						BaTlokwa, deriving from a distortion of the name of their leader,
						Mmanthatisi (Sekonyela's mother). It came, however, to be applied less
						precisely to wandering groups in the regions around the Vaal and Orange
						rivers and to migrant workers seeking employment by Europeans (Etherington
						2001:148, Sheldon 2012:233, Beinart 2003:59).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0069">
					<orgName type="main">Mechanics' Institute, Cape Town</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">The Mechanics' Institutes movement originated in the
						early nineteenth century as a means of educating the adult labouring classes
						in mathematics, sciences, and the arts. The Cape Town institute was founded
						in 1828, but closed a year later. It was re-established in 1853 and remained
						active until the 1870s (Dubow 2006:49n124).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0071">
					<orgName type="main">Mephato (pl.) or mophato (sing.)</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Called mepato (pl.) and mopato (sing.) by Livingstone.
						Male "age-sets" or "regiments" among the BaTswana that operated as military
						and political units. Young men who passed through initiation together became
						life-long members of the same mophato (Morton 2012a:385-86).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0072">
					<orgName type="main">Moravians</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Protestant denomination, founded in the eighteenth
						century. In the 1720s, a remnant of the almost extinct Bohemian Brethren
						movement left their home in Moravia (in present-day Czech Republic) and
						established a community in Germany on the estate of Nikolaus Ludwig, Count
						von Zinzendorf. The settlement, Herrnhut, became the centre of a pietistic
						movement that had considerable influence on mainline Protestantism,
						particularly Lutheranism. The Moravians are highly service oriented, and
						began commissioning missionaries around the globe in the 1730s (Livingstone
						2013:380).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0073">
					<orgName type="main">Niger Expedition</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">British expedition to west Africa (1841-43), which sought
						to open trade and establish treaties along the Niger. It was supported by
						the Society for the Extinction of the Slave Trade and for the Civilization
						of Africa, founded in 1839 by Sir Thomas Fowell Buxton. Buxton's aim was to
						combat the slave trade by introducing Christianity, civilisation, and
						"legitimate commerce," ideas that Livingstone would develop in Missionary
						Travels. The expedition ended in failure, with a large number of the party
						dying of fever (Blouet 2010).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0075">
					<orgName type="main">Presbyterian</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Protestant denominations that follow the Presbyterian
						form of ecclesiastical structure, in which the church is represented and
						governed by bodies of elected lay elders and ministers. Presbyterianism is
						historically rooted in the sixteenth-century Reformation and Calvinist
						theology.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0076">
					<orgName type="main">Quakers</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Society of Friends. Christian group
						founded in the mid-seventeenth century, which emphasises the leading of the
						Holy Spirit and rejects the need for ordained clergy. In calling the BaYeyi
						the "Quakers of Africa," Livingstone alludes to the Friends' advocacy of
						non-violence and pacifism.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0077">
					<orgName type="main">Resurrectionist</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Another term for the "body snatchers" of the eighteenth
						and nineteenth centuries, who robbed graves and mortuaries in order to
						supply corpses to the medical profession for dissection.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0078">
					<orgName type="main">Rhenish</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Person from the historical Rhine Province of Prussia (the
						present-day Rhineland region of western Germany).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0079">
					<orgName type="main">Royal Geographical Society (RGS)</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Learned society of geographers, founded in 1830 in London
						with the aim of advancing geographical knowledge and promoting exploration.
						The society awarded Livingstone the annual Founder's medal in 1855 and
						became one of his sponsoring organisations.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0043">
					<orgName type="main">Royal Observatory, Cape of Good Hope</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Observatory founded in 1820. It is South Africa's oldest
						scientific establishment and was the southern hemisphere's first major
						observatory.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0074">
					<orgName type="main">Society for the Promotion of Permanent and Universal
						Peace</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Peace Society. Peace association,
						founded in 1816 by Quakers and other Christian pacifists in the wake of the
						Napoleonic Wars. The Society adopted an anti-war stance, opposing even
						defensive conflicts, and established local branches across Britain (Laity
						2001:13-14).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0080">
					<orgName type="main">South Sea Islanders</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Collective term used in the eighteenth and nineteenth
						centuries to refer to the peoples of the Polynesian islands in the
						east-central Pacific.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0081">
					<orgName type="main">St Mary Woolnoth</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Anglican church on the corner of King William Street and
						Lombard Street, London, built by Nicholas Hawksmoor between 1716 and
						1727.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0082">
					<orgName type="main">Thames steamers</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Paddle steamboats used as a means of public transport in
						nineteenth-century London, particularly in the 1830s before the ascendancy
						of the railway. At its peak, there were fifteen companies operating steamers
						on the Thames (Dumpleton 2002:40).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0083">
					<orgName type="main">Thracians</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Inhabitants of the area between the Danube River and
						Aegean Sea, known to the Ancient Greeks as Thrace. The region came under
						Persian authority in the 6th century BCE, and became a province of Rome in
						46 CE. Today, the territory in the south-east Balkans that historically
						constituted Thrace is divided between Turkey, Greece, and Bulgaria (Augustyn
						et al. 2019f).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0084">
					<orgName type="main">Troughton and Simms</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Scientific instrument makers, established as a
						partnership between Edward Troughton (1753–1835) and William Simms
						(1793–1860). The business provided equipment for navigation and surveying,
						as well as large-scale astronomical apparatus. They were the official
						suppliers of the East India Company, and constructed and repaired
						instruments for the Royal Greenwich Observatory (McConnell 2004,
						2007).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0085">
					<orgName type="main">United Presbyterian Church</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Presbyterian denomination in Scotland, created in 1847 by
						the unification of the United Secession Church and the Relief Church. In
						1900, the United Presbyterian Church merged with the Free Church of Scotland
						to form the United Free Church of Scotland, which in turn rejoined the
						Church of Scotland in 1929 (Lyall 2016:123).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0086">
					<orgName type="main">University of Coimbra</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">One of Europe's ancient universities and the oldest in
						Portugal. It was established in Lisbon in 1290, but moved permanently to
						Coimbra in the mid-sixteenth century.</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0087">
					<orgName type="main">Wesleyans</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Movements and denominations with origins in the theology
						of John Wesley, the eighteenth-century cleric and evangelist. Wesleyanism
						began as a reform and revival movement within the Church of England, but
						became independent by 1795. It is often associated with Arminianism and an
						emphasis on the sanctification of the believer through the Holy Spirit. The
						Wesleyan Methodist Missionary Society was formed in 1818 to support
						initiatives already under way across the globe. Wesleyan missionary work
						began in west Africa in 1811 and in South Africa in 1814 (Pritchard
						2013:25-27).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0088">
					<orgName type="main">Westminster</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Area in London in which the United Kingdom's Houses of
						Parliament and other institutions of government are located. Westminster
						Hall in the Palace of Westminster was home to Britain's High Courts (Court
						of the Exchequer, Court of King's Bench, and Court of Common Pleas) until
						the Royal Courts of Justice were opened in the Strand in 1882 (Rivlin
						2015:26-27).</note>
				</org>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<org xml:id="org0089">
					<orgName type="main">Zambesians</orgName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone's collective term for groups resident in the
						Zambezi valley.</note>
				</org>

			</listOrg>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
