<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Livingstone Online: Annotated Region List</title>
				<author>Adrian S. Wisnicki</author>
				<author>Megan Ward</author>
				<author>Justin D. Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2019</date>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">(c)
						Livingstone Online. <ref
							target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
							Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License</ref>.</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>A Livingstone Online project.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<listPlace>

				<!-- Current higest number = region0052 -->

				<place xml:id="region0017" type="region">
					<!-- The Cape -->
					<placeName type="main">Cape of Good Hope</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also the Cape. The southern tip of Africa. Traditionally,
						the dividing point between the Atlantic and Indian Oceans.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0001" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Chunya district of Mbeya region[?]</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Area in the western part of present-day Tanzania that is
						home to the Bungu people and that lies just to the south-east of Lake
						Rukwa.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0002" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Dodoma[?]</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in the central part of present-day Tanzania that
						is home to the Gogo people.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0003" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Iringa[?]</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in the south-central part of present-day Tanzania
						that is home to the Bena people.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0004" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Karagwe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in present-day northern Tanzania lying just to the
						west of Lake Victoria and to the east of Rwanda that served as the site of a
						major kingdom in the nineteenth century.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0005" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Katanga</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in the southern part of present-day Democratic
						Republic of the Congo. During the period in question, ruled by Msiri and
						known for its underground mines and for resources such as copper, gold, and
						malachite.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0006" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Kingdom of Tirhaka</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Tirhaka (also Taharqa, Taharka, or Tirhakah) ruled over
						Egypt and Kush from 690 to 664, B.C.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0007" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Legaland</placeName>
					<!-- Metamba -->
					<note type="editorial">Also called Metamba by Livingstone. Region in the eastern
						part of present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo that is home to the
						Lega people and that encompasses the valleys of the middle and upper Elila
						and the upper Ulindi rivers.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0009" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Linyanti</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in the northern part of present-day Botswana, just
						south of the Zambezi River, which became one of the primary settlements of
						the Makololo state.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0010" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Lubaland</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Savannah region in the central part of present-day
						Democratic Republic of the Congo that served as the site of the Luba
						kingdom, a major African empire in the nineteenth century.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0011" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Lunda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Significant central African kingdom that, in the
						nineteenth century, encompassed what are now the southern part of the
						Democratic Republic of the Congo, north-eastern Angola, and north-western
						Zambia.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0012" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Maasailand</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region in east Africa that is home to the Maasi people
						and stretches from northern Tanzania to southern Kenya.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0013" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Maniema</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also Manyema or Mayuema. Region in the eastern part of
						present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo roughly bordering the Lomami
						River to the west, Katanga to the south, Lakes Tanganyika and Kivu to the
						east, and the territory of Stanley Falls to the north.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0014" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Mbeya[?]</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Usango in Livingstone's time. Region in the
						western part of present-day Tanzania that is home to the Sangu people and
						that lies just to the east and south-east of Lake Rukwa.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0015" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Midian</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Ancient civilization in the northwest Arabian
						peninsula.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="region0016" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Shire highlands</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Plateau east of the Shire River in the southern part of
						present-day Malawi.</note>
				</place>


				<!-- Missionary Travels Glossary List -->

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0018" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Barotseland</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Barotse country by Livingstone. Region in
						present-day western Zambia to the west of the Kafue River, and homeland of
						the Lozi people. Historically, it covered a larger area including Zambia's
						current Western, North-western, and Southern Provinces (Minahan
						2002:1115).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0019" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Bashan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Country appearing in the Old Testament, which formed part
						of ancient Palestine. The Israelites' victory over Og, the King of Bashan,
						is recorded in Numbers 21:33-36. See also Deuteronomy 3:1-11, which recounts
						the events in more detail and describes Og's enormous iron decorated bed,
						held by the Ammonites, as a relic of his kingdom.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0020" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Bechuanaland</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Bechuana country by Livingstone. Region in
						southern Africa, and homeland of the BaTswana groups. It was annexed by
						Britain in 1885, with the area south of the Molopo River becoming a crown
						colony and the northern area becoming the Bechuanaland Protectorate. It
						became independent Botswana in 1966 (Curran 2003:52).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0021" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Benguela</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region on the west coast of Angola. Its capital city,
						also named Benguela, was founded in 1617 by the Portuguese and became a
						major port for the trade and transportation of slaves (James
						2011:40).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0022" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Boróro</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone uses the term to mean the country of the
						"Baroro," or the Sangu people (also historically known as the Rori). Their
						historic homelands are in the Mbeya region, north of Lake Malawi in
						south-western Tanganyika (Olson 1996:509).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0023" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Canaan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Name used in the Old Testament and other sources for
						ancient Palestine. The Israelites' occupation of Canaan, which was for them
						the "promised land," in the second millennium BC is described in the book of
						Joshua.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0024" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Cape Colony</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">British colony in the south and west of what is now South
						Africa. It began as a Dutch port and settlement in 1652, but was occupied by
						the British in 1795. It was briefly returned to the Dutch in 1803 before
						becoming a British possession in 1814. With the Union of South Africa in
						1910, it became the Cape Province (or the Province of the Cape of Good Hope)
						(Olson 1991:115).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0025" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Cassange valley</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Upper valley of the Kwango (or Cuango) River, in
						north-central Angola.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0026" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Central African basin</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called central basin and central valley by Livingstone.
						Roderick Murchison, the President of the Royal Geographical Society, had
						proposed in 1852 that the physical structure of southern Africa was an
						elevated "central trough or basin" encircled by a highland ridge. Although
						based on limited information and mistaken geological premises, his
						theoretical speculation proved largely correct. Livingstone came to the same
						view of Africa's continental structure during his cross-continental
						expedition, and considered his observations to provide empirical
						confirmation of Murchison's proposition (Stafford 1988:8, 17; Murchison
						1852:cxxii; Livingstone 1857aa:475, 500; Schapera 1963,2:314).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0027" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Crimea</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Peninsula located between the Black Sea and the Sea of
						Azov. It was the site of the Crimean War (1853-56), in which Russia was
						defeated by the combined forces of Britain, France, and the Ottomans. The
						conflict was the result of power struggles in the Middle East, and was
						precipitated by a dispute between the Ottomans and the Russians over the
						protection of Orthodox Christians in the Ottoman Empire. It was a badly
						organised campaign, with infection and unsanitary conditions responsible for
						a large proportion of lives lost (Kohn 2013:133).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0028" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Dande</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Coastal region of north-western Angola, in present-day
						Bengo Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0029" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Darfur</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region of present-day western Sudan, predominantly
						consisting of extensive plains.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0030" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Eastern Province</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Eastern region of the Cape Colony. The colony's eastern
						frontier and the AmaXhosa territories beyond, known in the nineteenth
						century as "Kaffraria" or "Kaffreland," were the site of the century-long
						series of disputes between the AmaXhosa and the British known as the Cape
						Frontier Wars (1779–1879). See also Kaffraria.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0031" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Hebrides</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Group of islands off the west coast of Scotland. Those to
						the west of the Minch and Little Minch channels are known as the Outer
						Hebrides, while those to the east are known as the Inner Hebrides.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0032" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Kaffraria</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Caffraria and Caffreland by Livingstone. Region in
						the Eastern Cape of present-day South Africa, and historically homeland of
						the AmaXhosa people. It was the site of the century-long series of disputes
						between the AmaXhosa and the British, known as the Cape Frontier Wars
						(1779–1879). The region was annexed in 1835 as Queen Adelaide Province, but
						this was annulled within the year. It was annexed again in 1847 as British
						Kaffraria and was integrated into the Cape Colony in 1865 (Augustyn et al.
						2017c).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0033" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Kashmir</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">North-western region of the Indian subcontinent. In 1846,
						following the first Anglo-Sikh War, Kashmir became a princely state under
						British indirect rule.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0034" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Katonga</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Area on the Zambezi River in present-day Zambia's Western
						Province, bordering Namibia's Caprivi Strip. According to Livingstone, it
						was twenty-five miles west of where Sesheke was then located (Livingstone
						1857aa:684).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0035" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Lanarkshire</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Historical county in south-central Scotland, covering the
						area of present-day North Lanarkshire, South Lanarkshire, the City of
						Glasgow, and East Dumbartonshire.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0036" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Luanda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Loanda and Loando by Livingstone. Region in
						western Angola, which is today one of the country's eighteen
						provinces.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0037" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Luba</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Major central African state, which existed in the region
						between the Lomami and Lualaba rivers in what is now southern Democratic
						Republic of the Congo. Luba had become a "dynastic kingdom" by 1700, and
						expanded its sway throughout the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries as far
						east as Lake Tanganyika, as far south as Lake Mweru, and as far north as
						Kasuland and Songyeland (Macola 2016b:1320-21).</note>
				</place>
				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0038" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Lunda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Lui, Loi, and Londa by Livingstone.
						Significant central African commonwealth of autonomous but interlinking
						states, encompassing what is now southern Democratic Republic of the Congo,
						north-eastern Angola, and north-western Zambia. At the heart of the
						commonwealth was the central Lunda state (known as the Ruund), situated
						between the Kasai and Lubilash rivers. Other Lunda polities traced their
						origin to the Ruund and derived their status from its royal title. The
						commonwealth stretched west to Kasanje's kingdom on the Kwango (or Cuango)
						River, east to Kazembe's kingdom in the Luapula valley, and south to a
						number of smaller states (Macola 2016a:34, 2016b:1320-22).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0039" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Luvale</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lobale by Livingstone. Region encompassing parts
						of present-day north-western Zambia and south-eastern Angola, that was
						historically homeland of the Luvale people (Schapera 1963,1:38n2; Augustyn
						et al. 2017d).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0040" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Makololo country</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Territory occupied by the Makololo in the 1830s and 40s,
						predominantly in the Bulozi Plain of present-day Zambia's Western Province.
						Before the Lozi uprising of 1864, the Makololo empire extended from the
						northern point of the plain as far south as the Linyanti swamps and Victoria
						Falls (Kalusa 2009:62).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0041" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Mango</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Manga by Livingstone. Area around the
						confluence of the Lungwebungu and Zambezi rivers, in the northern part of
						present-day Zambia's Western Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0042" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Manica</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also called Manoa and Manwa by Livingstone. Region
						historically occupied by the Shona-speaking Manyika people, in the eastern
						part of present-day Zimbabwe (Manicaland Province) and the bordering area of
						Mozambique (Manica District). Its gold fields and gold trade date to at
						least the seventeenth century (Augustyn et al. 2017e; Schapera
						1963,2:426n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0043" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Mashonaland</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Mashona hills by Livingstone. Historic homelands
						of the Shona people, in present-day north-eastern Zimbabwe.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0044" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Mokwankwa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Area in eastern Angola, in the vicinity of present-day
						Cazombo in Moxico Province (Schapera 1963,1:69n1; Livingstone 1857aa:306-07,
						685).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0045" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Natal</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">British colony in what is now KwaZulu-Natal, South
						Africa. The region, which had been established as an independent Boer
						Republic in 1839, was annexed by Britain in 1843. In 1910, it was integrated
						into the newly formed Union of South Africa as Natal Province (Augustyn et
						al. 2007).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0046" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Ophir</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Wealthy region described in the Old Testament, which
						traded with King Solomon in gold and opulent goods (see 1 Kings 9:28, 10:11,
						and 2 Chronicles 8:18). It has been identified variously with sites in the
						Arabian Peninsula, India, and east Africa.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0047" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Orange Free State</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Boer Republic between the Orange and Vaal rivers, in what
						is now east-central South Africa. The region was initially annexed by
						Britain as the Orange River Sovereignty in 1848, but was granted status as
						an independent Boer Republic in 1854. In the Second Anglo-Boer War
						(1899-1902), it was defeated by the British and made into the Orange River
						Colony. In 1910, it was integrated into the newly formed Union of South
						Africa as the Orange Free State Province (Olson 1991:473).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0048" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Polynesia</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Known historically as the South Sea Islands. Group of
						over 1000 islands in the east-central Pacific Ocean.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0049" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Pungo Andongo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Region of north-western Angola, and the site of a
						seventeenth-century Portuguese fort, about fifty miles west of Malanje in
						present-day Malanje Province. Before it was conquered by the Portuguese in
						1671 and established as a military enclave, it was a stronghold of the
						Ndongo Kingdom (Pungo-a-Ndongo). Pungo Andongo is also the site of a
						celebrated formation of giant monoliths (Thompson 2017:51, Wheeler and
						Pélissier 1971:39).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0052" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Salisbury Plains</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Chalk plateau in Wiltshire, south-west England, best
						known for its archaelogical sites and prehistoric monuments including
						Stonehenge.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0050" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">South African Republic</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as the Transvaal. Boer Republic between the
						Vaal and Limpopo rivers, in what is now north-eastern South Africa. The
						state was established with the Sand River Convention of 1852, which conceded
						the independence of the Boer communities north of the Vaal River. It was
						annexed in 1877 as the British Transvaal Territory, but this was revoked as
						a result of the Boers' victory in the First Anglo-Boer War (1880-81).
						Defeated by the British in the Second Anglo-Boer War (1899-1902), it became
						the Crown Colony of the Transvaal. In 1910, it was integrated into the newly
						formed Union of South Africa as the Transvaal Province (Laband 2009b:264-65,
						Augustyn et al. 2009).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="region0051" type="region">
					<placeName type="main">Tweeddale</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">District in the central Scottish Borders.</note>
				</place>





			</listPlace>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
