<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://livingstoneonline.github.io/LEAP-ODD/leap.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Livingstone Online: Annotated Settlement List</title>
				<author>Adrian S. Wisnicki</author>
				<author>Megan Ward</author>
				<author>Justin D. Livingstone</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Livingstone Online</authority>
				<publisher>University of Maryland Libraries</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD, USA</pubPlace>
				<date>2019</date>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">(c)
						Livingstone Online. <ref
							target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
							Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License</ref>.</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>A Livingstone Online project.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<listPlace>

				<!-- Current higest number = sett0095 -->

				<place xml:id="sett0001" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Bagamoyo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">East African costal town in present-day Tanzania that
						served as one of the most important trading ports of the nineteenth
						century.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0002" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Bambarre</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also Bambare, Kabambare, and Kabambarre. Village in
						Maniema, an eastern region in present-day Democratic Republic of the Congo.
						Livingstone stayed there 21 September-1 November 1869, 19-26 December 1869,
						and 22 July 1870-16 February 1871, and wrote most of the 1870 Field Diary
						there.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0003" type="settlement">
					<placeName type="main">Delphi</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City in Greece known for its oracle in ancient
						times.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0004" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Kanyembo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">In present-day northern Zambia. The capital of Cazembe
						(Kazembe VIII), chief of the Lunda.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0005" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Kasongo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in Maniema, an eastern region in present-day
						Democratic Republic of the Congo, lying to the east of the Lualaba River.
						One of the key nineteenth-century outposts for Zanzibari traders</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0016" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Kilwa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Collective name for Kilwa Kisiwani, Kilwa Kivinje, and
						Kilwa Masoko, all in present-day Tanzania. One of the most important centers
						for the slave trade on the east coast of Africa in the nineteenth
						century.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0006" type="settlement_village">
					<!-- Entry slightly adapted by JL, to include dates. JL -->
					<placeName type="main">Kolobeng</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone's third mission station, near Gaborone in
						present-day Botswana. Livingstone, Sechele, and the BaKwena settled here in
						1847 following serious water shortage at Chonuane. From Kolobeng,
						Livingstone journeyed to Lake Ngami (1849), and laid plans to make contact
						with Sebitwane (1851) and explore the Zambezi. A group of Transvaal Boers
						ransacked the Kolobeng mission in 1852 as part of an attack on
						Sechele.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0007" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Kuruman</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">London Missionary Society (LMS) mission to the BaTlhaping
						(a SeTswana speaking group) in the Northern Cape of present-day South
						Africa. Owed its origins to the work of missionary James Read and was
						developed in the 1820s by Robert and Mary Moffat, later Livingstone's
						parents-in-law. When Livingstone arrived, Kuruman was the northernmost of
						the LMS's mission stations in southern Africa and was considered to be a
						prototype of a successful mission station.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0008" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Lebadea</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in ancient Greece (Livadeia in modern
						Greece).</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0017" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Mamohela</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village about 7 days northwest of Bambarre, according to
						Livingstone.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0009" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Meroe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Ancient city on the east bank of the Nile.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0010" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Nashik</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City in India.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0011" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Nineveh</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Ancient city of Upper Mesopotamia, located in modern-day
						Iraq.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0012" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Nyangwe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village and marketplace on the banks of the Lualaba River
						in Maniema, an eastern region in present-day Democratic Republic of the
						Congo. Livingstone stayed there 23 March-20 July 1871 and wrote most of the
						1871 Field Diary there.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0013" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Sais</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Ancient Egyptian town in the western Nile delta.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0014" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Ujiji</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village on the eastern shore of Lake Tanganyika. In the
						nineteenth century, Ujiji was one of the major trading depots in the
						Arab-African trading network of east Africa.</note>
				</place>

				<place xml:id="sett0015" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Unyanyembe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in the central part of present-day Tanzania that, in
						the nineteenth century, served as one of the major depots on the trade
						routes that ran between the east coast of Africa and the interior.</note>
				</place>



				<!-- Missionary Travels Glossary List -->

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0018" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Aden</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Port in Yemen, under British governance from 1839–1967.
						It occupied a strategic position between Africa and the Middle East, and
						played an important role in Britain's imperial trade network.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0019" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Ambaca</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Early Portuguese trading centre in north-western Angola.
						From the seventeenth century it was one of the most important towns in the
						slave trade, occupying a key location on the caravan route between the
						Angolan interior and Luanda. It is estimated that in 1845, over half of the
						district's population of around 73,000 individuals were slaves (Vansina
						2005:1-2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0020" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Ambriz</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Slave port in Angola, about seventy miles north of
						Luanda. It had long been a point of departure for slaves headed to the
						Americas, but was only occupied by the Portuguese in 1855. In his journals,
						Livingstone describes it as a "notorious nest of slave-dealers" (Birmingham
						2015:35; Schapera 1963,1:156n2, 189)</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0021" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Babel</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City in the land of "Shinar" described in the Old
						Testament. According to the book of Genesis, the inhabitants set out to
						construct an enormous tower "to make a name for [them]selves," before God
						intervened by confounding the language of the people and scattering them
						"over the face of the whole earth" (Genesis 11:1–9).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0022" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Bango</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in north-western Angola, in the vicinity of
						Golungo Alto in present-day Cuanza Norte Province. It was probably a Mbundu
						settlement.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0023" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Bannockburn</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Historic country in central Scotland and the location of
						the Battle of Bannockburn (1314) in which Robert the Bruce defeated the
						English army under Edward II. See also Robert I (Robert the Bruce).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0024" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Benguela</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City on the west coast of Angola. It was founded in 1617
						by the Portuguese and became a major port for the trade and transportation
						of slaves (James 2011:40).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0025" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Blantyre</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Industrial and mining town about eight miles south-east
						of Glasgow in South Lanarkshire, Scotland, and the birthplace of David
						Livingstone.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0026" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Bloemfontein</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City in present-day South Africa's Free State. It was the
						capital city of the Orange Free State (1854–1902), one of the independent
						Boer Republics.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0027" type="settlement_farm">
					<placeName type="main">Boomplaats</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Site of the battle of Boomplaats, about fifty miles south
						of Bloemfontein in present-day South Africa's Free State. Following the
						annexation of the Orange River Sovereignty, a contingent of Boers under
						Andries Pretorius rebelled and installed itself at Boomplaats farm. They
						were defeated by the British, led by Sir Harry Smith, on 29th August 1848
						(Raugh 2004:56).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0028" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Bothithong</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Motito by Livingstone. Village in the
						north-eastern part of present-day South Africa's Northern Cape, where the
						Société des Missions Évangélique de Paris (Paris Evangelical Missionary
						Society) established its first mission station in 1833 (Newcomb 1855:47-48,
						Mosimann-Barbier 2014:21).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0029" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Bothwell</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in South Lanarkshire, Scotland. Bothwell Bridge,
						over the River Clyde, was the site of the defeat of the Presbyterian
						Covenanters in 1679 by the Royalists under the Duke of Monmouth. The area is
						also home to the medieval Bothwell Castle, where repeated battles were
						fought during the Scottish Wars of Independence in the late thirteenth and
						early fourteenth centuries (Chisholm 1910-11,4:304; Hull 2008:82).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0030" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Cabango</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Lunda village in north-eastern Angola, around forty-five
						miles east of Saurimo in present-day Lunda Sul Province (Schapera
						1963,2:242n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0031" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Cabinda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Portuguese station in north-western Angola, in
						present-day Cuanza Norte Province. According to Livingstone's journal, it
						was four and a half hours east of Golungo Alto on the road to Ambaca
						(Schapera 1963,1:180).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0032" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Caconda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in west-central Angola, in the northern part of
						present-day Huila Province and about eighty miles south-west of
						Huambo.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0033" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Cahenda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Site of a former mission station in north-western Angola,
						just north of Ambaca. According to the nineteenth-century traveller,
						Francisco Travassos Valdez, it was established in 1651 by Anontio de
						Montecuculi, an Italian member of the Order of Friars Minor Capuchin (Valdez
						1861:301).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0034" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Cambambe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in north-western Angola on the Cuanza River, in the
						southern part of present-day Cuanza Norte Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0035" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Cambondo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Clearing near Golungo Alto in north-western Angola, in
						present-day Cuanza Norte Province. It is also called Cambombe in
						Livingstone's journals (Schapera 1963,1:163, 179).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0036" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Cambuslang</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in South Lanarkshire and a suburb of Glasgow, about
						five miles south-east of the city centre.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0037" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Candumba</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in north-western Angola, in present-day Malanje
						Province. According to Livingstone, it was fifteen miles east of Pungo
						Andongo and 300 yards north of the Cuanza River (Livingstone
						1857aa:686)</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0038" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Cape Town</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City on the south coast of present-day South Africa's
						Western Cape. In Livingstone's day, it was the capital of the Cape Colony.
						See also Cape Colony.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0039" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Cassange</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Portuguese settlement in north-central Angola, in
						present-day Lunda Norte Province. It was about 300 miles east of Luanda, and
						was described by Livingstone as "the farthest inland station of the
						Portuguese in Western Africa" (Livingstone 1857aa:368, 375).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0040" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Cazengo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">District just south of Golungo Alto in north-western
						Angola, in present-day Cuanza-Norte Province. In the mid-nineteenth century
						it became an important centre in Angola's developing coffee industry.
						Livingstone provides census information of 1854 for Cazengo in his journal
						(Birmingham 1999:97; Schapera 1963,1:178)</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0041" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Chennai</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Known historically as Madras. City in south-eastern
						India, on the Bay of Bengal coast. During the period of East India Company
						rule and the British Raj, it was the administrative capital of southern
						India.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0042" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Chonuane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone's second mission station, about fifteen miles
						south of present-day Gaborone in south-eastern Botswana. Livingstone
						established the mission in 1846 to develop his work among the BaKwena
						people. He had also quarrelled with his colleague Roger Edwards at Mabotsa,
						their shared station. Chonuane was poorly resourced with water and so the
						Livingstones and the BaKwena moved to Kolobeng in the following year (Ross
						2002:51, 55; Schapera 1960a:74n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0043" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Coimbra</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City on the Mondego River in western Portugal.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0044" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Culloden</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Site of the Battle of Culloden (16th April, 1746) in
						Inverness-shire, Scotland. The battle was the last stand in the Jacobite
						rebellion (1745-46), which sought to restore the House of Stuart to the
						throne of Great Britain. See also Stuart, Charles Edward.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0045" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Dambarari</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in the vicinity of present-day Jumbo (where the
						Jumbo mine was established in 1890), in northern Zimbabwe. According to
						Livingstone, it was also known as Bambala. In 1856, he identified it as a
						settlement with an active gold trade (Schapera 1963,2:431-32, 432n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0046" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Dikgatlhong</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Likatlong by Livingstone. BaTlhaping settlement
						near the confluence of the Harts and Vaal rivers in Griqualand West (in
						present-day South Africa's Northern Cape), where the London Missionary
						Society had a station. It originated as an outpost of the more established
						mission at Griqua Town (present-day Griekwastad) (Laband 2014:160; Mackenzie
						1871:90, 84-85).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0047" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Dithubaruba</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Litubaruba by Livingstone. BaKwena settlement
						several miles from Molepolole, north-west of present-day Gaborone in
						south-eastern Botswana. It was occupied briefly by the Makololo between 1824
						and 1826, and it served as the BaKwena capital from 1853 to 1863.
						Livingstone spent time there learning SeTswana after meeting Sechele in
						1842. According to Livingstone, it was also known as Lepelole, after nearby
						caves of that name (Morton, Ramsay, and Mgadla 2008:95).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0048" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Duque de Bragança</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Braganza by Livingstone. District and Portuguese
						station in north-western Angola, established in 1838. Now known as
						Calandula, it is about forty miles north-west of Malanje in present-day
						Malanje Province (Corrado 2008:10).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0049" type="settlement_castle">
					<placeName type="main">Eglinton Castle</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Site of the Eglinton Tournament in Ayrshire, Scotland,
						held in August 1839. Organised and financed by the Earl of Eglinton,
						Archibald William Montgomerie, the tournament was a three-day historical
						recreation of a medieval joust consisting of fully armoured knights and
						guests attired in medieval garb. Attendees numbered in the thousands (Pionke
						2008:27).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0050" type="settlement_street">
					<placeName type="main">Fleet Street</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Commercial London street, particularly associated with
						journalism, but which was also a popular address for scientific instrument
						makers in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0051" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Gio</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Also known as N'Gio-N'Gio. Village in north-western
						Angola about fifteen miles south-east of Malanje, in present-day Malanje
						Province. Livingstone adopts the spelling Ngio in Missionary Travels, but
						uses Gio in his journals (Schapera 1963,1:133).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0052" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Golungo Alto</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in north-western Angola, in present-day Cuanza Norte
						Province, around 100 miles inland from Luanda. In his journal, Livingstone
						describes the wider Golungo Alto district as "about 67 ½ miles east &amp;
						west and about 30 north and south," and "not so populous as Ambaca and some
						other districts, nor so destitute of inhabitants as others." He also
						provides information on the district's organisation (Schapera
						1963,1:141).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0053" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Grahamstown</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">City in present-day South Africa's Eastern Cape. It began
						in 1812 as a defensive garrison on the frontier of AmaXhosa territory and by
						Livingstone's day had become the capital of the Cape Colony's Eastern
						Province (Vernal 2012:85-87).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0054" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Gravesend</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town in Kent, in south-east England.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0055" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Griekwastad</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Known historically as Griquatown. Town in present-day
						South Africa's Northern Cape. In Livingstone's day it was the capital of the
						Griqua settlement, Griqualand West, where the London Missionary Society had
						established a mission in 1804 (Waldman 2007:62, Moffat 1842:193).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0056" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Hadley Green</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">A park in Monken Hadley, an historic village north of
						London (which is now part of the London Borough of Barnet). Livingstone
						rented a property there in 1857 while writing Missionary Travels, prior to
						his departure on the Zambezi Expedition (Roberts 2008).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0057" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Hamilton</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Industrial town in South Lankarkshire, Scotland, about
						two miles from Livingstone's childhood home in Blantyre.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0058" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Icolo e Bengo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Icollo I Bengo by Livingstone. District and
						Portuguese station in north-western Angola, just east of Luanda in
						present-day Bengo Province. When Livingstone visited, its headquarters were
						on the shore of Lake Quilunda. In his journal, Livingstone offers more
						information about the district from a census taken in 1852-53 (Schapera
						1963,1:160, 176).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0059" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Interra</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in east-central Mozambique near the Cuacua River,
						about thirty miles inland from Quelimane (Shapera 1963,2:472n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0060" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">John o' Groats</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in Scotland, at the most northerly point of the
						mainland United Kingdom.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0061" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Kat River Settlement</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Settlement on the Kat River in the Cape Colony's eastern
						frontier (present-day South Africa's Eastern Cape). It was established in
						1829 as a defensive barrier between AmaXhosa territory and the Cape, and was
						populated with Khoekhoe and "mixed race" groups. It remained loyal to the
						British during the Sixth and Seventh Frontier Wars (1834-35 and 1846-47).
						However, fuelled by discriminatory Cape policy and land dispossession, the
						settlement unexpectedly refused to support the Cape Colony in 1851 during
						the Eighth Frontier War, with a considerable proportion joining the AmaXhosa
						forces. The rebellion was defeated and the settlement lands were allocated
						to European colonists (Kirk 1973:412, 425, 427).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0062" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Katima Mulilo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Katima-molelo by Livingstone. Town on the Zambezi
						River in present-day Namibia's Caprivi Strip, bordering Zambia's Western
						Province and directly across river from Sesheke.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0063" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Kilombo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Presumably a Mbundu village, in the vicinity of Golungo
						Alto in Angola's present-day Cuanza Norte Province. The word may be a
						descriptor for a settlement rather than a proper name. The Mbundu term,
						"kilombo," initially meant a "male initiation camp" and was later used to
						describe "a military encampment in constant readiness for attack." In his
						journal, Livingstone uses the spelling Quilombo (Jaede 2007:406; Schapera
						1963,1:183).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0064" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Langside</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">District in south Glasgow and the site of the Battle of
						Langside (13th May 1568) fought between Mary Queen of Scots and James
						Stuart, the Earl of Moray, her half brother. Following defeat, Mary fled to
						England where she was soon imprisoned by Elizabeth I (Wagner
						1999:180-81).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0065" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Lattakoo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Historical name for Dithakong in present-day South
						Africa's Northern Cape, where the London Missionary Society mission to the
						BaTlhaping people had initially been based. When the Moffats moved the
						mission south-west to Kuruman, it was known for some time as New Lattakoo or
						simply Lattakoo (Schapera 1961:13n2, 42n5; Weinberg 2015:147).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0066" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Letlhakane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Lotlakani and Lotlakane by Livingstone. Village in
						present-day east-central Botswana, about twenty miles south of the outskirts
						of Ntwetwe Pan.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0067" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Letloche</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Settlement about twenty miles north of the BaNgwato
						capital, Shoshong, in present-day east-central Botswana (Parsons
						1973:100n55).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0068" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Libebe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village on the Okavango River, in the western part of
						present-day Namibia's Caprivi strip (Schapera 1963,2:334n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0069" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Libonda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Libonta by Livingstone. Village on the Zambezi
						River in the north-western part of present-day Zambia's Western Province,
						near the Liuwa Plain National Park. In Livingstone's day it was the "last
						town of the Makololo" when travelling westward (Livingstone 1857aa:250;
						Schapera 1963,1:16n1).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0070" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Linangelo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Former town on the Zambezi River in the vicinity of
						Naliele, in the western part of present-day Zambia's Western Province. It is
						described by Livingstone as the "old town of Santuru" (the former Lozi King,
						Mulambwa Santulu) and also as "the town of one of Santuru's wives"
						(Livingstone 1857aa:685, Schapera 1960a:211). See also Mulambwa
						Santulu.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0071" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Linyanti</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town on the Chobe River, on the border between
						present-day Botswana and Namibia's Caprivi Strip. It was the capital of the
						Makololo kingdom during the period of Makololo ascendancy in the Zambezi
						Valley (c.1840–1864). Livingstone hoped his transcontinental expedition
						(1852-56), which took him from Linyanti to both Angola and Mozambique, would
						establish a trade route connecting central Africa with the west and east
						coasts (Kalusa 2009:55-56, Livingstone 1857aa:203).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0072" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Litofe</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Island and Makololo town on the Zambezi River north of
						Ngonye Falls, in present-day Zambia's Western Province. Livingstone
						describes it as one of Sebitwane's "stations" (Schapera 1960a:22, 199;
						Livingstone 1857aa:685).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0073" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Luanda</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Known historically as São Paulo de Luanda or St Paul de
						Loanda. Also called Loanda and Loando by Livingstone. Coastal city and
						capital of Angola, founded in the 1570s by the Portuguese. It developed into
						a major centre for the international export of slaves, mainly to Brazil
						(James 2011:152). </note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0074" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Mabotsa</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Livingstone's first mission station, in present-day South
						Africa's North West Province near the border with Botswana (about fifty
						miles south of Gaborone). The station was established with Roger Edwards in
						1844 and was over 200 miles north-east of Kuruman. According to Livingstone,
						permission to establish the mission was given by the BaKgatla chief,
						Mosiele. After quarrelling with Edwards Livingstone moved to a new site,
						Chonuane, in 1846 (Livingstone 1843; Ross 2002:45, 51; Schapera
						1960a:299n6).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0075" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Makolontwane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Melita by Livingstone. Former BaNgwaketse capital
						in the vicinity of Moshaneng, south-west of Gaborone in present-day Botswana
						(Morton 2014:31).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0076" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Malanje</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Malange by Livingstone. Village in north-western
						Angola. It is now the capital city of present-day Malanje Province and lies
						about fifteen miles from the Cuanza River.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0077" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Massangano</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">District and town in north-western Angola, in present-day
						Cuanze Norte Province. It is about fifty miles south-west of Golungo Alto,
						where the Lucala River enters the Cuanza River. The Portuguese fortress at
						Massangano was established by Paulo Dias de Novais, the first Governor of
						Portuguese Angola, and dates to the late sixteenth century (Newitt
						2010:18-19).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0078" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Mazaro</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Point at which the Muto channel (called Mutu by
						Livingstone) connects the Zambezi and Cuacua rivers in east-central
						Mozambique. It is in the vicinity of present-day Mopeia district and about
						seventy miles from the main mouth of the Zambezi River (Schapera
						1963,2:471n3, 471n5)</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0079" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Mitilone</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Reference uncertain. Presumably Ilha Mitaone or another
						port at the Chinde mouth of the Zambezi River, which is about twenty-five
						miles above the river's main mouth on the Mozambique coast (Schapera
						1963,2:470n3).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0080" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Naliele</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Important town on the Zambezi River, near the capital of
						present-day Zambia's Western Province, Mongu. Naliele had previously been a
						major Lozi centre, but when Livingstone visited in the early 1850s it was
						the Makololo's northern capital under the governorship of Mpepe (Kalusa
						2009:66, Rijpma 2015:52n45).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0081" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Nameta</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village on the Zambezi River, just north of Ngonye Falls
						in present-day Zambia's Western Province (Livingstone 1857aa:684).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0082" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Namissan</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Ngabisane by Livingstone. Settlement on the Boteti
						River in present-day north-central Botswana. It is south-west of Nxai Pan,
						and about 100 miles east of Lake Ngami. In his journals, Livingstone also
						uses the spelling Ñabisane (Schapera 1960a:69n4, 306).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0083" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Quelimane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Kilimane and Quilimane by Livingstone. Port city
						near the Mozambique coast. Originally an Islamic settlement, it became a
						Portuguese trading post in 1544 and by the mid-eighteenth century had
						developed into a colonial town. It was a significant entrepôt for the trade
						and export of slaves in the eighteenth and ninteenth centuries (Augustyn et
						al. 2017f, Newitt 1995:139).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0084" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Sanza</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Village in north-western Angola, about thirty-five miles
						east of Malanje in present-day Malanje Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0085" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Sena</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Senna by Livingstone. Town on the Zambezi River in
						central Mozambique, about 125 miles from Quelimane and about 130 miles from
						Tete. It had originally been an Islamic settlement, but was occupied by the
						Portuguese in the late sixteenth century. It was an important post on the
						major trade route from the east African coast (Newitt 1995:141).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0086" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Sesheke</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Town on the Zambezi River. When Livingstone visited, it
						was an important Makololo centre and was located in the south-western corner
						of present-day Zambia's Southern Province. The modern town of Sesheke is
						located today around sixty-five miles further north-west, in Western
						Province (Livingstone 1857aa:684).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0087" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Shokwane</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Called Shokuan and Shokuane by Livingstone. BaKwena
						settlement, just north-east of Molepolole in present-day south-eastern
						Botswana. The BaKwena were resident there when Livingstone first met Sechele
						in 1842 (Schapera 1974:49n2).</note>
				</place>
				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0088" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Smithfield</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Area in north-west London, known for its meat market
						which dates from the middle ages.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0089" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Sofala</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Historic harbour on the Mozambique coast, in present-day
						Sofala Province. It was southern Africa's oldest seaport, its use dating
						from the tenth century. Conquered by Pero de Anhaia in 1506, it became one
						of the first Portuguese possessions in east Africa. Sofala declined in
						importance during the nineteenth century and was eventually eclipsed when
						the port city, Beira, was founded in 1891 (Augustyn et al. 1998b, Newitt
						2005:74).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0090" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Tala Mungongo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">District and Portuguese station in north-central Angola,
						around sixty miles east of Malanje in present-day Malanje Province.</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0091" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Tete</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Port town on the Zambezi River in west-central
						Mozambique, about 130 miles from Sena and 250 miles from Quelimane.
						Originally an Islamic settlement, it was occupied by the Portuguese in the
						sixteenth century. It was a key destination on the trade route into central
						Africa from the east coast, and in the eighteenth century surpassed Sena as
						a centre of commerce (Newitt 1995:141, 144-45).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0092" type="settlement_city">
					<placeName type="main">Timbuktu</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Known historically as Timbuctu or Timbuctoo. City in
						present-day Mali, west Africa, and historically a major trading centre. From
						the Renaissance, it acquired mythical status in the western imagination as a
						place of unrivalled opulence and isolation. It was visited by European
						explorers in the early nineteenth century, but remained symbolic of the
						inaccessible outer reaches of the known world (Heffernan 2001:203,
						205-06).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0093" type="settlement_village">
					<placeName type="main">Tlomtla</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Settlement just north of Ntwetwe Pan in present-day
						north-eastern Botswana. It was described by Livingstone as an BaNgwato
						"cattle post" (Schapera 1960a:9).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0094" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Trombeta</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">Portuguese station in north-western Angola in present-day
						Cuanza Norte Province, just west of Golungo Alto and about ninety miles
						inland from Luanda (Schapera 1963,1:144n2).</note>
				</place>

				<!-- MT glossary entry -->
				<place xml:id="sett0095" type="settlement_town">
					<placeName type="main">Zumbo</placeName>
					<note type="editorial">River port at the confluence of the Luangwa and Zambezi
						rivers, and the westernmost town of Mozambique. It was established in 1715
						by the Portuguese and was a destination on the trade route into central
						Africa from the east coast. For a time it was the largest Portuguese town on
						the Zambezi River, but it declined later in the eighteenth century and was
						abandoned in 1836. It was in ruins when Livingstone first visited in the
						1850s, but it was re-established in 1862 (Newitt 1995:202-06, 284).</note>
				</place>

			</listPlace>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
